<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Nevv-Yeares gift for English Catholikes, or A briefe and cleare explication of the new Oath of Allegiance. By E.I. student in Diuinitie; for a more full instruction, and appeasement of the consciences of English Catholikes, concerning the said Oath, then hath beene giuen them by I.E. student in Diuinitie, who compiled the treatise of the prelate and the prince.</title>
            <author>E. I., student in divinitie.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 241 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 106 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03941</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14049</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S119291</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854498</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854498</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19923</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03941)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19923)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 990:10 or 2006:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Nevv-Yeares gift for English Catholikes, or A briefe and cleare explication of the new Oath of Allegiance. By E.I. student in Diuinitie; for a more full instruction, and appeasement of the consciences of English Catholikes, concerning the said Oath, then hath beene giuen them by I.E. student in Diuinitie, who compiled the treatise of the prelate and the prince.</title>
                  <author>E. I., student in divinitie.</author>
                  <author>Preston, Thomas, 1563-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[30], 208, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>W. Stansby],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>With licence of superiours. 1620.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to R. Widdrington (i.e. Thomas Preston). Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Errata on M8v, final leaf.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 2006:1 is an imperfect copy, lacking preliminary leaves and pages 195, 196, 201-204.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in the British Library and Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Kellison, Matthew. --  Right and jurisdiction of the prelate, and the prince --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Oath of allegiance, 1606.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A NEW-YEARES GIFT FOR ENGLISH CATHOLIKES, <hi>OR</hi> A Briefe and cleare <hi>Explication</hi> of the New <hi>Oath</hi> of
<hi>Allegiance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>E. I.</hi> Student in Diuinitie; <hi>For a more full Inſtruction, and appeaſement of the conſciences of</hi> Engliſh Catholikes, <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſaid</hi> OATH, <hi>then hath beene giuen them by</hi> I. E. Student in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, <hi>who compiled the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe of the</hi> PRELATE <hi>and the</hi> PRINCE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1. PET. 2.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Feare God, Honour the King.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>christogram</figDesc>
               <head>I H S.</head>
            </figure>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATTH. 22.</bibl>
               <p>
                  <hi>Render to</hi> Caeſar <hi>the things that are</hi> Caeſars: <hi>and the things that are</hi> Gods <hi>to</hi> God.</p>
            </q>
            <p>With licence of Superiours. 1620.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:2"/>
            <head>A BRIEFE SVMMARIE of what is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in this TREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISE.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt,</hi> An <hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> to Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Catholiks, to examin their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this <hi>New Oath</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: for that by refuſing the ſame if it bee lawfull and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred
<pb facs="tcp:19923:3"/>by good and full authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, (as this Treatiſe conuinceth it to bee) they hazard not only their temporall eſtates, but alſo their eternall ſaluation, by diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beying and reſiſting lawfull au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and the ordinance of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> are ſet downe a <hi>Copie</hi> of the new <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, <hi>The</hi> 13. Prieſts
<hi>Proteſtation;</hi> M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Iohn Colletons Petition</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee confirmeth his former <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation:</hi> and the
<hi>Acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Thomas Greene,</hi> (a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Prieſt of the order of Saint <hi>Benedict,</hi> and <hi>Profeſſour</hi> of Diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie) concerning his opinion of the ſaid <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, with certaine notes and Obſeruations added by the
<hi>Authour</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> &amp;
<hi>Acknowledgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Certaine generall
<hi>Obſeruations</hi> are ſet downe, to
<pb facs="tcp:19923:3"/>know <hi>firſt,</hi> the nature and condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of euery lawfull Oath. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly,</hi> what rules are to be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for the vnderſtanding and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting of the true ſenſe and meaning of any ambiguous word or ſentence contained in any Law, and conſequently in this
<hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance eſtabliſhed by a <hi>Parliamentall</hi> Law.
<hi>Thirdly,</hi> what was the intent and meaning of his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the <hi>Parliament,</hi> in framing and propoſing this new and vnwonted
<hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, deuiſed vpon occaſion of that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted Barbarous and Deuilliſh Conſpiracie of the <hi>Powder-Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours;</hi> to wit, not to make a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, betwixt <hi>Proteſtants</hi> &amp;
<hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> but between <hi>Catholikes</hi> &amp;
<hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> in point of their loyaltie and ciuill obedience, eſpecially concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> authority to practiſe the depoſition of <hi>Princes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19923:4"/>which was the ground of that da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nable
<hi>Powder-Treaſon. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> to know vpon what aſſured grounds the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depoſe</hi> Princes, or to
<hi>practiſe</hi> their depoſition, may not only be bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly denyed, but alſo abiured as <hi>damnable; impious,</hi> and <hi>hereticall:</hi> to wit, for that it is a controuerſie among learned Catholikes, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to depriue Princes or no: and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that it is open iniuſtice in the <hi>Pope;</hi> and manifeſt Treaſon in the Subiect to attempt the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing of any Soueraigne
<hi>Prince,</hi> by vertue of this pretended au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie and clayme, ſo long as this Controuerſie remayneth a foot, and is not decided by a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Iudge, and who without all doubt and Controuerſie is known ſo to bee.
<hi>Fiftly, page</hi> 64. it is ſhewed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is no lawfull
<pb facs="tcp:19923:4"/>Iudge to end and decide this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie concerning his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded authoritie to depriue Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Princes;</hi> for that it is a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among Learned Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and approued by very many famous <hi>Prelates, Cardinals,</hi> and <hi>Doctours</hi> cited by the
<hi>Authour,</hi> that the <hi>Pope,</hi> without the conſent and approbation of a lawfull and vndoubted generall <hi>Councell,</hi> hath not authoritie to decide, deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, or define any doctrinal que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion at all, and much leſſe in his owne particular cauſe, as is this Controuerſie betwixt Him and Chriſtian <hi>Princes:</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although hee ſhould take vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him to decide this queſtion, yet the Controuerſie would ſtill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne a foote, and bee vndecided as it was before.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> In the <hi>first</hi> eight Chapters it is cleerly ſhewed, that
<pb facs="tcp:19923:5"/>there is not any one Clauſe of the <hi>Oath,</hi> which wanteth either <hi>Veritie, Iuſtice,</hi> or Iudgement: and that therefore Engliſh Catholikes not only may lawfully, but alſo are bound in conſcience to take it, when they are vrged thereunto by the
<hi>Magiſtrate,</hi> whom the <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>State</hi> hath appointed to ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſame: otherwiſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt lawfull authoritie, and the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God, which <hi>whoſoeuer reſiſt purchaſe to themſelues dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Rom.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> In the <hi>ninth</hi> and laſt Chapter are cleerly anſwered the <hi>Popes</hi> declaratiue <hi>Breues,</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding Engliſh Catholikes to take the <hi>Oath, for that it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth many things, which are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly repugnant to faith and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> which <hi>Breues</hi> therefore doe not make, but only ſuppoſe the
<hi>Oath</hi> to bee vnlawfull, as contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it ſome manifeſt falſhood
<pb facs="tcp:19923:5"/>or iniuſtice: and therefore, abſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cting from the
<hi>Popes Breues,</hi> ſome particular clauſe of the <hi>Oath</hi> muſt be proued to be vnlawfull, which this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> doth euidently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince to bee vntrue. And <hi>firſt</hi> in this Chapter it is ſhewed, that it is no diſobedience or irreuerence, not to obey. ſuch
<hi>declaratiue Breues,</hi> ſeeing that they are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon one of theſe <hi>two</hi> (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vpon both) falſe ſuppoſitions: to wit, that either the doctrine for the <hi>Popes</hi> power to depriue
<hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> is certaine, of Faith, and out of all Controuerſie, and the contrarie not approued by learned Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, which <hi>ſuppoſition</hi> is manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe: or elſe that the <hi>Popes</hi> power to
<hi>excommunicate,</hi> to bind and looſe, and to abſolue from Oaths in general, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly his Spirituall authoritie is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed in the Oath, which alſo is no
<pb facs="tcp:19923:6"/>leſſe vntrue: and that therefore Engliſh Catholikes not only may lawfully and without any diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience or irreuerence, but alſo are bound in conſcience not to obey them, conſidering that they are ſo preiudiciall to themſelues, ſo ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous to the <hi>Catholike Roman Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> which they profeſſe, and ſo iniurious to their <hi>Soueraign Prince,</hi> who, being in reall poſſeſſion of his Kingdome, cannot vpon any controuerſed Title or Power with out open iniuſtice bee diſpoſſeſſed thereof.
<hi>Secondly,</hi> it is ſhewed, that albeit diuers <hi>Popes</hi> haue ſince the time of Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the VII. challenged to themſelues authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to depriue <hi>Soueraigne Princes,</hi> yet they cannot bee truly ſaid, to haue beene for any little time in poſſeſſion of this their pretended authoritie, right and clayme: for that they haue euer beene reſiſted
<pb facs="tcp:19923:6"/>and contradicted by Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> and
<hi>Subiects</hi> in this their pretended right and clayme, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, to poſſeſſe authoritie, right, or clayme to any thing, it is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, according to the approued do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Molina,</hi> and
<hi>Leſsius</hi> both Ieſuites, and of all Diuines and Lawyers, that it bee without reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and contradiction of the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe part: but one may truly and really poſſeſſe corporall things, as Lands, Houſes, Kingdomes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee, that pretendeth to haue right to the ſame, yea and perchance hath true right there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, contradict and reſiſt neuer ſo much. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is ſhewed, that howſoeuer any man may vnder pretence of following a <hi>probable</hi> opinion, thinke himſelfe excuſed in conſcience and in the ſight of God (wherewith <hi>Princes</hi> in their Tribunals doe not meddle, but
<pb facs="tcp:19923:7"/>leaue mens conſciences to the iudgement of God, the only ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher of all mens hearts) by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring with the <hi>Pope</hi> to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing and diſpoſſeſſing of his So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne <hi>Prince;</hi> yet conſidering that it is not only <hi>probable,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo moſt
<hi>certaine,</hi> that hee is excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in conſcience and in the ſight of God, by defending his <hi>Prince</hi> againſt ſuch damnable, and tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous practiſes, which are groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>at the most</hi> vpon a
<hi>probable</hi> power, title, and clayme, and alſo that hee cannot bee excuſed from formall Treaſon in the externall Court, both Eccleſiaſticall and Secular of his <hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> who is in actuall poſſeſſion of his Kingdome, &amp; ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not without open iniuſtice be diſpoſſeſſed vpon any vncertayne and controuerſed power, clayme, or title though it were neuer ſo probable; it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb facs="tcp:19923:7"/>that thoſe Subiects might iuſtly bee accounted worſe then mad, that would in ſuch damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and trayterous practiſes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curre with the <hi>Pope</hi> to the diſpoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing of their
<hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> vnder pretence of a power, or ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, which, euen in ſpeculation, and abſtracting from practiſe, can be at the moſt but probable.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> are ſet downe, <hi>Firſt,</hi> the
<hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> or the <hi>first Article</hi> of the lower Houſe of <hi>Parliament,</hi> wherein of two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Deputies</hi> for the third Eſtates were but ſix <hi>Protestants: Secondly,</hi> two
<hi>Arrests</hi> or <hi>Decrees</hi> of the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of
<hi>Paris,</hi> forbidding vnder paine of Treaſon Cardinall
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines</hi> Booke againſt <hi>Barckley,</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> Booke againſt our Kings <hi>Maieſties</hi> Premonition, and
<hi>third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> another <hi>Decree</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> ordayning likewiſe that
<pb facs="tcp:19923:8"/>no perſon of what qualitie or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſoeuer doe teach the ſaid doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> Princes as
<hi>problematicall</hi> or probable. All which <hi>Decrees</hi> are proued to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to truth and iuſtice, and that <hi>Christian Princes,</hi> by vertue of their temporall power, haue good and full authoritie, both to forbid the teaching, maintayning, and publiſhing of all vnneceſſarie doctrines &amp; poſitions, be they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo probable, as the teaching and publiſhing of the ſame ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to the ſubuerſion of States-and to the diſturbance of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like peace in the Ciuill Common, wealth, and is dangerous to the Crownes and liues of temporall Princes; and alſo to puniſh with temporall puniſhments the teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, maintayners, and publiſhers of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="admonition">
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:8"/>
            <head>AN ADMONITION TO ENGLISH Catholikes.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſider</hi> with your ſelues, <hi>(Deare Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men)</hi> how greatly this <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> concerneth you all, not only in your temporall ſtates and libertie, which in conſcience you are bound to regard, and not wilfully
<pb facs="tcp:19923:9"/>to caſt away, (and the more if you haue a charge of Wife and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, for whom in nature you are obliged to prouide) but chiefly in your ſoules health, which aboue all temporall things in this World you are bound to preferre. <hi>For what doth it profit a man, if hee gaine the whole World, and ſuſtaine the damage of his ſoule?</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.</note> Now if this <hi>new Oath</hi> bee truely an <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>temporall Allegiance, and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred by lawfull authoritie,</hi> (as this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> doth conuince it to bee) doubtleſſe you incurre the danger of eternall damnation if you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe it, by diſobeying and reſiſting the iuſt commandement of lawfull authoritie, and the Ordinance of Almightie God, from whom all power and authoritie doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. <hi>For he that reſiſteth power</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.</note> (or authoritie) <hi>reſiſteth the Ordinance of God; And they that reſiſt pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe
<pb facs="tcp:19923:9"/>to themſelues damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore, it behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth you that are
<hi>Lay-men,</hi> to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine diligently this matter, and not to be led hoodwinkd into the pit both of ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall miſerie, eſpecially by blinde and ignorant guides, who neither vnderſtand, nor are deſirous to know the true grounds of this im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Controuerſie, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can hardly bee drawne for the informing of your conſciences to deſcend with you in particular to the examination of the lawfulnes, or vnlawfulneſſe of euery Branch of this <hi>Oath,</hi> which many of them, (I ſpeak with griefe, and not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Booke) haue not ſo much as euer read, but to cloake their igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance vnder colour of Zeale and Deuotion, without any further examining, they only cry out to you in general termes, The
<hi>Church,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:19923:10"/>the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Rocke</hi> is that, which good Catholikes ought to cleaue vnto; not knowing themſelues, what authoritie is ſpirituall and due to the <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> and what authoritie is temporall and due to temporall <hi>Princes,</hi> and that the
<hi>Pope</hi> is not the <hi>Church,</hi> but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the chiefe member thereof; and that the <hi>Popes</hi> opinion, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently his <hi>Declaratiue Breues,</hi> when they are grounded either vpon falſe ſuppoſitions, or elſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon his opinion, are not the <hi>Rocke,</hi> whereon Catholikes ought to build their eternall ſaluation; and <hi>laſtly,</hi> not conſidering, that many times when <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> haue beene and ſhall bee in op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, the <hi>Popes</hi> both haue bin, may lawfully bee, and alſo ought to bee reſiſted. As the
<hi>reſiſtance,</hi> which <hi>Philip</hi> the Faire made to Pope
<hi>Boniface</hi> the VIII. (who
<pb facs="tcp:19923:10"/>
               <hi>depriued</hi> the ſaid <hi>King,</hi> &amp; gaue his Kingdome to
<note n="a" place="margin">Genebrard. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ad annum</hi> 1294.</note> 
               <hi>Albertus</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and declared, that
<hi>he accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them for Heretikes, who did not beleeue that the ſaid King was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to him in Spiritualls and Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls</hi>)
<note n="b" place="margin">Vignerius <hi>ad annum.</hi>
               </note> and the reſiſtance, which <hi>Lewis</hi> the XII. made to Pope <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the II. (by whom he was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued, and his Kingdome
<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <p>Genebrard. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ad annum</hi> 1503.</p>
                  <p>Guicciardin. <hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>hiſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Richeome <hi>in Apoleget. cap.</hi> 24 25.</p>
                  <p>See <hi>Brerely</hi> in the Preface of his <hi>Protestants Apologie, &amp;c. Sec.</hi> 20. 21. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> giuen in pray to any that could take it) is well commended by <hi>Lewis Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheome</hi> Prouinciall of the <hi>Ieſuites,</hi> and propoſed for an example to be imitated; yea and he ſheweth, that whenſoeuer any <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<hi>Rome</hi> ſhould offend the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> as thoſe
<hi>Kings</hi> were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended by thoſe <hi>Biſhops,</hi> the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites in ſuch an occaſion would doe that which good Clergie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, and good
<hi>French-men</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſaid King <hi>Philip,</hi> and
<hi>Lewis</hi> did in thoſe times,
<pb facs="tcp:19923:11"/>who defended their rights againſt thoſe Popes,
<hi>Boniface</hi> and <hi>Iulius,</hi> without any irreuerence to the <hi>Sea Apostolike.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I beſeech you, <hi>(Deare Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-men)</hi> to take heed vpon what guides you relye for the directing of your ſoules in theſe important affaires, and remember that
<hi>Admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition</hi> of our <hi>Sauiour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
15.</note> 
               <hi>Blinde they are, and guides of the blinde. And if the blinde be guide to the blinde, both fall into the ditch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Secondly,</hi> you that are <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and haue taken vpon you to guide others in the way to ſaluation, and ought <hi>to be alwayes readie to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie euery one that asketh you a reaſon of that</hi> faith <hi>which is in you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi>
3</note> if you thinke in your conſciences the <hi>Oath</hi> to bee
<hi>lawfull, and miniſtred by good and full authoritie,</hi> you ought to take great heede, that your ſoules bee not defiled, nor
<pb facs="tcp:19923:11"/>your conſciences ſtayned with ſome worldly reſpect, and that neither hope of gaine or prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, nor feare of want or diſgrace keepe you backe from giuing war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thoſe, whom you are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to guide, direct, and inſtruct, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the danger, which they are like to fall into by reſiſting the Ordinance of God, if they refuſe the
<hi>Oath,</hi> when it is tendred them by <hi>lawfull authoritie;</hi> leſt that you foreſeeing their danger, and not crying out to them to take heede, be not only partakers of their ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall harme, but doe alſo coope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to their temporall ruine, and ſo haue cauſe to rue your ſilence, and to cry out your ſelues when it is too late, <hi>Vae mihi quia tacui, Woe is mee becauſe I haue held my peace.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi>
6.</note> But if perchance any of you, who in your conſciences thinke the
<pb facs="tcp:19923:12"/>
               <hi>Oath</hi> to be lawfull, <hi>ſhould</hi> for ſome worldly reſpect, (which God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) cry out againſt the takers or approouers thereof, this were not only to ſin moſt damnably againſt your owne conſciences, but alſo in ſome ſort againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> and to impugne that, which in your ſoules and conſciences you thinke, and acknowledge to bee true, which how hardly it is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuen
<hi>either in this World, or the next,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi>
12.</note> our <hi>Sauiour</hi> himſelfe doth expreſly witneſſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> that in their conſciences thinke the <hi>Oath</hi> to be <hi>vnlawfull,</hi> and thereupon do not only giue warning to thoſe, whom they haue taken vpon them to guide and direct, to take heede, and beware of the ſpirituall dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, which they thinke will ariſe by taking the ſame, but alſo in
<pb facs="tcp:19923:12"/>their zeale do cry out againſt their Catholike Brethren, who either doe take the <hi>Oath,</hi> or thinke it to be lawfull, as
<hi>Apoſtates</hi> from the <hi>Catholike</hi> Faith and Religion, and diſobedient children to the Pope and <hi>Church,</hi> (giuing the like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to others to cry out againſt them, as <hi>Apoſtates</hi> from their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Allegiance, and diſobedient &amp; diſloyall Subiects to their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall Prince) it behoueth them moſt of all to looke to themſelues, and, (according to the admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> vpon occaſion of relating the fearefull death of Pope
<hi>Innocentius</hi> the III. giueth to Prelates and Paſtours<note place="margin">Bellar. <hi>de ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu, columbae, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 9.</note>) to examine all the ſecrets of their conſciences moſt exactly, leſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance it bee erroneous, albeit to them it ſeeme to be ſound &amp; iuſt: and that their zeale (albeit to them
<pb facs="tcp:19923:13"/>ſelues ſeeme pure, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to knowledge) bee not blind, and grounded vpon wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or culpable ignorance, like that, which the <hi>Iewes</hi> had in cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifying our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> and Saint
<hi>Paul,</hi> (when he was <hi>Saul</hi>) in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting his Diſciples, who thought thereby to doe <hi>God</hi> great ſeruice.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And truly if their <hi>Zeale</hi> were hurtfull to none but to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they would doubtleſſe be the more excuſable; but conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring how preiudiciall it is both to his <hi>Maiesties</hi> honour, and alſo to his temporall <hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> how ſcandalous it is to
<hi>Catholicke</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and how iniurious it is to their
<hi>Catholike</hi> brethren, not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour to themſelues in vertue and learning (whom they ſeeke to diſgrace, and to make odious to all
<pb facs="tcp:19923:13"/>
               <hi>Catholickes,</hi> epecially to their benefactors and friends, and ſo by taking from them their good names and maintenance, to bring them into extreame want and miſerie, and, as much as in them lyeth, into manifeſt deſperation (for which they are one day to render a moſt ſtrict account) they haue great cauſe to examine their conſciences narrowly, and carefully to conſider, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what aſſured grounds they can excuſe themſelues at the dreadfull day of Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for taking ſuch ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, iniurious, and vnchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table courſes, both againſt their
<hi>Soueraigne Prince,</hi> (whom next vnder God they are bound to honour and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey in temporals) and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb facs="tcp:19923:14"/>their <hi>Catholicke</hi> bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, who not onely are as learned and religious as them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, but alſo haue exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned this important controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, and all the danger both ſpirituall and temporall that dependeth thereon, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently, if not farre more, then they themſelues haue done.</p>
            <p n="6">6. To the end therefore that all of you, (my <hi>deare Countrimen</hi>) may examine your conſciences in this poynt of the
<hi>Oath,</hi> more eaſily and eactly, and be more fully in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed therein, then you haue beene by <hi>I. E.</hi> the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of the
<hi>Prelate</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> (who, if the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rumour bee true, will heare ſhortly with ſhame e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough
<pb facs="tcp:19923:14"/>what goodly <hi>Inſtruct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ions</hi> he hath giuen you) I haue out of <hi>Roger Widdringtons</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe doctrine and grounds col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected this little <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> which for that it was finiſhed this firſt day of the yeare, I am bould to preſent it to your Charities for a <hi>New-yeares-gift,</hi> as a ſmall token of the great deſire I haue both of your ſpirituall and temporall welfare. And my onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt is, that you will bee plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to read it, as I hope you will, it beeing neither ſo prolixe, but that in ſome few houres you may mane it ouer, nor ſo obſcure, but that any man of meane ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacitie may vnderſtand it, and after you haue read it, to iudge thereof accordingly. And if I ſhall heare, that you haue rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped
<pb facs="tcp:19923:15"/>any benefit thereby, I ſhall thinke my paines exceeding well beſtowed; but howſoeuer, I ſhall not thinke my labour loſt by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing you this euident token of my loue: for that the loue and dutie I owe to my <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Countrie,</hi> to the
<hi>Catholicke</hi> Religion, and to you my deare <hi>Catholick</hi> brethren, and aboue all to <hi>God</hi> Almightie, the <hi>Author</hi> of all
<hi>truth,</hi> yea <hi>truth</hi> it ſelfe, and <hi>who will</hi> in due time <hi>render to euerie man according to his workes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.</note> hath, for the defence of a
<hi>neceſſarie truth,</hi> moued mee to take this paines. And ſo with my beſt wiſhes, I bid you heartily <hi>farewell,</hi> hoping that you will bee wiſe, and not be tranſported with a blind and intemperate zeale to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Prelate,</hi> but that you will bee carefull <hi>to feare God,</hi> to <hi>honour the King,</hi> and without
<pb facs="tcp:19923:15"/>all partialitie, <hi>to render to</hi> God
<hi>and</hi> Caeſar (and conſequently to Popes <hi>and</hi> Princes)
<hi>that which is their due.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:16"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19923:16"/>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>A Copie of the new <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> deuided into eight <hi>Branches</hi> as it is in this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> explay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I A.B. doe truely and ſincerely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, profeſſe, teſtifie and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare in my conſcience before God and the World, That our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> is lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, and of all other his Maieſties Dominions and Countries.</p>
               <p n="2">2. And that the Pope neither of himſelfe, nor by any authoritie of the Church, or See of Rome, or by any other meanes which any other hath any Power or Authoritie to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe any of his Maieſties Kingdomes, or Dominions, or to authorize any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prince to inuade or annoy Him or his Countries, or to diſcharge any of his Subiects of their Allegiance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Maieſtie, or to giue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe or leaue to any of them to beare Armes, rayſe Tumults, or to offer any
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19923:17"/>Violence, or hurt to his Maiſties Royall Perſon, State, or Gouernment, or to any of his Maieſties Subiects within his Maieſties Dominions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Alſo, I doe ſweare from my heart, that notwithſtanding any Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or Sentence of Excommunication, or Depriuation made or granted, or to be made or granted by the Pope or his Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, or by any Authoritie deriued or to be deriued from him, or his See againſt the ſaid King, his Heires or Succeſſours, or any abſolution of the ſaid Subiects from their Obedience, I will beare Faith and true Allegiance to his Maieſtie, his Heires and Succeſſours, and him and them will defend to the vttermoſt of my power, against all Conſpiracies and At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts whatſoeuer, which ſhall be made againſt His, or their Perſons, their Crown and Dignitie, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, and will doe my beſt endeuour to diſcloſe and make knowne vnto his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, his Heires and Succeſſours, all Treaſons and Trayterous Conſpiracies, which I ſhall know or heare of to bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him or any of them.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19923:17"/>4. And I doe further ſweare, That I doe from my heart abhorre, deteſt and abiure, as impious and hereticall, this damnable doctrine, and poſition, That Princes which bee excommunicated or depriued by the Pope may be depoſed or murthered by their Subiects, or any other whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p n="5">5. And I doe beleeue, and in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence am reſolued, that neither the Pope, nor any perſon whatſoeuer hath power to abſolue mee of this Oath, or any part thereof.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Which I acknowledge by good and full authoritie to bee lawfully miniſtred vnto me, and doe renounce all Pardons and Diſpenſations to the contrarie.</p>
               <p n="7">7. And all theſe things I doe plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely acknowledge and ſweare, according to theſe expreſſe words by mee ſpoken, and according to the plaine and common ſenſe and vnderſtanding of the ſame words without any Equiuocation, or mentall euaſion, or ſecret reſeruation whatſoeuer.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And I doe make this recognition and acknowledgement heartily, willingly and truly vpon the true Faith of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. So helpe me God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="protestation">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19923:18"/>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>A Copie of the <hi>Protestation,</hi> which
<hi>thirteene</hi> Reuerend Prieſts made of their <hi>Allegiance</hi> to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> by a publike Inſtrument the laſt day of
<hi>Ianuary</hi> 1602. in the laſt yeere of her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iesties</hi> Reigne.</head>
                  <p>WHereas it hath pleaſed our Dread <hi>Soueraigne Ladie</hi> to take ſome notice of the Faith, and Loyaltie of vs Her naturall borne Subiects <hi>Secular Prieſts</hi> (as it appeareth in the late
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation</hi>) and of her <hi>Princelike</hi> cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie hath giuen a ſufficient earneſt of ſome mercifull fauour towards vs (being all ſubiect by the Lawes of the Realme to death by our returne into the Countrie after our taking the Order of Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood ſince the firſt yeere of Her
<hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> Reigne) and only demandeth of vs a true profeſſion of our <hi>Allegiance,</hi> ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to bee aſſured of our fidelitie to Her
<hi>Maieſties</hi> Perſon, Crowne, Eſtate and Dignitie, <hi>Wee,</hi> whoſe names are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>written, in moſt humble wiſe proſtrate at
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19923:18"/>Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> feet doe acknowledge our ſelues infinitely bound vnto Her <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie</hi> therefore, and are moſt willing to giue ſuch aſſurance and ſatisfaction in this point, as any Catholike <hi>Prieſts</hi> can or ought to giue vnto their <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Firſt,</hi> therefore wee acknowledge, and confeſſe the <hi>Queenes Maieſtie</hi> to haue as full Authority, Power and Soueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ouer vs, and ouer all the Subiects of the Realme, as any Her
<hi>Highneſſe</hi> Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours euer had: And further we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test, that we are most willing and readie to obey Her in all Caſes and Respects as farre forth, as cuer Christian Priests within this Realme, or in any other Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Countrie were bound by the Law of God and Chriſtian Religion to obey their Temporall <hi>Princes;</hi> as to pay Tribute, and all other Regall Duties vnto Her <hi>Highneſſe,</hi> and to obey Her Lawes and Magistrates in all Ciuill Cauſes, to pray vnto God for Her prosperous and peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Reigne in this life according to his bleſſed will and that ſhee may hereafter attaine euerlaſting bliſſe in the Life to come. And this our acknowledgement
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19923:19"/>wee thinke to bee ſo grounded vpon the Word of <hi>GOD,</hi> as that no Authoritie. no Cauſe, or pretence of Cauſe can or ought (vpon any occaſion) be a ſufficient Warrant more vnto vs then to any Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant to diſobey Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> in any Ciuill or Temporall matter.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> whereas for theſe many yeeres paſt diuers Conſpiracies againſt her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Perſon and Eſtate, and ſundrie forcible attempts, for inuading and conquering her Dominions, haue bin made vnder we knew not what pretences and intendments of reſtoring Catholike Religion by the ſword (a courſe moſt ſtrange in the World, and vndertaken peculiarly and ſolely against Her <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie,</hi> and Her Kingdomes among other Princes departed from the Religion and Obedience of the <hi>See Apoſtolike</hi> (no leſſe then ſhe) by reaſon of which violent Enterprizes, her <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> otherwiſe of ſingular clemencie toward Her Subiects, hath beene greatly mooued to ordayne, and execute ſeuerer Lawes againſt Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes (which by reaſon of their vnion with the <hi>See Apoſtolike</hi> in Faith and Religion, were eaſily ſupp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſed to fauour
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19923:19"/>theſe Conſpiracies and Inuaſions) then perhaps had euer bin enacted or thought vpon, if ſuch Hoſtilitie and Warres had neuer beene vndertaken; <hi>We,</hi> to aſſure Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of our faithfull Loyaltie alſo in this particular cauſe doe ſincerely proteſt, and by this our publike fact make knowne to all the Chriſtian World, That in theſe caſes of Conſpiracies, of practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing Her
<hi>Maieſties</hi> death, of Inuaſions, and of whatſoeuer forcible Attempts, which hereafter may be made by any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>Prelate, Prince</hi> or <hi>Potentate,</hi> whoſoeuer either ioyntly or ſeuerally for the diſturbance or ſubuerſion of Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Perſon, Estate, Realmes, or Dominions, vnder colour, ſhew, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or intendment of reſtoring the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Romane Religion in <hi>England,</hi> or <hi>Ireland, We</hi> will defend Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Perſon, Eſtate, Realmes and Dominions from all ſuch forcible and violent aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ults and iniuries. And moreouer <hi>Wee</hi> will not only our ſelues detect and reueale any Conſpiracies or Plots which we ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand to bee vndertaken by any <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, Prince,</hi> or
<hi>Potentate</hi> against Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Perſon or Dominions for any
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19923:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:19923:20"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:19923:21"/>cauſe whatſoeuer as is before expreſſed, and likewiſe to the vttermoſt of our power reſiſt them, but alſo will earnely perſwade, as much as in vs lyeth, all Catholikes to doe the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thirdly,</hi> if vpon any <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> denounced or to bee denounced againſt Her <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> or vpon any ſuch Conspiracies, Inuaſions or forcible At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts to be made as are before expreſſed the <hi>Pope</hi> ſhould alſo excommunicate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one borne within Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Dominions that would forſake the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid defence of Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and Her Realmes, and take part with ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirators, or Inuaders in theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther like Caſes, wee in theſe and all ſuch like Caſes doe thinke our ſelues, and all the Lay-Catholikes borne within Her <hi>Maieſties</hi> Dominions not bound in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to obey this or any ſuch like Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, but will defend our
<hi>Prince</hi> and Countrie, accounting it our duties ſo to doe, and that notwithſtanding any <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie,</hi> or any <hi>Excommunication whatſoeuer</hi> either denounced or to bee denounced as is aforeſaid, to yeild vnto Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> all obedience in Temporall Cauſes.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19923:21"/>And becauſe nothing is more certaine, then that whilſt we endeuor to aſſure Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of our dutifull Affection and Allegiance by this our Chriſtian and ſincere
<hi>Proteſtation,</hi> there will not want who will condemne and miſconſtrue our lawfull Fact, yea, and by many finiſter ſuggeſtions and calumnies diſcredit our doings with the Chriſtian World, but chiefly with the <hi>Popes Holineſſe</hi> to the greateſt preiudice and harme of our good names and perſons that may be, vnleſſe maturely wee preuent their endeuours herein, <hi>Wee</hi> moſt humbly beſeech Her
<hi>Maieſtie,</hi> that in this our recognizing and yeilding
<hi>Caeſars</hi> due vnto Her, wee may alſo by Her <hi>Gracious</hi> leaue be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, for auoyding Obloquie and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, make knowne by like publike Act, that by yeilding Her right vnto Her, wee depart from no bond of that Chriſtian Dutie which we owe vnto our Supreme ſpirituall Paſtour.</p>
                  <p>And therefore wee acknowledge and confeſſe the
<hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to be the Succeſſour of <hi>Saint Peter</hi> in that See, and to haue as ample and no more Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie or Iuriſdiction ouer vs and other
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19923:22"/>Chriſtians, then had that Apoſtle by the gift and commiſſion of <hi>Chriſt</hi> our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, and that
<hi>Wee</hi> will obey him ſo farre forth as we are bound by the Lawes of God to doe, which we doubt not but will ſtand well with performance of our Duty to our Temporall <hi>Prince</hi> in ſuch ſort as we haue before profeſſed. For as we are moſt ready to ſpend our bloud in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of Her <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and our Country, ſo we will rather loſe our liues then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringe the lawfull authoritie of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Catholike Church.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <list>
                           <item>William Biſhop.</item>
                           <item>Iohn Colleton.</item>
                           <item>Iohn Muſh.</item>
                           <item>Robert Charnocke.</item>
                           <item>Iohn Boſſeuile.</item>
                           <item>Anthonie Hebborne.</item>
                           <item>Roger Cadwallader.</item>
                           <item>Robert Drury.</item>
                           <item>Anthony Champney.</item>
                           <item>Iohn Iackſon.</item>
                           <item>Francis Barneby.</item>
                           <item>Oſwald Needham.</item>
                           <item>Richard Button.</item>
                        </list>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:19923:22"/>
                  <p>This <hi>Protestation</hi> of the <hi>thirteene Catholike Prieſts</hi> (to which a great number more would haue ſubſcribed, if the Articles which thoſe Prieſtes gaue vp to the State, had beene retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them backe, but ſome few dayes before the end of the time prefixed to them by the <hi>Proclamation,</hi> to make known to the State their Allegiance) was the ground and foundation from whence the <hi>Parliament</hi> (as the Lord Archbiſhop of Canterburie D. <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croft</hi> told a friend of mine) framed the forme of this <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> as agreeable to the doctrine, which any Catholike ſubiect, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the grounds of true Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion, might lawfully main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, to make thereby a <hi>true diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on not betweene Proteſtants, and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, but betweene ciuilly obedient Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and in all other things good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, and ſuch other Catholikes as in their hearts maintained the like violent bloodie maximes that the Powder-Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours did.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See
<hi>beneath</hi> in the <hi>third</hi> Obſeruation.</note> And doubtleſſe, whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer will compare the <hi>new Oath,</hi> and their
<hi>Proteſtation</hi> together, and doe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19923:23"/>withall conſider, that Queene
<hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth</hi> was long before that time depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of all <hi>Regall power, authoritie, dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi> and <hi>Iuriſdiction</hi> by the
<hi>Bull</hi> of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> and alſo obſerue vpon what aſſured grounds and principles thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> could lawfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge her <hi>Maieſty</hi> to <hi>haue as full Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, Power and Soueraignty ouer them and all the Subiects of this Realme, as any Her Predeceſſours euer had,</hi> and alſo could lawfully promiſe, <hi>that they would yeild to Her</hi> Maieſtie all <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in Temporall Cauſes, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any authority, or any Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation whatſoeuer denounced or to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt Her</hi> Maieſtie,
<hi>or Her Subiects, as is aforeſaid;</hi> he will cleerly perceiue, that their <hi>Proteſtation</hi> is all one in effect and ſubſtance with this
<hi>new Oath</hi> of Allegiance, and that the only difference betwixt them is, that in the <hi>Oath</hi> the <hi>Popes</hi> authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King, &amp;c. is expreſly and in plaine wordes denyed, and in their
<hi>Proteſtation</hi> the deniall thereof is only couertly, vertually, and by a neceſſary conſequence implyed; notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19923:23"/>all the euaſions, tergiuerſations, turnings, windings, ſayings and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayings, which any one of theſe Prieſts (if for ſome worldly reſpect or other motiue hee ſhould now repent him of what he had done) could to excuſe himſelfe from Periurie, poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly vſe or inuent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>
                  <hi>A Copie</hi> of Maſter <hi>Iohn Colletons</hi> Petition to the Lord <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Canterburies Grace,</hi> wherein hee confirmeth his former <hi>Proteſtation,</hi> many yeeres after the <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> was eſtabliſhed.</head>
               <p>IF your <hi>Grace</hi> and the <hi>State</hi> ſaw the preſent affections of my heart, and were pleaſed to looke on my carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges past, neyther trouble ſome, or vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpectiue, I hope the fauour I am to deſire, albeit it may ſeeme extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, yet the ſame could not altogether be deemed vnworthily extended. The <hi>vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntarie</hi> and <hi>free Recognition</hi> I made in the late <hi>Queenes</hi> Reigne as it then ſufficed, and is now extant in print, ſo
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19923:24"/>doth it ſtill witneſſe the readineſſe of my <hi>profeſſed Allegiance</hi> in all Secular and Ciuill affaires. Neither haue I bin, am now, or by Gods grace euer ſhall be otherwiſe affected, then in like ſort to acknowledge his
<hi>Maieſtie</hi> that now gouerneth, for my lawfull Dread
<hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne,</hi> obey in all Politicall admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration, and defend his ſacred Perſon, Crowne, and Dominions to the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most of my power against all enemies <hi>of what place and calling ſoeuer.</hi> The commiſeration I most humbly beſeech your <hi>Grace</hi> to take of my aged yeeres, accompanied with ſundrie infirmities, is, to ſtand ſo good Lord vnto me, as to enlarge me vpon ſufficient ſecuritie for my appearance before your
<hi>Honour,</hi> at the time your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhall thinke fit to aſſigne, An euident meane of lengthing my life, beſide the eaſing of the heauy charge my impriſonment im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth. I would very gladly haue beene herein my owne <hi>Sollicitour</hi> in perſon, but that I hold the boldneſſe greater in reſpect of my diſgracefull ſtate, then I durst to aduenture on without your
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19923:24"/>
                  <hi>Lordſhips</hi> good liking thereunto first vnderstood.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>26. of <hi>March,</hi>
1610.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your <hi>Graces</hi> moſt ſuppliant Petitioner, IOHN COLLETON.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="declaration">
               <head>A <hi>Copie</hi> of the <hi>Declaration</hi> and
<hi>Acknowledgement</hi> which Maſter <hi>Iames Houghton,</hi> alias
<hi>Thomas Green,</hi> a Religious Prieſt of the Order of Saint
<hi>Benedict,</hi> and profeſſour of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ninitie, made vnder his owne hand writing to the <hi>Lord</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> the firſt of
<hi>Nouember,</hi> 1619. tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching his opinion of the Oath of Allegiance.</head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Iames Houghton,</hi> alias, <hi>Thomas Green,</hi> his opinion touching the Oath of Allegiance.</head>
                  <p n="1">1 <hi>FIrſt,</hi> I do ingenuouſly confeſſe, that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> had very iust cauſe, by occaſion of that moſt trecherous plot of the <hi>Gunpowder-Treaſon,</hi> to propoſe to all

<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19923:25"/>his Subiects Engliſh Catholikes
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Oath</hi> of ciuill fidelitie and obedience due vnto <hi>Kings</hi> both by the Lawes of God and Nature, and that in most ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall and peremptory termes, for try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of their fidelity and loyalty to H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <hi>Maieſtie</hi> their true <hi>Soueraigne</hi> Lord and King.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it ſeemeth to me that the Church had done her dutie, if ſhe had ſhewed her diſlike of that odious practice of the <hi>Gun-powder-Treaſon,</hi> by ſome publike declaration in deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof, both for his <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction, and for the confirmation of his <hi>Catholike</hi> Subiects in their fidelity and allegiance vnto Him.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> I doe ingenuouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, that to me it ſeemeth most true, that the doctrine, which approueth murthering of Kings by their owne Subiects or any elſe, is both
<hi>damnable</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> yea, though it be <hi>in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu Apoſtaſiae a fide aut Infidelitatis, in caſe of Apoſtaſie from faith, or of Infidelitie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> I do ingenuouſly grant, that it ſeemeth to mee in my priuate
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19923:25"/>iudgement, that there is nothing in the
<hi>Oath,</hi> but that it may, according to <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Widdrington</hi> his Gloſſe and Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, be lawfully taken of Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes His
<hi>Maieſties</hi> Subiects, though ſome both Learned and Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious hold the contrarie.</p>
                  <p>Yet I finde three <hi>ſcruples</hi> concerning the
<hi>Oath,</hi> which cauſe mee to entreate ſome further time of conſideration and conference for my better ſatisfaction.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> is, concerning the <hi>Romane Councell</hi> vnder <hi>Gregorie</hi> the ſeuenth, and the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Lateran, ſub in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentio tertio,</hi> whether they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined any thing in this point.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Second</hi> is, whether it bee fit for mee to oppoſe my priuate iudgement to two <hi>Breues</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> that ſay in the <hi>Oath</hi> there bee many things contrarie to faith and ſaluation, though they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe not any thing in particular.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Third</hi> is, whether by taking the <hi>Oath</hi> I ſhall not giue ſcandall to many learned Priests and Catholikes, who refuſe it, and for refuſall hazard their liues and Estates.</p>
                  <p>In regard whereof I humbly pray
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19923:26"/>further reſpite, for better conſideration and confererence: And in the meane time I <hi>promiſe</hi> and <hi>vow</hi> to be a true &amp; faithfull Sabiect to His
<hi>Maieſtie</hi> &amp; His Succeſſours during my life, and ſo am fully reſolued to continue, notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any <hi>Sentence</hi> from the
<hi>Pope what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer</hi> of <hi>Excommunication, Depoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> or
<hi>Abſolution</hi> of his <hi>Maieſties</hi> Subiects from their naturall obedience to Him, and his Heires, &amp;c. for whom I most affectionately pray God of his infinite mercie, ſpecially to direct and aſſist in all their actions and procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Thomas GREENE.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <p>But as touching the three ſcruples mentioned in the
<hi>fourth Article,</hi> it is to bee obſerued, that all of them are particularly and verie cleerely anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by <hi>Roger Widdrington.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Widdringt. <hi>in Diſcuſſ. Diſcuſſ. part.</hi> 3.
<hi>ſec.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; in</hi> detecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one <hi>calum. D.</hi> Schulck. §. 7 <hi>nu.</hi> 16. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
                     </note>
                  </p>
                  <p>And <hi>first</hi> to the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Seuenth, hee ſheweth, that in the Canon,
<hi>Nos San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> nothing is defined, if wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard the rules, which Cardinall <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> alleageth to make a true defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition,<note place="margin">Bell.
<hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 12.</note>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:19923:26"/>neither is there any mention made in that decree of any conſent of the Biſhops, who were preſent; and that albeit any thing mentioned in that degree had beene expreſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined, yet conſidering that it is a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable doctrine, that the <hi>Popes</hi> defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions in a Prouinciall Councell, as was that <hi>Romane Councell,</hi> are vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and fallible, they cannot make the doctrine, which they define, to be certaine, and the contrarie to bee improbable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Secondly,</hi> hee ſheweth, that neither from the words of that <hi>Canon</hi> it can bee gathered, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to depriue <hi>Soueraigne Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> but only <hi>inferiour Lords</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates</hi> by the conſent and authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of thoſe <hi>abſolute Princes,</hi> to whom they are ſubiect in temporalls: and that therefore that Canon <hi>Nos San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum</hi> is to bee vnderſtood only of thoſe, who are ſubiect to the <hi>Pope</hi> in temporalls, and hath force to binde only in his owne Territories, or it was confirmed by the conſent and autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of other abſolute <hi>Princes,</hi> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19923:27"/>learned Canoniſts mentioned by Pope
<hi>Innocentius, Hoſtienſis,</hi> and <hi>Ioan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Andreas</hi> expound the Canon, <hi>Ad abolendam de haereticis.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>In can.</hi> Ad abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lendam.</note> And as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Dictatus Papae,</hi> which
<hi>Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> vrgeth and attributeth to a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Councell,</hi> wherein it is expreſly ſaid,<note place="margin">Widdringt. <hi>in Disput. Theol. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>ſec.</hi> 1.</note> 
                     <hi>That the Pope hath power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the Emperour: That he hath power to abſolue ſubiects from their Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, Widdrington</hi> ſheweth that they neither belong to any
<hi>Romane Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell,</hi> nor containe any definition, but only a declaration of the ſaid Pope <hi>Gregories</hi> opinion, who thought hee had ſuch authoritie, and that hee might lawfully practiſe it, wherein neuertheleſſe, as being <hi>a thing neuer heard of before that Age,</hi> ſaith <hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Onuphrius <hi>lib.</hi> 4.
<hi>de varia creat.</hi> Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Pont.</note> hee was greatly, and might lawfully be contradicted by true and vertuous Catholikes, as alſo at this preſent many other opinions of <hi>Popes</hi> concerning their Diſpenſations and Abſolutions in other things are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradicted by vertuous and learned Catholike Diuines.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>Councell</hi> of <hi>Lateran, Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:19923:27"/>hath anſwered at large, both in a peculiar <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of the Decree of this Councell againſt
<hi>Leſſius,</hi> and alſo in his Confutation of <hi>Fitz-her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts</hi> Reply, wherein hee ſheweth, that, according to the doctrine and expoſition of famous and learned <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonists</hi> and <hi>Diuines,</hi> the Decree of this <hi>Councell</hi> neither was, nor could be vnderſtood of <hi>Emperours, Kings,</hi> and <hi>abſolute Princes,</hi> who in temporall matters, wherein they are ſupreme and ſubiect to none but God, are not comprehended vnder any generall names, if the matter be penall and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, and much leſſe vnder the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name of a <hi>Temporall</hi> or <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall Magistrate</hi> or <hi>Lord,</hi> (as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther an <hi>Abbot</hi> is in penall and odious matters comprehended vnder the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall name of a <hi>Monke,</hi> nor a <hi>Biſhop</hi> vnder the generall name of a <hi>Priest</hi>) but that it is only to be vnderſtood of <hi>Dukes, Earles, Maiors, Bailiffes,</hi> and ſuch other inferiour temporall <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Magistrates</hi> (as likewiſe by the names of a <hi>Temporall</hi> and <hi>principall Lord</hi> or
<hi>Magistrate,</hi> they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19923:28"/>in the <hi>Emperours</hi> Decree, who vſeth the verie ſame generall words;) and that therefore this
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of the <hi>Lateran Councell</hi> had force to bind only in the
<hi>Popes</hi> temporall Dominions, or it was confirmed by the authoritie and conſent of <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes,</hi> to whom ſuch inferior
<hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Magiſtrates</hi> were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect.</p>
                  <p>To the <hi>ſecond</hi> Scruple concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> Breues, <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath fully anſwered in his <hi>Theologicall Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> and more at large in his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere</hi> to
<hi>Fitz-herbert:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ſec.</hi> 2.
<hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap. vlt.</hi>
                     </note> and partly in the laſt Chapter of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> wherein hee ſheweth, that it is no diſobedience or irreuerence not to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey theſe <hi>declaratiue Breues,</hi> being grounded vpon falſe ſuppoſitions, as he conuinceth them to be, and that it is not only fitting, but neceſſarie for euerie good and vertuous Catholike, not to obey any ſuch Breues, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly when they command a thing which is in preiudice of a third per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as is the forbidding of this <hi>Oath,</hi> which is ſo preiudiciall not onely to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19923:28"/>His <hi>Maiestie</hi> and his ſubiects, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to the temporall <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> of all other abſolute
<hi>Princes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the <hi>third</hi> Scruple concerning the <hi>ſcandall, Widdrington</hi> hath fully anſwered, partly in the <hi>Preface</hi> of his
<hi>Apologeticall Anſwere,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>nu</hi> 21.
<hi>cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ſec.</hi> 3.</note> and more fully in his
<hi>Theologicall Disputation</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee hath ſhewed, that if the
<hi>Oath</hi> be lawfull, and doth not containe any falſhood or iniuſtice, but is an <hi>Oath</hi> of true temporall Allegiance, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred by good and full authoritie, as this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> doth make manifeſt, it is no
<hi>giuing</hi> of ſcandall to take the <hi>Oath,</hi> but that thoſe Prieſts and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes doe <hi>giue</hi> great ſcandall by refuſing it, and giue iuſt occaſion to all <hi>Proteſtant Princes</hi> and
<hi>ſubiects</hi> to thinke, that true temporall Allegiance due to a temporall <hi>Prince</hi> cannot, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the grounds of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<hi>Roman</hi> Religion, ſtand with true ſpirituall obedience due to the
<hi>Pope</hi> and other ſpirituall Paſtours, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by they mightily wrong all temporall <hi>Princes,</hi> they greatly ſcandalize the Catholike
<hi>Roman</hi> Religion, &amp; as much
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19923:29"/>as much as in them lyeth, they ſeeke to auert all <hi>Protestant Princes</hi> and <hi>ſubiects</hi> from ſhewing any fauour to the profeſſors of the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="preamble">
            <head>A Plaine and neceſſarie <hi>Preamble,</hi> wherein certaine important <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations</hi> are ſet downe, for the better vnderſtanding of this new <hi>Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEfore I come to explaine the particular branches of this new
<hi>Oath</hi> eſtabliſhed by <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> I thinke it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe to ſet downe by way of a <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amble</hi> or
<hi>Preface</hi> certaine general Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruations, which may giue no little light to the better vnderſtanding of the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Firſt</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation.</note>1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> therefore to know the nature and conditions of an <hi>Oath,</hi> it is to be obſerued, that euerie lawfull
<hi>Oath</hi> muſt be <hi>diſcreet, iust,</hi> and <hi>true;</hi> according to that of the Prophet <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ierem.</hi>
4.</note> 
               <hi>And thou ſhalt ſweare in Truth, and in Iuſtice, and in Iudgement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iudgement</hi> is required chiefly in
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19923:29"/>regard of the ſwearer, that hee take not the Name of God in vaine, raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, irreuerently, without iuſt and vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent occaſion, and not duly exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the truth of what he ſweareth; for the matter or thing which is ſworne, may oftentimes bee true and iuſt, and yet the Name of God may bee taken in vaine, and without iuſt cauſe or neceſſitie to confirme the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iustice</hi> is required chiefly in a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſorie Oath,</hi> to wit, wherein ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is promiſed for the future time to be done or omitted: and therefore as it is vnlawfull to promiſe any thing which is vniuſt, ſo is it more vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to confirme that vniuſt promiſe by Oath. Yet <hi>Iuſtice</hi> may alſo ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times bee wanting in an
<hi>Aſſertorie Oath,</hi> as when one reuealeth a ſecret, which in Iuſtice hee is bound to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale, and confirmeth the ſame by Oath, for then he ſweareth truly, but vniuſtly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veritie</hi> or <hi>Truth</hi> is neceſſarie in all Oaths, for alſo in a <hi>promiſſorie</hi> Oath two kinds of <hi>veritie</hi> are required; the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19923:30"/>
               <hi>one</hi> is for the peſent time (wherein it reſembleth the nature of an <hi>Aſſertorie Oaeth</hi>) for hee that promiſeth to doe, or not to doe any thing, muſt haue his words agreeable to his minde, and therefore muſt for the preſent haue a minde or intent to performe what hee promiſeth; otherwiſe hee ſweareth vntruly; the
<hi>ſecond</hi> veritie is for the future time; for he that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth any thing, calling God for wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his promiſe, and through his owne default doth not performe his promiſe at the time appointed, is for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne, and his <hi>promiſſorie Oath</hi> wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth <hi>veritie:</hi> But
<hi>truth</hi> and <hi>veritie</hi> is chiefly required in <hi>Aſſertorie Oaths,</hi> to wit, wherein ſome thing is affirmed to be true or falſe. And therefore as it is vnlawfull for one to affirme that to be true, which hee knoweth to bee falſe, and contrariwiſe, for this were expreſly and formally to lye, or to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that to be true or falſe, whereof he is vncertaine or doubtfull, for this were to expoſe himſelfe to danger of ſpeaking an vntruth, ſo alſo it is much more vnlawfull to confirme the ſame by Oath.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:19923:30"/>2. Whereupon <hi>Periurie</hi> is defined by the Schoole-Diuines to be <hi>a lye confirmed by Oath.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Magiſter <hi>in</hi> 3. <hi>diſt.</hi> 39. <hi>S. Thom.</hi>
               </note> And therefore as a lye is deuided into a <hi>formall</hi> lye, to wit, when one affirmeth any thing to be true or falſe, and thinketh other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe in his mind (for <hi>to lye,</hi> ſaith Saint
<hi>Augustine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. <hi>lib de Mendacio.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>is to ſpeake against that which hee thinketh in his minde,</hi>) and into <hi>a materiall</hi> lye, to wit, when one ſpeaketh as hee thinketh, and yet in very deed it is otherwiſe; So <hi>Periu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> is deuiued into <hi>materiall</hi> and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall</hi> Periurie, for that
<hi>Periurie</hi> is a <hi>lye confirmed by Oath,</hi> and only ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to a
<hi>lye</hi> the calling of God to witneſſe of what hee ſpeaketh. And therefore whatſoeuer may bee affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med without danger of <hi>lying,</hi> may be ſworne without danger of <hi>Periurie:</hi> and as the falſhood which maketh a <hi>formall</hi> lye, is not to bee taken from the thing as it is in it ſelfe or <hi>ex parte rei,</hi> but as it is conceiued by the ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, for that to <hi>lye</hi> is to ſpeake againſt the minde, ſo the falſhood, which maketh <hi>formall</hi> Periurie, is not to be taken from the thing which is ſworn,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19923:31"/>as it is in it ſelfe, or <hi>ex parte rei,</hi> but as it is againſt the mind and knowledge of the ſwearer.</p>
            <p n="3">3. For <hi>the veritie, which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in an Oath, conſiſteth in this,</hi> ſaith <hi>Gregorius de Valentia</hi> &amp;
<hi>Sayrus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Valentia <hi>tom.</hi> 3 <hi>diſp.</hi> 6. <hi>q.</hi> 7.
<hi>p.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>Sayrus <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>Theſauri cap.</hi> 4.
<hi>nu.</hi> 7.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>that the thing bee true, at least wiſe accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reaſonable iudgement of the ſwearer. And therefore it is to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,</hi> that to iudge whether an <hi>Oath</hi> be true or falſe, we muſt not ſo much regard the thing ſworne, as the mind and knowledge of him that ſweareth. So that <hi>whoſoeuer affirmeth a thing by Oath,</hi> ſaith <hi>Siluester</hi> and <hi>Petrus A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragoua,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Silueſt. <hi>verbo</hi> Periurium <hi>q.</hi> 1.</p>
                  <p>Aragoua, 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 89. <hi>art.</hi> 3.</p>
               </note>
               <hi>in that manner as hee knoweth it to be true, is not formally forſworne:</hi> as if he ſweare his opinion, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, or perſwaſion, he muſt be morally certaine, that he is ſo perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, if he ſweare it abſolutely to bee ſo, he muſt bee morally certaine it is ſo, otherwiſe he expoſeth himſelfe to danger of being forſworne, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in very deed it fall out other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, then he is morally certain, yet he is excuſed in the Court of Conſcience from the ſinne of Periurie, and hee is not <hi>formally,</hi> but only <hi>materially</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſworne.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:19923:31"/>
               <note place="margin">The <hi>Second</hi> Obſeruation.</note>4. <hi>Secondly,</hi> to know in what ſenſe the words of euery <hi>Law,</hi> and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently of this <hi>Oath,</hi> which is eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by a <hi>Parliamentall Law,</hi> ought to be taken, it is to bee <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued</hi> out of the doctrine of <hi>Franciſcus Suarez a famous Ieſuite,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de</hi> Legibus <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> that the
<q rend="inline">"<hi>words of euery Law are commonly to be vnderstood according to their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and vſuall ſignification, and that if any wordes haue many proper and vſual ſignifications, that ſenſe is to be taken, wherein the Law-maker doth vnderstand them, becauſe vpon the will and intention of the Law-maker (which is the ſoule of the Law) the ſubstance and force of the Law, doth chiefly depend. Whereupon if by any meanes the will of the Law-ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker can bee knowne, according to it eſpecially wee muſt interprete the words of the Law, becauſe that is the true interpretation of the Law, by which we follow the meaning and will of the Law-maker. But if by the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Law-maker wee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not gather the meaning of any equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocall and ambiguous word or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19923:32"/>contayned in the Law, then we must vſe thoſe rules, which in all am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous and doubtfull ſpeeches are prudently to be obſerued: to wit, that the matter or contents of the Law, with the antecedents, &amp; conſequents, and other circumstances be diligently conſidered, for by them the meaning of the words, and the will of the Law-maker will eaſily be gathered. And eſpecially we must conſider the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Preface or Preamble, of the Law, and with it to ioyne the rest that followeth: for to the beginning, if there be no other let, all that followeth is to be applyed; becauſe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or Preface of euery Law is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually contayned the finall end, cauſe, and reaſon, which chiefly moueth the Law-maker, and which is morally a ſure meanes to finde out his will and meaning, and by which the ambigui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of any word or ſentence is chiefly to be determined. And finally we muſt alwaies, if there be no other let, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the words of the Law, when they are doubtfull, in the more milde and fauourable ſenſe, eſpecially if the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19923:32"/>matter be odious, and penall, aeccor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to thoſe approued rules of the Law,</hi> Benignius <hi>leges &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leg.</hi> Benignius <hi>ff de</hi> legibus. <hi>De</hi> regulis Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris <hi>in Sexin.</hi>
                  </note>
               </q> Laws are to be interpreted in the more fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable ſenſe, &amp;c. And it is meete that odious things be reſtrayned, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours bee enlarged.
<q rend="inline">"<hi>Yea, and if the words of the Law being taken in their proper ſignification ſhould argue any iniuſtice, or like abſurditie to bee in the minde of the Law-maker, they must bee drawne to a ſenſe although improper, wherein the Laew may bee iust and reaſonable, becauſe this is preſumed to bee the will of the Law-maker, as it hath beene declared by many Lawes</hi> in ff. tit. de Legibus. Nam in ambigua voce, &amp;c.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Leg.</hi> in ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gua <hi>ff.</hi> de legi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus.</note> For in a doubtfull word of the Law, <hi>ſaith the Law,</hi> that ſenſe is rather to bee choſen, which is voide of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault, eſpecially ſeeing that the will alſo of the Law-maker may here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be gathered: <hi>becauſe it ought not to be perſumed, that the Law-maker did intend to command any abſurd or inconuenient thing.</hi>
               </q> Thus
<hi>Suarez.</hi> What blame then doe they deſerue,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19923:33"/>who ſeeke to wreſt the wordes of this Oath, to a ſenſe which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to bee moſt falſe and abſurd, with ſo great preiudice to the ſoules and temporall States of Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes, and with no leſſe irreue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to his <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the State whom next vnder God they are bound to honor and obey in all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall affaires, whereas they may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the words, according to their proper and vſuall ſignification, in a true, conuenient, and fauorable ſenſe, as the Reader may ſee beneath?</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> to know the end and reaſon of this
<hi>Oath</hi> and of the makers thereof, it is to bee <hi>obſerued,</hi> that the <hi>Parliame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> in the very beginning of this Act, (to which according to <hi>Suarez,</hi> we muſt, if there be no other let, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply all that followeth) did expreſly ſet downe the cauſe, end, and reaſon, for which this <hi>new Oath</hi> was deuiſed, to wit, <hi>to make a better tryall how His</hi> Maieſties <hi>ſubiects ſtand affected in point of their loyaltie, and due obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi> For His <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the
<hi>State</hi> perceiuing, that the <hi>Powder-Traytors.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:19923:33"/>who were all of them <hi>Romane Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> did ground, as it doth appeare by their confeſſions, their barbarous and deuilliſh plot chiefly vpon the <hi>Popes</hi> power to take away the Crownes and liues from temporall <hi>Princes</hi> in order to ſpirituall good, and knowing with all, that many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Roman Catholikes</hi> did from their hearts deteſt, and abhorre ſuch tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous and diabolicall practiſes, and the wicked grounds thereof, thought it needfull, for the better diſcouering and repreſſing of ſuch bloudie Aſſaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates, and their diſciples, to deuiſe ſuch an <hi>Oath,</hi> wherein true <hi>temporall Allegiance</hi> due to all <hi>temporall Princes</hi> of what Religion ſoeuer, ſhould bee demanded, and no true
<hi>ſpirituall obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience</hi> due to the <hi>Pope,</hi> or other
<hi>ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Pastours</hi> ſhould be denyed, and yet the wicked principles of that moſt damnable Conſpiracie ſhould bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and abiured. And the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of this <hi>new Oath</hi> they did take from the <hi>Protestation</hi> of thoſe <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene</hi> Catholike Prieſts (as the Lord Archbiſhop of Canterburie, Doctor
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19923:34"/>
               <hi>Bancroft</hi> told a deare friend of mine) only vſing another forme of words, and expreſſing ſome things concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the <hi>Popes</hi> pretended authoritie, which in their
<hi>Protestation</hi> are not expreſſed, but only ſuppoſed, implyed and virtually contayned, for in effect and ſubſtance they little differ, as partly you haue ſeen aboue, and more fully ſhall perceiue when you haue ſeene all the branches of the <hi>Oath</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>playned.
<note place="margin">In his <hi>Premo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition pag.</hi> 9. &amp; in hir <hi>Apologie</hi> for the Oath. pag. 2. &amp; pag. 9.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. And not only the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath ſet downe the end and reaſon of this <hi>new Oath,</hi> but alſo His <hi>Maieſtie</hi> Himſelfe hath often by publike Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings in expreſſe words declared, that He intended to exact <hi>in this Oath</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe of His Subiects,
<hi>then a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of that temporall Allegiance and ciuill Obedience, which all ſubiects</hi> (what Religion ſoeuer they profeſſe) <hi>by the Law of God and Nature do owe to their lawfull Prince with a promiſe to reſist and diſcloſe all contrarie vnci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill violence; and to make a true diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not betwixt</hi> Catholikes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, <hi>but betwixt ciuilly obedient</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19923:34"/>Catholikes, <hi>and ſuch</hi> Catholikes
<hi>as are the Diſciples of the Powder-Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> Whereupon <hi>hee cauſed the lower houſe of Parliament, who at firſt would haue had the Oath to contayne the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall of the Popes power to excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate him, to reforme that clauſe. So carefull was He, that nothing ſhould be contayned in this</hi> Oath <hi>except the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of naturall Allegiance, and ciuill and temporall obedience.</hi> He ſaid <hi>in this Oath;</hi> for as the <hi>Oath of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie,</hi> ſaith His <hi>Maiestie, was deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for putting a difference betweene</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and them of our profeſſions ſo was this</hi> Oath <hi>ordayned for making a difference betweene the ciuilly obedient</hi> Papiſts, <hi>and the peruerſe diſciples of the Powder-Treaſon.</hi> And againe, <hi>This Oath,</hi> ſaith His <hi>Maieſtie, was orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned only for making a true diſtinction betweene</hi> Papiſts <hi>of quiet dispoſition, and in all other things good ſubiects, and ſuch other</hi> Papiſts <hi>as in their harts maintayned the like violent bloudie maximes that the</hi> Powder-Traytours
<hi>did.</hi> The ſame alſo but in more am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wordes affirmeth His
<hi>Maiestie</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:19923:35"/>in His <hi>Apologie</hi> for the
<hi>Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. Wherefore we muſt diſtinguiſh betwixt the vnderſtanding, beliefe, or perſwaſion of His <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and His will, intent, or meaning as Hee is a <hi>Law-maker.</hi> For albeit His
<hi>Maiestie</hi> ſhould beleeue and be fully perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> is not the Supreme Head of the whole Church, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that he hath not by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt any power to
<hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate</hi> him, yet his will and meaning is not, that His ſubiects ſhal in <hi>this Oath</hi> profeſſe the ſame, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce any ſpirituall obedience due to the <hi>Pope,</hi> which euery
<hi>Catholike,</hi> according to the grounds of true Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Religion, is bound to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, but only, that they make a profeſſion of that temporall Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance, and ciuill obedience, which all ſubiects, of what Religion ſoeuer, do owe to their lawfull Prince. From whence it cleerly followeth, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit there were in <hi>this Oath</hi> ſome am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous or doubtfull ſentence (as there is not) which might be applyed as well to the denying of that ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19923:35"/>obedience, which, according to the grounds of Catholike Religion, is due to the <hi>Pope</hi> and other ſpirituall Paſtours, as to the profeſſing of that temporall Allegiance, which is due to temporall Princes, we ought to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete the words in that ſenſe, wherein, according to the will, minde, and end of the Law, and declaration of the Law-maker, only temporall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance is demanded, for that <hi>by the end and reaſon of the Law the ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guitie of the words,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Suarez,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>de</hi> Legibus
<hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>nu.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>is chiefly to be determined, and it is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally a ſure meanes to finde out the will and intention of the Law-maker, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that reaſon which is expreſſed in the Law, for then the reaſon of the Law is in ſome ſort a part thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is contayned and ſuppoſed therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> it is to bee <hi>obſerued,</hi> that albeit <hi>Engliſh Catholikes</hi> might <hi>at the firſt,</hi> before they examined par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly the end, reaſon, matter, and contents of this <hi>new Oath,</hi> iuſtly ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it to be vnlawfull, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne in it more then <hi>temporall Alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giance;</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:19923:36"/>and that His <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the
<hi>Parliament</hi> vnder pretence of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding that <hi>temporall Allegiance,</hi> which by the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> is due to all <hi>temporall Princes,</hi> did intend to haue couertly at leaſtwiſe abiured ſome <hi>ſpirituall obedience,</hi> which by the inſtitution of <hi>Christ</hi> is due to <hi>ſpirituall Paſtours,</hi> both for that it is a new, vncouth, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted <hi>Oath</hi> of
<hi>Allegiance,</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly denyeth the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, to depoſe wherewith other <hi>Christian Princes,</hi> in the ordinarie
<hi>Oaths</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which they demand of their ſubiects, doe not in plaine and expreſſe termes intermeddle; and alſo for that it was deuiſed by thoſe, who are oppoſite to the Catholike <hi>Romane</hi> Religion; yet this bare ſuſpicion can bee no ſufficient cauſe, ground, or motiue to condemne it (as likewiſe no man vpon a bare ſuſpicion is to be condemned) but only to haue it exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, and if after due examination it be found faulty, to reiect it, if other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe to approue it. But doubtleſſe whoſoeuer will ſincerely, and with a
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19923:36"/>pure deſire to find out the truth, and to yeeld without all partialitie as wel to <hi>Kings</hi> as to <hi>Popes</hi> that which is their due, examine the occaſion, end, matter, and contents of this <hi>new</hi> and <hi>vnwonted Oath,</hi> will quickly finde, that it is condemned by ſome, vpon a bare and naked ſuſpicion and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out due examination; by others, vpon a blind and inconſiderate zeale to the <hi>See Apostolike,</hi> not regarding in like manner the dutie which by the
<hi>Law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> they owe to their <hi>temporall Prince;</hi> and by all that thinke it vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull, without ſufficient ground.</p>
            <p n="9">9. For the occaſion of this <hi>vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Oath,</hi> was that <hi>vnwonted</hi> barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>Powder-plot</hi> of certaine Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, who pretended to iuſtifie their neuer heard of <hi>Barbariſme</hi> vnder the colour of Religion, and the <hi>Popes</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to diſpoſe of the Crownes and liues of <hi>temporall Princes</hi> in order to ſpirituall good; and ſo no maruell, that to preuent the like <hi>vnwonted</hi> crueltie was deuiſed this <hi>vnwonted</hi> remedie. And albeit the inuenters of this
<hi>Oath</hi> are oppoſite to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19923:37"/>Romane Religion and are fully perſwaded, that the <hi>Pope</hi> by the Law of God, hath no authoritie ouer this Kingdome, ſo much as in ſpiritualls, yet there meaning was not, as you haue ſeene aboue, to meddle <hi>in this Oath</hi> with that ſpirituall authoritie, which is granted him by all Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, but only to demand a profeſſion of that temporall Allegiance, which all the Subiects of this Land, of what Religion ſoeuer they be, doe owe to their <hi>temporall</hi> Prince, and not to the
<hi>Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. And therefore, which is care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully to bee
<hi>obſerued,</hi> this <hi>Oath</hi> doth not meddle <hi>poſitiuely</hi> with the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, for that it doth not belong to
<hi>temporall Princes</hi> to declare what authoritie the <hi>Pope</hi> hath, but it med<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth <hi>poſitiuely</hi> with the <hi>Kings</hi> tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<hi>Soueraigntie,</hi> and <hi>negatiuely</hi> with the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie; and it doth not declare
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> what authoritie the <hi>Pope</hi> hath, but only what authoritie hee hath not. And what man, I pray you, can bee ſo blinde as not to ſee, that whoſoeuer <hi>expreſly</hi> affirmeth
<hi>King
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19923:37"/>Iames</hi> to bee his true and rightfull
<hi>King</hi> and <hi>Soueraigne</hi> in temporalls, and to haue ouer him and his other Subiects all <hi>Kingly Power, Authority,</hi> and
<hi>Iuriſdiction,</hi> doth <hi>conſequently</hi> and <hi>vertually</hi> deny the ſame of the <hi>Pope?</hi> Wherefore if wee well examine the matter and contents of this <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wonted Oath,</hi> wee ſhall find, that His
<hi>Maiestie</hi> and the <hi>State</hi> doe herein deny no other authoritie of the <hi>Pope expreſly</hi> and by name, then which not only in the
<hi>Protestation</hi> of thoſe <hi>thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene</hi> Catholike Prieſts, but alſo in all other <hi>vſuall</hi> Oaths of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> which abſolute Princes are wont to demand of their Subiects, is vertual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, couertly, and in effect implyed. For whoſoeuer ſincerely and from his heart acknowlegeth, any Prince to be his only rightfull <hi>King</hi> and
<hi>Soueraigne</hi> in temporals (which all abſolute <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> in their vſuall Oaths of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance demand of their Subjects) hee muſt
<hi>vertually</hi> acknowledge, that the <hi>Pope</hi> is not his
<hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> in temporals, and conſequently, that he hath no authoritie ouer his Prince or
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19923:38"/>him in temporals, and therefore nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to depoſe his Prince, or to diſpoſe of His temporall Dominions, for that theſe are te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral things for what end, cauſe, crime, or pretext ſoeuer, either ſpirituall or temporall, they be done.</p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Fiftly,</hi> to know vpon what aſſured grounds the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depoſe Princes,</hi> or to attempt and practiſe their depoſition, is by Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes denyed <hi>in this Oath,</hi> it is to be <hi>obſerued,</hi> that as <hi>Leonardus Leſſius,</hi> a famous Ieſuite, noteth very well,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leſſius</hi> in his <hi>Singleton,</hi> part. 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>a power which is not altogether certaine but probable, cannot be a</hi> ſufficient
<hi>ground</hi> or title, <hi>whereby immediately any man may bee puniſhed or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of that right, dominion, or any other thing which he actually poſſeſſeth, but ſuch a power or title must bee most certaine, and without all doubt or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</hi> Wherefore neither can the
<hi>Pope,</hi> nor any other <hi>Prince,</hi> without manifeſt iniuſtice inuade the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of another <hi>Prince,</hi> make warre againſt him, or ſeeke to depoſe or diſpoſſeſſe him vpon a probable, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine, or controuerſed title. <hi>For
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:19923:38"/>certes,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> (and who is knowne to bee a famous <hi>Doctor</hi> and <hi>Profeſſor</hi> of Diuinity though masked vnder the name of <hi>I. E.</hi>)<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cap.</hi> 11.
<hi>pag.</hi> 235.</note> 
               <hi>as it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice to put one out of his land or houſe, who hath probable right and and withall poſſeſſion, becauſe</hi> poti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>r eſt conditio poſſidentis, better is the condition of him that is in poſſeſſion, <hi>So were it open iniustice in the</hi> Pope <hi>to depriue a</hi> King <hi>of his Crowne and Kingdome, who hath probable right and withall poſſeſſion.</hi> And this alſo is the receiued doctrine of all Diuines and Lawyers,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Victoria <hi>in</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect <hi>de ture bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li. nu.</hi> 29.
<hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Vaſquez 1. 2. <hi>diſp.</hi> 64. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>Gregorius <hi>de</hi> Valentia 2. 2. and Pope <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian</hi> with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others cited by <hi>Valentia.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and grounded in the light of naturall reaſon, and declared by the approued rules of the Law, that no man can bee iuſtly inuaded, or be put out of his poſſeſſion vpon an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine or controuerſed title, becauſe <hi>In cauſa dubia, ſiue incerta potior est conditio poſſidentis, In a doubtfull</hi> or diſputable cauſe <hi>the condition of the poſſeſſor is to bee preferred,</hi> and <hi>Cum ſunt iura partium obſcura fauendum est reo potius quam Actori. When the rights</hi> or titles <hi>of the parties that are
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:19923:39"/>in ſuite are obſcure,</hi> or not cleere,
<hi>the Defendant is rather to be fauoured then the Plaintiffe.</hi> And this is the <hi>first</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured ground and principle, for which the doctrine of depoſing <hi>Princes</hi> by the Popes <hi>authoritie</hi> may not only be barely and ſimply denyed, as it is in the <hi>ſecond</hi> clauſe of the
<hi>Oath</hi> by force only of the words, but alſo bee ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred, deteſted and abiured as <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, damnable,</hi> moſt cleerly repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, and in that ſenſe <hi>hereticall,</hi> as it is in the
<hi>fourth</hi> clauſe. The <hi>ſecond</hi> manifeſt principle is, that it is a controuerſie among learned Catholikes, and approued by many, and therefore <hi>truely probable,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authority to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue <hi>Princes</hi> of their Regall Power and Authoritie.</p>
            <p n="12">12. For the better cleering where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, it is to be obſerued <hi>ſixtly,</hi> that, as <hi>Ioannes Azorius</hi> a famous Ieſuite ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly affirmeth,<note place="margin">Azor. <hi>tom.</hi> 2.
<hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>it hath euer beene a great controuerſie betwixt Emperours and Kings on the one ſide, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome on the other, whether in ſome certaine caſes the Pope hath a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19923:39"/>right and power to depriue Kings of their Kingdome. For ſome Kings haue oftentimes</hi> (yea ſince the time of the great <hi>Lateran Councell</hi>) <hi>contended with Popes about this matter, ſaying, that they haue their Kingdome from God, and not from the Pope, and that in thoſe things, which are ciuill and temporall the power of Kings is ſupreme and abſolute, and that herein Kings are not ſubiect to the Pope, although in ſacred, Eccleſiaſticall and ſpirituall things the Pontificall power is ſupreme, and that herein Kings and Princes are ſubiect to Popes, as children to their Fathers, and ſheepe to their Pastours, &amp;c. And many complayned that</hi> Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie <hi>the ſeuenth did excommunicate</hi> Henry <hi>the fourth, and depriue him of the adminiſtration of his Kingdom.</hi> Thus <hi>Azor. And it is a controuerſie among the Schoolemen,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Ioannes Trithe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mius</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trithemius <hi>in Chron. Hirſaug. ad annum</hi> 1106.</note>)
<hi>and as yet it is not decided by the Iudge, whether the Pope hath power to depoſe the Emperour or no. And the Eccleſiasticall power</hi> (ſaith
<hi>Iacobus Almainus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Almain. <hi>de d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minio natur. ciu. &amp; Eccleſ in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</hi> 2. <hi>concluſ.</hi>
               </note> a famous Doctor of Paris, and whom
<hi>Azor</hi> relateth<note place="margin">Azor. <hi>tom.</hi> 1. <hi>lib.</hi>
2. <hi>cap.</hi> 14.</note> among
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19923:40"/>Claſſicall Doctors) <hi>cannot by the inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of God inflict any ciuill puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as are death, exile, priuation of goods,</hi> much leſſe of Kingdomes, &amp;c. <hi>Nay nor ſo much as impriſon,</hi> vt ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Doctoribus placet, <hi>as is the opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of most, or of very many Doctors, but it is extended only to a ſpirituall pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, as is Excommunication, and the other puniſhments, which ſhe vſeth, doe proceed from the pure poſitiue Law,</hi> or as
<hi>Gerſon</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">Gerſon <hi>de po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. Eccleſ con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>from the grant of Princes. And the libertie of the Church of France,</hi> ſaith <hi>Petrus Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thaeus</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pithaeus <hi>in Cod. libert. Eccleſ. Gallicanae</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at
<hi>Paris</hi> by authoritie of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the yeere 1594.</note> (whom <hi>Antonius Poſſeuinus</hi> the Ieſuite commendeth for a man
<hi>truely learned and a diligent ſearcher of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquitie</hi>
               <note place="margin">Poſſeuinus <hi>in verbo</hi> Petrus Pithaeus.</note>) <hi>is grounded in this principle, which France hath euer held for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that the</hi> Pope <hi>hath not power to depriue the French King of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, or in any other manner to diſpoſe thereof; And that notwithſtanding any whatſoeuer Monitions</hi> or Monitories, <hi>Excommunications, or Interdicts, which by the</hi> Pope <hi>can bee made, yet the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects are bound to yeeld obedience due to the King for temporals; neither therein
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:19923:40"/>can they be diſpenced or abſolued by the Pope;</hi> Which poſition is in very deed the whole ſubſtance both of our
<hi>new Oath,</hi> and alſo of the <hi>late Oath</hi> of France, which the lower houſe of <hi>Parliament</hi> would haue had eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed for a
<hi>fundamentall law.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. And to omit now many other learned Catholikes cited by
<hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his Anſwere to <hi>Fitzherb.</hi> part. 1.</note> that it is a controuerſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Catholikes, and approued by many, and therefore truly probable, that the Pope hath no authoritie to depoſe Princes, it is ſo manifeſt, that no learned man, vnleſſe hee will bee ſhamefully impudent, can denie it, and the publike Writings of learned Catholikes on both ſides,<note place="margin">See beneath in the end of this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> the Oath of Fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> and <hi>Bell.</hi> Booke, and a decree of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> touching the doctrine of the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</note> the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Bookes of <hi>Cardinall Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine,</hi> of <hi>Schulckenius,</hi> and of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez,</hi> the propounding of the aforena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Oath</hi> by the lower houſe of
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi> wherein of two hundred Knights and Burgeſſes there were but <hi>fix Proteſtants,</hi> beſides the complaint of ſome Doctors of <hi>Paris</hi> to the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Sorbon</hi> againſt the
<hi>Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſia Anglicana</hi> of <hi>Becanus,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19923:41"/>other teſtimonies of learned men of our owne Nation, not only of thoſe who haue taken the Oath, or thinke it to be lawfull, but alſo of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, doe moſt cleerly conuince the ſame. In ſo much that <hi>Cardinall Peron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Card. Peron.</hi> in his ſpeech to the lower houſe of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament.</note> compelled by ſo manifeſt a truth, doth plainly confeſſe the ſame; and thereupon acknowledgeth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> himſelfe doth in
<hi>France</hi> tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate thoſe Catholikes, that hold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him in this point, <hi>tolerate,</hi> I ſay, not as publike Vſurers, Harlots, or other notorious ſinners, are in ſome Countries permitted, but by admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them to Sacraments, which nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Pope,</hi> nor the <hi>Prelates</hi> of
<hi>France</hi> could lawfully doe, if for hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that doctrine thoſe
<hi>Frenchmen</hi> were to bee condemned of Hereſie, Errour, Temeritie, or any other dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſinne. So that it is moſt cleere &amp; manifeſt to any man of iudgment, that it is a great controuerſie among learned Catholikes, and that it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by many of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore truly probable, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to <hi>depoſe</hi> or
<hi>depriue</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:19923:41"/>Soueraigne Princes. See alſo the
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour</hi> of the <hi>Potestants</hi> Apologie for the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in his <hi>Preface</hi> from Sect. 19. to the end, where you may ſee his diſlike of this doctrine for the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depoſe Princes, and taxeth them, who <hi>ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge the ſupreme Paſtour with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competent attributes of Authoritie in temporals:</hi> and in his owne authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Manuſcript he more particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and expreſly ſhewed, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no Authority in temporals, <hi>either directly, or indirectly,</hi> which laſt words it pleaſed thoſe who had commiſſion to print his Booke to leaue out, whereof he greatly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained to a friend of mine. And like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe for the diſlike, which this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Authour</hi> ſhewed in his <hi>Preface,</hi> of this authoritie of the <hi>Pope</hi> to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe of temporals, it pleaſed the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour,</hi> who tranſlated his Booke into Latine, to leaue out the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> altogether, which neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe is a chiefe part of his Booke, and it deſerued to bee put in <hi>Latine</hi> as much if not more then any other
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:19923:42"/>part thereof. But the <hi>Authours</hi> of Bookes muſt now adaies, if they looke not themſelues to the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting &amp; publiſhing of them, ſpeak as it pleaſeth the Tranſlators &amp; Cenſors.</p>
            <p n="15">15. Neither is it ſufficient for a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny man, which alſo is to bee <hi>obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> to condemne any doctrine as temerarious or improbable, for that in his iudgement and opinion it is repugnant to
<hi>Scriptures,</hi> ancient <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Councels, Canons,</hi> practice of the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Theologicall</hi> reaſons, if it bee approued by other learned Catholikes, who haue examined all the arguments on either ſide; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe the <hi>Thomists</hi> might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne of temeritie the
<hi>Scotists,</hi> and the <hi>Scotists</hi> the <hi>Thomists</hi> in the queſtion of the B. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgins</hi> Concep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; The <hi>Diuines</hi> of
<hi>Rome</hi> might condemne of temeritie the <hi>Diuines</hi> of
<hi>Paris,</hi> and the <hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> the <hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in the queſtion of the Popes infallibilitie, and ſupe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rioritie of the <hi>Pope</hi> and a <hi>Generall</hi> Councell; and the
<hi>Ieſuites</hi> might condemne of temeritie the <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cans,</hi>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:19923:42"/>and the <hi>Dominicans</hi> the
<hi>Ieſuits,</hi> in the queſtion of the efficacie of Grace: for all of them alledge for their opinion, <hi>Scriptures, Fathers, Councels, Canons,</hi> &amp; <hi>Theologicall</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; it is vſuall in moſt Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to bring ſuch arguments on both ſides. But true probabilitie and improbabilitie, and whereof not only learned men, but alſo the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned without any great difficultie or perplexitie of conſcience may iudge, is to be taken not from <hi>intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall</hi> grounds, which are vnknowne to vnlearned men, but from <hi>extrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecall</hi> grounds, to wit, the authoritie of learned men who are knowne to approue that doctrine. And therefore <hi>Aristotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtotle <hi>lib.</hi> 1.
<hi>Top. cap.</hi> 8.</note> whome all Philoſophers &amp; Diuines do herein follow, did by <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall</hi> grounds define <hi>probable,</hi> to be that which <hi>is approued by wiſe, learned, and skilfull men</hi> in the Art which they profeſſe: as in a matter of Law that is probable, which is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proued by learned and skilfull Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers; in a matter of Phyſicke that is probable, which is approoued by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19923:43"/>learned and skilfull Phyſicians, and in a matter of Theologicall learning that is probable, which is approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by learned and skilfull Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Diuines: which definiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>probable</hi> is grounded in the light of naturall reaſon, for that it is not againſt prudence, and therefore no temeritie to giue credit to one in a matter wherein he is skilfull, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that vulgar maxime, <hi>Vnicui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que in ſua arte perito credendum est, Credit is to bee giuen to euery man that is skilfull in his Art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">16. Theſe bee the <hi>two principall grounds,</hi> for which the doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> Princes by the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie may lawfully bee denyed, and alſo abiured in the manner afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid; for if it bee <hi>certaine,</hi> that it is open iniuſtice to diſpoſſeſſe any man vpon a <hi>probable, vncertaine,</hi> and
<hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſed</hi> power or title, and it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>certaine,</hi> that it is a <hi>controuerſie,</hi> and not <hi>certaine,</hi> whether the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to <hi>depoſe Princes</hi> or no; it followeth euidently, that it is as lawfull for any man to ſweare, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19923:43"/>
               <hi>depoſe</hi> Princes, as that hee hath no authoritie to commit open iniuſtice. But of this <hi>probabilitie</hi> ſee more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neath in the end of this Treatiſe.</p>
            <p n="17">17. The <hi>Seuenth</hi> and <hi>last</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation is, that wee muſt carefully conſider, what the ſwearer is bound to acknowledge and ſweare in euery <hi>branch</hi> of this <hi>Oath</hi> by
<hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>expreſſe words, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the plaine and common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding of them,</hi> to which by the <hi>ſeuenth branch</hi> hee is expreſly tyed, and what he may lawfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſweare by <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>matter;</hi> for this diſtinction may no little auaile to the better vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of ſome clauſes of this <hi>Oath,</hi> ſeeing that it may often fall out, that in regard of the <hi>matter</hi> one may lawfully ſweare that, which by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> hee is not bound or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to ſweare. As for example, if one bee commanded to ſweare, what his iudgement, opinion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion or acknowledgement is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning ſomething, whereof not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he is certaine; by <hi>force</hi> of the <hi>wordes</hi> hee is bound only to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:19923:44"/>ſweare, that hee thinketh, iudgeth, is perſwaded, and acknowledgeth it to bee ſo, yet by <hi>reaſon</hi> of the
<hi>matter</hi> which to him is certaine, hee may lawfully ſweare that abſolutely and aſſuredly it is ſo. Likewiſe if one bee commanded to abiure as <hi>falſe,</hi> and <hi>hereticall</hi> a <hi>conditionall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiue</hi> propoſition, which imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a choice to take which part of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> he pleaſe, by <hi>force</hi> of the wordes hee is bound to abiure but <hi>one part</hi> of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> as
<hi>he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall,</hi> becauſe to make ſuch a <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunctiue</hi> propoſition to bee <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> it ſufficeth that <hi>one part</hi> only of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> bee <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> yet ſomtimes by <hi>vertue</hi> of the
<hi>matter,</hi> when both parts of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> are
<hi>heretical,</hi> he may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully abiure both as heretical, albeit by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>wordes</hi> hee bee not bound thereunto. As theſe propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>Any man may lawfully honour, or blaſpheme God, The Pope by vertue of his Paſtorall power may excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate or murther any wicked Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> are <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> and yet
<hi>one part</hi> of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> is true, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:19923:44"/>only the other is <hi>falſe</hi> and
<hi>hereticall:</hi> but both parts of this propoſition, <hi>any man may lawfully hate or blaſphem God,</hi> are <hi>falſe</hi> and
<hi>hereticall,</hi> &amp; ſo by <hi>reaſon</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> both parts may be abiured as <hi>hereticall,</hi> although by <hi>force</hi> of the forme of words, to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure the whole propoſition as <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal,</hi> it ſufficeth to abiure only <hi>one part</hi> thereof as <hi>hereticall,</hi> And how this alſo may bee applyed to the <hi>fourth</hi> branch of the
<hi>Oath,</hi> wherein a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionall diſiunctiue</hi> propoſition is contayned, and whether the <hi>doctrine</hi> not only of <hi>murthering Princes, which be excommunicated or depriued</hi> by the <hi>Pope,</hi> but alſo of <hi>depoſing</hi> them, may bee abiured as <hi>hereticall,</hi> you ſhall ſee beneath. Theſe <hi>Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uations</hi> being conſidered, there will be found little or no difficultie in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part or parcell of the Oath.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="chapter">
            <head>The <hi>First</hi> Chapter. The <hi>Firſt</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an <hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q>I <hi>A.B.</hi> doe truely and ſincerely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, profeſſe, testifie, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:19923:45"/>in my conſcience before God and the World, That our Soueraigne Lord King <hi>Iames</hi> is lawful &amp; rightful King of this Realme, and of all other His Maiesties Dominions and Countries.</q>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Branch</hi> (which is the ground and foundation of the whole Oath, and as it were the roote and fountaine, from whence all the other branches, wherein the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie is any way denyed, doe ſpring and are deriued) is ſo cleere and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that no learned and well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted ſubiect can take any colourable exception againſt the ſame. In ſo much that Fa. <hi>Parſons</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">In his Booke entituled, <hi>The Iudgement of a Catholike En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh man, &amp;c. part.</hi> 7. <hi>nu.</hi> 22.
<hi>pag.</hi> 13. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.</note> himſelfe feareth not to affirme,
<hi>that there is no man, who ſticketh or maketh difficulty to acknowledge our Soueraigne to bee true King and rightfull Lord ouer all his Dominions, for that euery Engliſh Catholike will ſweare and acknowledge most willingly all thoſe parts and clau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the</hi> Oath, <hi>that doe any way ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertayne to the Ciuill and Temporall Obedience due to His</hi> Maieſtie <hi>whom hee acknowledgeth for his true and lawfull King and Soueraigne ouer all
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:19923:45"/>His Domioions.</hi> And <hi>Martinus Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canus</hi> a famous Ieſuite in the firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his
<hi>Controuerſia Anglicana</hi> writeth thus:<note place="margin">Becanus
<hi>in Controuerſia An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glic. cap.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 102</note> 
               <hi>And truly to me it is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, that all the parts and propoſitions of the Oath are not falſe if they bee well declared. For theſe are true:</hi> firſt,
<hi>that King</hi> Iames <hi>is lawfull King of England, Scotland and Ireland:</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, <hi>that in the ſame Kingdomes he is the Supreme or Soueraigne Lord in Temporalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>First</hi> therefore, if wee conſider the end of this Oath (which is only to make profeſſion of our temporall
<hi>Allegiance,</hi> and to <hi>make a true diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction not</hi> betwixt
<hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testants,</hi> &amp;c. the expreſſe declaration of His <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and the rules be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned in the
<hi>ſecond</hi> and <hi>third</hi> Obſeruation, it is euident, that by thoſe wordes [<hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi>] is not to be vnderſtood the
<hi>Kings Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remacie</hi> in Spirituall and Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, but only in Temporall and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill cauſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is alſo euident, that albeit by
<hi>force</hi> of the <hi>expreſſe wordes,</hi>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:19923:46"/>and the <hi>plaine and common vnderstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſame,</hi> to which the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth</hi> branch of this <hi>Oath</hi> tyeth the ſwearer, wee are bound only to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge that <hi>King</hi> Iames <hi>is lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, and of all other His Maiesties Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Countries,</hi> and not that <hi>Hee is the Soueraigne Lord of the ſame,</hi> both for that thoſe words [<hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi>] are put only <hi>ex parte ſubiecti,</hi> and not <hi>ex parte predicati,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>words</hi> are not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed; as likewiſe he that ſtileth the Pope <hi>most holy and most bleſſed,</hi> doth not affirme him to bee <hi>most holy and moſt bleſſed</hi> vnleſſe the words <hi>moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> &amp; <hi>moſt bleſſed</hi> be put <hi>ex parte predi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cati;</hi> &amp; alſo that if we regard the
<hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of thoſe words [<hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi>] they haue not the ſame ſenſe, which the words [<hi>lawfull and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full King</hi>] haue, ſeeing that one may be a <hi>lawfull and rightfull King,</hi> and yet not the <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> of His Kingdome, as if the
<hi>Emperour</hi> ſhould make the great <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>Toſcan</hi> King of <hi>Hetruria,</hi> he would be <hi>lawfull and
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19923:46"/>rightfull King</hi> of that Countrie, and yet not the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> or <hi>Supreme Lord</hi> of the ſame, becauſe hee is as a feudarie ſubiect to the <hi>Emperour.</hi> Neuertheleſſe becauſe the <hi>lawfull and rightfull King</hi> of <hi>England.</hi> is alſo the <hi>Soueraigne Lord</hi> of the ſame, by <hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> and
<hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> we may lawfully, and if it bee demanded at our hands, are bound to acknowledge and ſweare, that <hi>King Iames</hi> is not only the <hi>lawfull</hi> and <hi>rightfull King</hi> of England &amp; of all other His <hi>Maieſties</hi> Dominions, but alſo the
<hi>Soueraigne</hi> or <hi>Supreme Lord</hi> of the ſame. And in this ſenſe, both the XIII. <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and alſo M. <hi>Greene</hi> vnderſtood the word <hi>Soueraigne</hi> in their <hi>Proteſtation</hi> and
<hi>Declaration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Neither is it to the purpoſe which ſome obiect, that the <hi>King</hi> of England is the <hi>Popes <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſſall,</hi> and as a feudarie ſubiect to him in Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and therefore the <hi>Pope,</hi> and not <hi>King Iames</hi> is the abſolute <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and <hi>ſupreme Lord</hi> in Temporals of this Kingdome. For although wee ſhould abſurdly admit, that for the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19923:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>

               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:19923:47"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>

               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:19923:48"/>title and clayme of <hi>Temporall Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntie,</hi> which the <hi>Pope</hi> pretendeth to haue ouer this Kingdome by vet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of ſome grant of former Kings, may bee brought ſome probable proofe, as there cannot, ſeeing that it is euident, that no
<hi>King</hi> of England hath authoritie to giue away His <hi>Kingdome,</hi> or make it ſubiect in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals to another <hi>Prince</hi> without the conſent of the <hi>Kingdome</hi> it ſelfe; and that no colour of any probable proofe can bee brought from any <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall</hi> Inſtrument to ſhew, that the <hi>Kingdome</hi> of England euer con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to any ſuch grant, yet conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring that no <hi>probable title</hi> can bee a ſufficient ground to <hi>depriue</hi> any man of that Right, Dominion, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing which he <hi>actually poſſeſſeth,</hi> but ſuch a title muſt bee <hi>moſt certaine</hi> and out of all controuerſie, as I ſhewed aboue in the <hi>Fift</hi> Obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it is manifeſt, that, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any ſuch <hi>probable</hi> title, euery ſubiect of this Land may lawfully acknowledge by <hi>Oath,</hi> that <hi>King Iames</hi> is not only the <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19923:48"/>King</hi> of this Realme, and of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther His
<hi>Maiesties</hi> Dominions and Countries, but alſo the <hi>Soueraigne</hi> or <hi>ſupreme temporall Lord</hi> of the ſame.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. II. The <hi>Second</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an
<hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q>ANd that the Pope neither of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, nor by any authoritie of the Church, or See of Rome, or by any other meanes which any other hath any Power or Authoritie to depoſe the King, or to diſpoſe any of his Maieſties Kingdomes, or Dominions, or to authorize any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Prince to inuade or annoy Him or his Countries, or to diſcharge any of his Subiects of their Allegiance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to his Maieſtie, or to giue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe or leaue to any of them to beare Armes, rayſe Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to His Maiesties Royal Perſon, State, or Gouernment, or to any of His Maieſties ſubiects within His Maieſties Dominions.</q>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Branch</hi> ſuppoſing the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<hi>Obſeruations,</hi> hath in it no diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19923:49"/>at all, although wee ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, that the
<hi>immediate</hi> obiect there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, or which is all one, that, which in this
<hi>Branch</hi> by <hi>force of the words</hi> we are bound
<hi>immediately</hi> to ſweare, is not only our ſincere acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and perſwaſion, but alſo that abſolutely and aſſuredly the <hi>Pope hath not any authoritie to depoſe the King, &amp;c.</hi> For conſidering that the whole tenour of this <hi>Branch</hi> tendeth to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, namely,
<hi>to depoſe, to diſpoſe, to inuade, annoy, beare Armes, rayſe Tumults, offer violence or hurt,</hi> and <hi>to diſcharge ſubiects of their Allegiance,</hi> and alſo, that it is a doctrine approo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by many learned Catholikes, and who haue examined all the argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments on both ſides, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that it is <hi>truely probable,</hi> that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to depriue Princes, or to diſpoſe of their Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, it is as cleere and manifeſt, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man, whether hee bee the Kings ſubiect or no, what opinion ſoeuer he followeth in
<hi>ſpeculation</hi> concerning the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depriue Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, yet hee may as certainly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19923:49"/>and ſweare, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> that is, to practize his depoſition, or any other of thoſe things mentioned in this <hi>Branch,</hi> as it is cleere and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that hee may certainly acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and ſweare that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to commit open iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and that in a <hi>doubtfull</hi> vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, and diſputable <hi>caſe, the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the poſſeſſour is to bee preferred.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Neither doe <hi>temporall Princes,</hi> or other priuate men that haue any thing in their poſſeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> greatly regard, what learned men, who by the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiltie of their wits can eaſily finde out ſome probable colour of a broken and pretended title, may
<hi>ſpeculatiuely</hi> diſpute in Schooles concerning their titles, ſo that in <hi>practice,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſuch <hi>disputations</hi> and
<hi>ſpeculati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> they bee ſecured from being put out of that which they really and <hi>bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na fide</hi> doe poſſeſſe. And doubtleſſe moſt miſerable were the ſtate of all men that poſſeſſe any thing of worth, and much more of <hi>Princes,</hi> if vpon a title, which ſome learned m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19923:50"/>in <hi>ſpeculation</hi> approoue, it were law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to inuade their poſſeſſions, before a lawfull Iudge, and who is certainly knowne ſo to bee, hath decided and determined the title or controuerſie<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> To preuent which miſchiefe all <hi>Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi> being guided herein by the light of naturall reaſon haue agreed in this
<hi>manifest principle,</hi> that it is open in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice to put any man out of his poſſeſſion vpon any title which is not moſt certaine and free from all contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie vntill a lawfull and vndoubted Iudge hath decided the matter. (I ſaid <hi>a lawfull and vndoubted Iudge</hi>) for if it be doubtfull, vncertaine, and queſtionable whether he be a lawfull and competent Iudge to determine that cauſe, his deciſion cannot be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to end the controuerſie. For which cauſe the <hi>Pope</hi> is not to bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted a lawfull and competent Iudge to decide this queſtion concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his owne pretended authoritie to depriue Princes, for that it is a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among learned Diuines and approued by very many (as Pope
<hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> the <hi>Cardinaell</hi> of <hi>Cambray,</hi> the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19923:50"/>
               <hi>Cardinall Cuſanus,</hi> the <hi>Cardinall Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>normitan,</hi> the <hi>Cardinall</hi> of <hi>Florence</hi> Maſter to
<hi>Panormitan, Iohn Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Abulenſis, Ioannes</hi> Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſienſis, <hi>Ioannes</hi> Gerſon, <hi>Iohn Maior, Almaine,</hi> and almoſt all the Vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of Paris cited by <hi>Widdrington</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Widdring.</hi> in the diſcouerie of D. <hi>Schulke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius</hi> ſlanders. §. 7.</note>) that the <hi>Pope</hi> is not a competent Iudge to decide or define infallibly any do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall point (and much leſſe in his owne cauſe) without a true and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted generall Councell, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore although he ſhould hereafter, (as yet he hath not) attempt to define and decide this queſtion, his deciſion could not end the controuerſie, nor giue ſufficient warrant to any man to practize the depoſition of Princes, vpon ſo doubtfull, vncertaine, and queſtionable power or title.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Neuertheleſſe it behooueth <hi>temporall Princes</hi> to be very carefull, that their titles to the Dominions which they lawfuly poſſeſſe, be not ſo much as <hi>ſpeculatiuely,</hi> or only for
<hi>Diſputation</hi> ſake diſputed <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> by learned men, leaſt that ſome ignorant or turbulent ſpirits, which
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19923:51"/>either doe not know, or of ſet pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to colour their practices, vnder a pretence of a <hi>probable title,</hi> will not take notice of the manifeſt difference betwixt <hi>ſpeculation</hi> and
<hi>practice,</hi> may take occaſion thereby to diſturbe the publike peace, and to moleſt, annoy, or to offer any violence or hurt to their
<hi>Royall</hi> Perſons, States, or Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment. For which cauſe the
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> hath with great wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and reaſon oftentimes by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Edicts</hi> ordained,<note place="margin">See beneath in the end of this <hi>Treatiſe</hi> ſome of theſe Decrees.</note> that the doctrine of depoſing their <hi>Kings</hi> ſhould not bee ſo much as taught and maintay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to bee probable, or <hi>problematike,</hi> that occaſion be not giuen to ſeditious ſpirits (who know not, or will not take notice of the difference betwixt ſpeculation and practice) to attempt, vnder pretence of a probable title any violence againſt the Crowns or ſacred Perſons of their Kings. And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is manifeſt, for that the temporall Common-wealth hath good and full authoritie to forbid the teaching and publiſhing of any doctrine which is not neceſſarie, whereby probable
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19923:51"/>danger to the Crownes and liues of temporall Princes, and perturbations in the Common-wealth may ariſe.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore, by thoſe words of this Branch [nor <hi>by any other means with any other</hi>] it is euident, that the
<hi>Parliament,</hi> which repreſenteth the whole bodie of the Kingdome or Common-wealth did not intend to meddle with the authoritie which the whole Kingdome or Common-wealth may (according to the opinion of ſome Doctors) pretend to haue in ſome caſes ouer their <hi>ſoueraign</hi> Prince, as
<hi>Leſſius</hi> and others (whom the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors</hi> of the
<hi>Prelate</hi> and the Prince, doth ſeeme to follow) doe idly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect. And although the meaning of thoſe words were, to deny, that the whole Kingdome, or Common-wealth hath no authoritie to <hi>depoſe</hi> their <hi>King,</hi> yet conſidering that it is alſo a probable doctrine, &amp; approued by many learned Catholike Diuines, and Lawyers cited by <hi>Widdrington,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Widdr. <hi>in Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log. nu.</hi> 111. and in his <hi>Anſwere</hi> to <hi>Fitz-herb. part.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; cap.</hi> 11. <hi>nu.</hi> 36.
37.</note> that the <hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath no ſuch authority, it is alſo lawful for any man (of what opinion ſoeuer hee bee in
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19923:52"/>
               <hi>ſpeculation</hi> concerning this authoritie of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monweath) to acknowledge and ſweare, that the
<hi>Common-wealth</hi> hath no more authoritie to depoſe the <hi>King,</hi> that is, to practize his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, then ſhe hath to commit o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen iniuſtice; But the true meaning of His <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the
<hi>Parliament</hi> is, as the words themſelues doe plainely ſignifie, only to deny the <hi>Popes</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to depoſe, &amp;c. to wit, that the
<hi>Pope neither of himſelfe,</hi> that is, neither as a ſole and totall cauſe, nor <hi>by any authoritie, &amp;c.</hi> that is, neither <hi>as an Instrument or Minister of the Church or See of Rome,</hi> nor <hi>by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes with any other,</hi> that is, nor as a principall, or true and proper par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall cauſe or Agent, <hi>hath any authoritie to depoſe the King, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Neither by thoſe wordes [<hi>or to authorize any forraigne Prince to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uade or annoy Him or His Countries</hi>] did His
<hi>Maiestie</hi> and the <hi>Parliamen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> intend to denie the authoritie which temporall Princes may haue in ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> caſes to make warre againſt their neighbour Princes, and conſequently
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:19923:52"/>againſt His <hi>Maiestie,</hi> if he ſhould giue them iuſt cauſe of warre (yet euer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing, that no
<hi>probable</hi> power, cauſe, or title can bee a ſufficient ground to puniſh any <hi>Prince,</hi> or to inuade His Countries) but, as the expreſſe words do plainly ſhew, only to deny <hi>the Popes authoritie, to authorize any forraigne Prince to inuade or annoy Him or His Countries:</hi> becauſe all the authoritie which <hi>temporall Princes</hi> haue to make warre, or to inuade the Kingdome of an other Prince for what cauſe, crime, or end ſo euer it bee, is deriued from their temporall Soueraigntie groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi> or <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> &amp; not from the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie. And likewiſe all the authority, which the temporall Common-wealth may pretend to haue in ſome caſes to riſe vp in Armes againſt their Prince, is not deriued from the <hi>Popes</hi> warrant, licenſe or authoritie, but (if there be any ſuch power) from the Law of Nature. And therefore with great reaſon this <hi>Clauſe</hi> denyeth in the
<hi>Pope</hi> all <hi>power and authoritie to authorize a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forraigne Prince to inuade or annoy
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19923:53"/>His</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>or his Countries, or to giue licenſe or leaue to any of his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to beare Armes, rayſe Tumults, or to offer any violence or hurt to His</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtis <hi>Royall Perſon, State, or Gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t:</hi> becauſe although they ſhuld haue any ſuch authoritie, leaue, or licence, wherewith His <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the
<hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament</hi> would not in this <hi>Oath</hi> inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle, they haue it not from the <hi>Pope,</hi> but from the Law of <hi>Nations,</hi> or
<hi>Nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in this <hi>Branch</hi> is not denyed the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> in temporals in order to ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all good, or to <hi>declare,</hi> that they who haue authoritie to
<hi>depoſe,</hi> or to make warre, are bound to vſe their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall authoritie, and to draw forth the temporall Sword, when the neceſſitie of the Church, and the ſpirituall good of ſoules ſhall require the ſame; for this authoritie of <hi>declare</hi> and <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand</hi> doth not exceede the limits of ſpirituall power, as <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath ſhewed at large heretofore:<note place="margin">Widdr. <hi>in</hi> Apol <hi>nu.</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. and in all his other Bookes very often, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in his Anſwere to <hi>Fitz-herb.</hi>
               </note> But here is only denyed the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depoſe</hi> temporall Princes, to <hi>dispoſe</hi> of
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19923:53"/>their temporals, <hi>to vſe</hi> or
<hi>draw</hi> forth the temporall Sword, or to authorize temporall
<hi>Princes</hi> or ſubiects to <hi>vſe</hi> or <hi>draw</hi> forth the ſame: for whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer giueth authoritie to another man to vſe the temporall Sword, hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to vſe it himſelfe, although ſometimes for want of ſtrength or ſome other neceſſarie Inſtrument hee cannot vſe it himſelfe, yet ſtill he hath authoritie to vſe it.</p>
            <p n="7">7. And although a <hi>Commander</hi> (which I wiſh the
<hi>Reader</hi> to obſerue for the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Prelate</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi>) is commmonly ſaid to doe that thing which is done by his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, (and ſo hee that counſaileth, conſenteth, or any way concurreth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though <hi>per accidens,</hi> and not by any proper vertue, or influxe of his owne, is ſaid to doe that thing) as hee that applyeth fire to ſtraw, or comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, counſaileth, yea, or doth not hinder the applying thereof, when hee is bound to hinder it, is ſaid to burne the ſtraw, although hee bee no true and proper efficient cauſe of the burning thereof, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19923:54"/>a cauſe <hi>per accidens</hi>) yet a
<hi>Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> is not ſaid to doe that which hee commandeth, as a true and proper cauſe, or as hauing authoritie to doe that thing which hee commandeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> (whereof this <hi>Branch</hi> of the Oath doth only ſpeake) but only as a <hi>cauſe per accidens,</hi> (which according to the doctrine of all Philoſophers, is no true and proper efficient cauſe) vnleſſe by his proper power, vertue, influxe or authoritie hee concurre to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thereof, and that the perſon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded hath his power, vertue, or au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to doe that thing deriued from the <hi>Commander,</hi> or depending on him.</p>
            <p n="8">8. For which cauſe a <hi>Painter,</hi> who commandeth his Seruant to make a Picture, and giueth him rules and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how to mingle his Colours, and afterwards to apply them, which without the directions of his
<hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> hee himſelfe could not doe, is the <hi>principall</hi> cauſe and agent of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that Picture, and the Seruant is only his
<hi>Instrument</hi> or <hi>Minister,</hi> for that all the Arte hee hath to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19923:54"/>make that picture is deriued from the commaundement and directions of the Painter, and depending on him, and yet a
<hi>King,</hi> who hath no skill to paint, and commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Painter to make a picture, is no <hi>true</hi> and <hi>proper efficient</hi> cauſe of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king that picture, but onely a <hi>cauſe per accidens,</hi> by morally applying the Painter that hath skill to vſe the ſame. So likewiſe a
<hi>Prince,</hi> who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth his Officers to condemne and put to death an egregious male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, is the <hi>principall</hi> cauſe of his death, and the Officers are onely his <hi>Inſtruments, Miniſters,</hi> and
<hi>Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners,</hi> for that all the authoritie, which they haue to condemne and kill that malefactour, is deriued from the Prince, and depending on him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe onely the <hi>Prince</hi> doth <hi>autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize,</hi> or giue them <hi>authoritie</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce and execute that ſentence: And yet the
<hi>Pope</hi> commaunding a <hi>Prince</hi> to vſe his temporall ſword, power, or authoritie when the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie of the Church ſhall require the ſame, as to make warre, inuade any
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19923:55"/>Countrey, or to put any egregious malefactor to death, is onely a <hi>cauſe per accidens,</hi> of that warre, &amp;c. by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying morally, to wit, by his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, the perſon, who hath au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to make warre, &amp;c. to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereof. But the
<hi>Pope</hi> is no true and proper cauſe of that warre, &amp;c. neither can hee bee ſaid to make that warre, as <hi>hauing authoritie</hi> to make it, or as <hi>authorizing,</hi> or giuing authority, leaue, or licence, (whereof onely this <hi>branch</hi> maketh mention) to the <hi>Prince</hi> to make that warre, &amp;c. Neyther is the <hi>Prince</hi> in making that warre, &amp;c. the
<hi>Popes Inſtrument, Miniſter,</hi> or <hi>Executioner,</hi> (as the
<hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Prelate</hi> and the the <hi>Prince</hi> abſurdly affirmeth) for that he hath not his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to make warre, &amp;c. deriued from the <hi>Popes</hi> commandement, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending on it, whereas (according to the doctrine of all Philoſophers) it is neceſſary to an
<hi>Inſtrument,</hi> that it haue all it vertue to worke deriued from the
<hi>principall</hi> Agent, or depending on it; but all the authoritie, which
<hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Princes,</hi> or <hi>Common-wealths</hi> haue
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19923:55"/>in temporall affaires, is deriued from the law of <hi>Nations,</hi> or <hi>Nature,</hi> and not from the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement.</p>
            <p n="9">9. By which it is apparant, how groſly the ſaid
<hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Prelate</hi> and the <hi>Prince,</hi> in excepting againſt this <hi>Branch,</hi> was miſtaken, for not conſidering the difference betweene a <hi>Commander,</hi> who hath onely autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to
<hi>command,</hi> but not to <hi>execute,</hi> or doe that which hee commandeth to be done, and a <hi>Commander,</hi> who hath authoritie both to commaund, and alſo to execute or doe that which he commandeth to be done, although perchance he cannot effect it for want of ſtrength or effectuall meanes, but not for want of authoritie, as euerie lawfull <hi>Prince</hi> hath ſufficient authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to ſubdue his Rebels, and yet hee cannot alwaies effect it, not for want of authority, but for want of ſtrength, force, or effectuall meanes, becauſe his Rebels are more ſtrong and potent then he is.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="chapter">
            <pb n="80" facs="tcp:19923:56"/>
            <head>CHAP. III. The <hi>Third</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an
<hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q>ALſo I doe ſweare from my heart, that notwithstanding any Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, or ſentence of Excommunication, or Depriuation made or granted, or to be made or granted by the <hi>Pope</hi> or his Succeſſours, or by any Authoritie deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, or pretended to be deriued from him, or his Sea againſt the ſaid King, his Heires or Succeſſours, or any abſolution of the ſaid ſubjects from their obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: I will beare faith and true allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to his <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> his Heires and Succeſſours, and him and them will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend to the vttermoſt of my power, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſpiracies &amp; attempts what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, which ſhall be made againſt his or their Perſons, their Crowne and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, by reaſon or colour of any ſuch ſentence or declaration or otherwiſe, and will doe my beſt endeuour to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſe and make knowne vnto his <hi>Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie,</hi> his Heires &amp; Succeſſors, all Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, &amp; Traiterous Conſpiracies which I ſhall know or heare of to be againſt him or any of them.</q>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:19923:56"/>1. This <hi>Branch</hi> of the <hi>Oath</hi> is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what clearer then the former, becauſe it doth not expreſſely and in plaine tearmes deny the <hi>Popes</hi> Authoritie to <hi>depriue</hi> or
<hi>depoſe</hi> Princes, but it onely containeth in expreſſe words a promiſe, which the Subiect confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth by Oath, that if in caſe the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath denounced, or hereafter ſhould denounce any ſentence of
<hi>Excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication</hi> or <hi>Depriuation</hi> againſt the <hi>King,</hi> his Heires, or Succeſſours, or any <hi>abſolution</hi> of the ſaid Subiects from their obedience, yet <hi>he wil beare faith and true allegiance to his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, his Heires and Succeſſours, and him and them will defend, &amp;c.</hi> Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe the lawfulneſſe or iuſtice of this <hi>promiſſorie</hi> Oath ſuppoſeth for the principall ground thereof, the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the former <hi>aſſertorie</hi> Clauſe, and therefore it implieth, and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally containeth a deniall of the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depriue</hi> or <hi>depoſe</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and to <hi>abſolue</hi> Subiects fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their temporall allegiance: for that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer doth ſweare, that notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any ſentence of depriuation,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19923:57"/>or abſolution of ſubiects from their obedience made, or hereafter to be made by the <hi>Pope</hi> or his Succeſſours againſt his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> his Heires or Succeſſours, to make this promiſe iuſt and lawfull, he muſt conſequently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that the Pope <hi>hath</hi> Authoritie to depriue Princes, or to abſolue Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their obedience, as <hi>Suarez</hi> examining this <hi>Branch</hi> of the Oath doth moſt clearely demonſtrate.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Suarez <hi>in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
                  <p>See Widdring. <hi>againſt</hi> Fitz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herbert <hi>part.</hi>
1. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               </note> For if the ſentence of depriuation to be made at any time hereafter againſt the <hi>King,</hi> his Heires or Succeſſours, for any manifeſt cauſe or crime what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, may be iuſt, lawfull, and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall, it is as vnlawfull to take this
<hi>clauſe,</hi> as it is vnlawfull for one to ſweare, that he will not obey the <hi>Popes</hi> ſentence and commandement, which hereafter he ſhall impoſe, be it neuer ſo inſt, and without all errour or default: But if this ſentence of <hi>depriuation</hi> at any time hereafter to be made can neuer be iuſt, it muſt needs follow, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no more authoritie to <hi>depriue</hi> or <hi>depoſe</hi> the <hi>King,</hi> his Heires or Succeſſours,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19923:57"/>then he hath authoritie to commit open iniuſtice.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Wherefore thoſe <hi>thirteene</hi> Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Prieſts, who ſolemnly proteſted to Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that
<hi>notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any authoritie</hi> (which words are farre more generall, then notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding any ſentence of depriuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) or <hi>any Excommunication either denounced, or to be denounced againſt her</hi> Maieſtie &amp;c. <hi>they would yeeld to her</hi> Maieſtie <hi>all obedience in temporall cauſes,</hi> would then haue made no dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie to take this <hi>Branch</hi> of the Oath, and conſequently to free them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from periurie, they muſt alſo deny the <hi>Popes</hi> Authoritie to depriue and depoſe Princes, for that the iuſtice of this <hi>Branch</hi> implieth &amp; ſuppoſeth as a chiefe ground thereof a deniall of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to <hi>depriue</hi> and <hi>depoſe,</hi> as <hi>Suarez</hi> doth moſt plainely conuince.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore in this <hi>Clauſe</hi> is not denied the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate,</hi> but onely that
<hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication</hi> being a ſpirituall cenſure doth not worke this temporall effect,
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19923:58"/>as to make <hi>Kings</hi> no <hi>Kings,</hi> or to de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>priue them of their <hi>Royall</hi> right and Soueraigntie, and conſequently not to <hi>abſolue</hi> Subiects from their natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall allegiance, which, according to the doctrine of Card. <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and
<hi>Suarez</hi> they doe by the <hi>law</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and Nature owe to their lawfull Prince.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Bell. <hi>in Tract. contra Barclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um cap.</hi> 21.
<hi>pag.</hi> 202.</p>
                  <p>Suarez <hi>in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. &amp;c. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.
<hi>nu.</hi> 6.</p>
               </note> And thus much his <hi>Maiestie</hi> hath alſo in expreſſe words declared. <hi>The truth is,</hi> ſaith his
<hi>Maiestie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>The</hi> Kings <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie in his</hi> Premonition <hi>&amp;c. pag.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>that the Lower houſe of Parliament at the firſt framing of this Oath, made it to containe, that the</hi> Pope <hi>had no power to Excommunicate mee, which I forced them to reforme onely making it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that no Excommunication of the</hi> Popes
<hi>can warrant my Subiects to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe againſt my Perſon or State, deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the depoſition of</hi> Kings <hi>to be in the</hi> Popes <hi>lawfull power, as indeede I take any ſuch temporall violence to be farre without the limits of ſuch a ſpirituall cenſure as Excommunication is,</hi> And alſo that depriuation or depoſition from temporall kingdomes is not an effect of Excommunicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath ſhewed at large heretofore,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19923:58"/>and <hi>Becanus</hi> and <hi>Suarez</hi> doe alſo in expreſſe words affirme the ſame.<note place="margin">Widdrington
<hi>in his</hi> Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie <hi>nu.</hi> 346. <hi>in his</hi> Anſwer <hi>to Suarez part.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect.</hi> 4. <hi>and in his</hi> Anſwer
<hi>to</hi> Fitzher. <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence it is very appara<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> ſaith <hi>Becanus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Becanus
<hi>in queſt. de fide haereticis ſeruan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da ca.</hi> 8. <hi>nu.</hi> 16.
<hi>and in his</hi> Controuerſia Anglic. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>qu.</hi>
2.</note> 
               <hi>that Heretikes by this preciſely that they are excommunicated, are not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of their Dominion or Iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on either ouer their ſubiects, or ouer their temporall goods, but this depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is a destinct puniſhment, and infli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by a destinct law.</hi> And againe, <hi>It is one thing,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>to excommunicate a King, and another thing to depoſe him, or depriue him of his Kingdome, neither is the one neceſſarily connected with the other. Many Kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours haue beene excommunicated, and yet not therefore depoſed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe many depoſed, and yet not therefore excommunicated.</hi> See alſo
<hi>Suarez</hi> cited by <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his <hi>Apologie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>tom.</hi> 5. <hi>diſp.</hi> 15. <hi>ſect.</hi> 6.
<hi>nu.</hi> 3.</note> and in his anſwere to <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> and
<hi>Fitzherbert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. And therefore in very truth I am ſorie, and doe in ſome ſort pittie the <hi>Author</hi> of the <hi>Prelate</hi> and the
<hi>Prince</hi> (a man whom heretofo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e I haue much loued, reſpected, and honoured) that he ſhould ſo groſly forget himſelfe, as
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19923:59"/>to bewray ſo palpably ſuch great want of learning, iudgement, and ſinceritie, in affirming ſo boldly, and without any proofe at all,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pag.</hi> 298.</note>
               <hi>that depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of Regall authoritie is an effect of excommunicating Kings and Princes, and ſo in denying the effect, the cauſe is denyed. For as,</hi> ſaith he,
<hi>if you ſhould ſay,</hi> A man is not <hi>riſibilis,</hi> that is,
<hi>hath not power to laugh, you ſhould deny him to be a man, ſo in denying that the</hi> Pope <hi>can depriue</hi> Princes <hi>of their King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, you deny in effect that he can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate.</hi> Whereas this <hi>Authour</hi> knew right well, that <hi>Widdrington</hi> in that very <hi>Chapter</hi> which hee citeth, did, by the expreſſe doctrine of <hi>Sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rez</hi> and
<hi>Becanus,</hi> but now related, cleerely prooue againſt
<hi>Leſſius,</hi> (who vrged euen as nakedly and without any proofe at all the ſame obiection) that <hi>depriuation</hi> is no <hi>effect</hi> at all of
<hi>Excommunication,</hi> much leſſe <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prium quarto modo,</hi> as
<hi>riſibilis, a power to laugh is to a man,</hi> as this <hi>Authour</hi> moſt vnlearnedly affirmeth. And yet <hi>forſooth</hi> he taketh vpon him, as it may appeare by the very <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Inſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:19923:59"/>of his <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> to giue a <hi>full In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and appeaſement to the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of Engliſh Catholikes concerning the Oath of Allegiance.</hi> But this ſhall ſuffice at this preſent for an imperfect portraying of this <hi>Authours</hi> want of iudgement and ſinceritie in his <hi>Expli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> of the Oath of
<hi>Allegiance,</hi> (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially if wee conſider his perſon, the Office hee now beareth, and the doctrine which in former times hee held) for that (as I am told) his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Picture both in this and other points is alreadie drawne, and will be ſet forth in liuely colours ere it be long.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is euident by the former Obſeruations, that thoſe wordes [<hi>Heires and Succeſſours</hi>] doe not ſignifie <hi>Vſurpers,</hi> as ſome would wreſt them contrarie to the meaning of the Law, the plaine and common ſignification of the wordes, and the rules before alleaged: For albeit this word [<hi>Succeſſour</hi>] may in generall bee taken for euery Succeſſour, who ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther vnlawfully or vnlawfull doth ſucceed, yet particularly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19923:60"/>when it is placed in a <hi>Law,</hi> it is v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually taken only for a <hi>lawfull Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour:</hi> wherefore according to that rule of the <hi>Ciuill Law</hi> before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the ſecond <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> that <hi>the doubtfull words of euery Law must be taken in that ſenſe, which is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out default,</hi> this word
[<hi>Succeſſours</hi>] muſt in this <hi>Oath</hi> eſtabliſhed by His
<hi>Maieſties</hi> Law bee limited only to <hi>lawfull Succeſſours,</hi> and who accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Lawes of the Kingdome doe ſucceed. For as according to Law, <hi>Id tantum poſſumus quod iure poſſumus: We can only doe that, which wee can doe lawfully or by Law,</hi> ſo according to Law, he only is accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to <hi>ſucceed,</hi> who by lawfull right doth
<hi>ſucced.</hi> Whereupon the <hi>Ciuill Lawyers</hi> doe define
<hi>Inheritance,</hi> to <hi>be a ſucceding to all the right of one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed,</hi> and <hi>an Heire, who ſucceedeth him in all his right,</hi> without adding <hi>lawfull</hi> ſucceeding, or <hi>lawfully</hi> ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, for that it is alwayes ſo to bee vnderſtood, and therefore being ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſuppoſed, it is not expreſſed, but altogether omitted in the defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:19923:60"/>of an <hi>Heire</hi> and of
<hi>Inheritance.</hi> And whenſoeuer in the <hi>Common</hi> or
<hi>Statute</hi> Lawes of this Kingdome any mention is made of the
<hi>King</hi> and his <hi>Succeſſours,</hi> this word [<hi>lawfull</hi>] is but few times added, although alwayes it ought to be vnderſtood.</p>
            <p n="6">6, <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is alſo euident by the former Obſeruations, that by thoſe words [<hi>Treaſons and Trayterous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies</hi>] are only vnderſtood true, proper, and naturall Treaſons, and which among all Nations, what Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion ſoeuer they profeſſe, are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and repugnant to natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Alleagiance and Temporall and Ciuill Obedience, and not ſuch Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, which in regard chiefly of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion are by the poſitiue Lawes of ſome Nations made <hi>Treaſons,</hi> and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted <hi>Treaſons</hi> onely for that they are puniſhed with the penalties which are due to proper and naturall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, as are the comming in of Engliſh Prieſts into this Kingdome made by the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, and all reconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the
<hi>Pope,</hi> though in matters that concerne Religion. For as His
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19923:61"/>
               <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the <hi>Parliament</hi> haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, the only intent of this <hi>Oath is to contayn the profeſſion of naturall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, and ſuch ciuill and temporall dutie and obedience, which euery true and well-affected ſubiect ought by the Law of God to beare to their lawfull Prince and Soueraigne with a promiſe to reſist and diſcloſe all contrarie vnciuill violence.</hi> For to preuent ſuch hainous attempts and miſchiefes, which in time to come might be plotted by the example of the <hi>Powder-Traytours,</hi> who vnder colour of Religion at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted that barbarous and deuilliſh Conſpiracie, <hi>this forme of Oath was framed,</hi> ſaith His <hi>Maiestie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, <hi>pag.</hi> 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 2.</note> to bee ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>by all my ſubiects, whereby they ſhould make cleere profeſſion of their reſolution, faithfully to perſiſt in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence vnto me, acrording to their naturall Allegiance; to the end that I might hereby make a ſeparation, not only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene all my good ſubiects in generall, and vnfaithfull Traytours that inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to draw themſelues from my Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience; but ſpecially to make a ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion betweene ſo many of my ſubiects,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19923:61"/>who although they were otherwiſe Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected, yet retayned in their hearts the print of their naturall dutie to their Soueraigne; and thoſe who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing carryed away with the like fanati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call zeale, that the</hi> Powder-Traytours <hi>were, could not contayne themſelues within the bounds of their naturall Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, but thought diuerſitie of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion a ſafe pretext for all kinde of Treaſons and Rebellions against their Soueraigne.</hi> Wherby it is apparant, that only ſuch
<hi>Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Trayte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Conſpiracies</hi> are here vnderſtood, which are repugnant and contrarie to <hi>naturall Allegiance,</hi> and not ſuch <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> which are not <hi>naturall Treaſons,</hi> but only in regard of Religion are by poſitiue Lawes made
<hi>Treaſons,</hi> and to be puniſhed with the ordinary penalties of true proper and <hi>naturall Treaſon.</hi> And in this ſenſe alſo thoſe
<hi>thirteene Reuerend Prieſts</hi> vnderſtood the words
<hi>Conſpiracies, Attempts,</hi> and <hi>Practiſes</hi> in their
<hi>Protestation.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="chapter">
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:19923:62"/>
            <head>CHAP. IIII. The <hi>Fourth</hi> Branch of the Oath and an
<hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q> "ANd I doe further ſweare, That I doe from my heart abhorre, detest, and abiure, as impious and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticall this damnable doctrine, and poſition, That Princes which bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated or depriued by the
<hi>Pope,</hi> may be depoſed or murthered by their ſubiects, or any other what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer.</q>
            <p n="1">1. Although this <hi>Branch</hi> may at the firſt ſight ſeeme ſomewhat ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in regard of that word <hi>hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call,</hi> yet if it be duly examined, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former Obſeruations, it will eaſily appeare, that it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth no ſuch difficultie, as ſome im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugners of the Oath would ſeeme to imagine, but that if it bee lawfull to
<hi>abhorre, detest,</hi> and <hi>abiure</hi> the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid poſition, as
<hi>cleerely falſe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurious</hi> to Princes, which the former Diſcourſe doth plainly conuince, it is
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19923:62"/>alſo lawfull to abiure it as
<hi>hereticall:</hi> or, which is all one, as contayning in it a falſhood, which is repugnant not onely to naturall reaſon, but alſo to the Word of God reuealed in the holy Scriptures: For, as euery Doctrine and poſition, which is agreeable to that truth, which God hath reuealed, is to be accounted
<hi>of faith:</hi> ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riwiſe, euerie Doctrine and poſition, which contayneth in it a falſhood, which is repugnant to the Word of God reuealed in the holy Scriptures, is to be accounted <hi>hereticall,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to <hi>faith.</hi> And in this ſence, the word <hi>hereticall</hi> is not onely by all <hi>Protestants,</hi> but alſo by many learned Catholique Diuines commonly and vſually taken, as <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath ſhewed at large in his anſwer to <hi>Fitz herbert.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his <hi>Adioinder</hi> to the
<hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>ſecond</hi> part.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Neyther is it neceſſarie, that we muſt take the word <hi>hereticall,</hi> as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe no other ambiguous word con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned in this Oath, in that ſtrict and rigorous ſenſe, wherein ſome Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes take the word <hi>hereticall,</hi> to wit, for that doctrine which not onely
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19923:63"/>contayneth a falſhood repugnant to the holy Scriptures, but alſo which by the <hi>Church</hi> or a <hi>generall Councell,</hi> which repreſenteth the <hi>Church,</hi> is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly and particularly declared and defined ſo to be, but it ſufficeth that we take the word, <hi>hereticall,</hi> in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and vſuall ſignification, and wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Catholickes doe commonly take it, eſpecially when this common ſenſe is agreeable to the meaning and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the Law-maker: for that, according to the approued rule be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſet downe in the
<hi>ſecond</hi> obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in a penall and odious matter, when the wordes of any Law are doubtfull or ambiguous, and there be many common ſenſes of the ſame word or ſentence, we ought to take them in that common ſenſe, which is more <hi>fauourable,</hi> eſpecially when it is not againſt the meaning of the Law-maker.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Neither alſo is it neceſſarie to make any Doctrine or Poſition to be <hi>hereticall,</hi> that the propoſition with all particular circumſtances therein expreſſed, muſt bee contained in the
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:19923:63"/>holy Scriptures, but it ſufficeth, that it contain a <hi>particular</hi> falſhood, which onely in the <hi>generall</hi> is expreſſed in the holy Scriptures, and that no <hi>particular</hi> word, or circumſtance bee added in the <hi>particular</hi> propoſition, which doth make it not to be contayned in the <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> falſhood, as a
<hi>particular</hi> in the <hi>vniuerſall.</hi> For which cauſe, theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, <hi>It is lawfull for one to take from his neighbour his purſe, or to mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther him with a piſtoll, if hee liue a wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton or wicked life,</hi> are <hi>hereticall,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugnant to thoſe words of holy Scripture, <hi>Thou ſhalt not steale, Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.</note> although thoſe
<hi>particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities</hi> of being a <hi>wanton</hi> or <hi>wicked</hi> man, or of killing him with a <hi>piſtoll,</hi> are not expreſly contained in the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, becauſe they doe not giue any warrant to ſtealing or killing, or make that <hi>particular</hi> ſtealing or killing not be included in thoſe <hi>generall</hi> words, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale, Thou ſhalt not kill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore, although by
<hi>rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of the <hi>matter</hi> of this <hi>Branch</hi> we may truely abiure as <hi>hereticall,</hi> not onely
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19923:64"/>the Doctrine of <hi>murthering,</hi> but alſo of <hi>depoſing Princes, which are excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated or depriued by the Pope,</hi> yet if we onely regard the <hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of the expreſſe words, according to the plaine and common ſenſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them, to which the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth clauſe</hi> of the Oath tyeth the ſwearer, we are not bound to abiure both Doctrines as
<hi>hereticall,</hi> but it ſufficeth, by <hi>vertue</hi> of the
<hi>words,</hi> to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure as <hi>hereticall,</hi> onely the Doctrine of
<hi>murthering</hi> ſuch Princes, as <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath ſhewed in his <hi>Theologi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Diſputation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In his Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>log.
<hi>Diſp.</hi> cap. 5. Sec. 2.</note> and proued more at large in his
<hi>Anſwer</hi> to <hi>Fitzherbert,</hi> in the end of the <hi>ſecond part.</hi> And the reaſon is, for that to make <hi>hereticall</hi> a
<hi>conditionall diſiunctiue</hi> propoſition, which implyeth a free choyce to take eyther part of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> if wee pleaſe, it ſufficeth that one part of the diſiunction be <hi>hereticall,</hi> although the other part be not hereticall, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chance moſt true and of faith, which contrariwiſe happeneth in an <hi>abſolute</hi> diſiunctiue propoſition, which ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth and implyeth no ſuch condition
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:19923:64"/>or choyce. As for example, This pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition,
<hi>It is lawfull for any man to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour or blaſpheme God, if hee will,</hi> or, which is all one in ſence with this, <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man may lawfully honour or blaſpheme God,</hi> is falſe and <hi>hereticall,</hi> and may be abiured as
<hi>hereticall,</hi> although one part only thereof be <hi>hereticall,</hi> and the other part of faith: For ſuch <hi>conditional diſiunctiue</hi> propoſitions, for as much as concerneth the truth or falſhood of them, doe not follow the nature of an <hi>abſolute</hi> and ordinarie
<hi>diſiunctiue</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, but of a <hi>copulatiue</hi> propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to the veritie whereof is required, that both parts muſt be true, and to make it falſe and <hi>hereticall,</hi> it ſufficeth that onely one part thereof bee falſe and <hi>hereticall,</hi> whereas contrariwiſe to the veritie of an <hi>abſolute diſiunctiue</hi> propoſition, which implyeth no ſuch choyce or condition, it ſufficeth that one part thereof be true, and to make it falſe and <hi>hereticall,</hi> both parts ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of muſt needes be falſe and <hi>hereticall:</hi> for which cauſe this propoſition, <hi>God is honoured or blaſphemed by good and vertuous men,</hi> is true, becauſe one part
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19923:65"/>of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> is true, and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, <hi>God is honoured and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by good and vertuous men,</hi> is falſe, becauſe both parts of the propoſition are not falſe, but one of them is true.</p>
            <p n="8">8. That this propoſition, <hi>Subiects may lawfully depoſe, or murther their Prince, who is excommunicated or depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the Pope,</hi> or which in ſence is all one with the Doctrine and poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contayned in this <hi>Branch</hi> of the Oath (ſeeing that onely the Verbe
<hi>paſſiue</hi> is changed into the <hi>actiue</hi>) is ſuch a
<hi>conditionall diſiunctiue</hi> propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as implyeth a free choyce and condition to take eyther part of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> if wee pleaſe, as likewiſe all ſuch <hi>diſiunctiue</hi> propoſitions, wherein the Coniunction [<hi>or</hi>] followeth the Verbe [<hi>may</hi>] doe imply and ſuppoſe, according to the vſuall ſignification of our Engliſh phraſe, a free choyſe and condition to take eyther part of the
<hi>diſiunction</hi> if we pleaſe, <hi>Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> proueth by many examples of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, neyther can there be alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſcarce any one propoſition,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:19923:65"/>wherein it is not commonly ſo taken. As for example, <hi>You may ſtay here or depart: You may eat or drinke: you may buy in ſuch a place Wine or Oyle: You may haue in the ſhambles Beefe or Mut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton: You may goe to ſuch a place by land or by water: You may buy that land in fee-farme or by leaſe. The King by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of an Act of Parliament, may take of conuicted Popiſh Recuſants, twentie pounds for euerie moneth, or the third part of all their lands. The Sherife may preſently hang a theefe condemned to die, or delay his death for ſome ſmall time. If any perſon hold any lands of any other Lord, then of the King, by Knights ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice, he may giue, dispoſe, or aſſure by his laſt Will and Teſtament, two parts of the ſaid lands holden by Knights ſeruice, or of as much thereof as ſhall amount to the full yearely value of two parts. If a man by his laſt Will and Testament ordayne, that his Executors may beſtow twentie pounds vpon the poore, or repayre ſuch a Bridge,</hi> it is in the free power of the Executor to chuſe whether of thoſe two he pleaſe. Finally, <hi>in clauſes of reuocation, where the words are, That one
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:19923:66"/>may by any deed in his life time, or by his laſt Will and Teſtament, reuoke the ſayd vſes, and limit new,</hi> it is in his free pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and choyce, to doe it by the one or by the other, as he ſhall thinke good. In theſe, &amp; infinite ſuch like examples, which may bee brought, the Verbe [<hi>may</hi>] implyeth a free power to chuſe eyther part of the <hi>diſiunction</hi> one plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, neyther can there ſcarcely bee alledged any one example, wherein the Coniunction diſiunctiue
[<hi>or</hi>] im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly following the Verbe [<hi>may</hi>] is not commonly ſo taken: and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially when the latter part of the
<hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iunction,</hi> which is affirmed, is no way leſſe certayne, but rather more cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then the former part: which note, I wiſh the
<hi>Reader</hi> to obſerue chiefly for the Doctrine of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent clauſe, which doth not affirme, that <hi>Princes</hi> beeing excommunicated or depriued by the Pope, may be <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> or <hi>depoſed</hi> by their ſubiects, for then ſome might imagine the ſenſe to be that ſuch
<hi>Princes</hi> may be <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered</hi> or <hi>at leaſt wiſe depoſed,</hi> becauſe the depoſing of ſuch <hi>Princes,</hi> is leſſer
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:19923:66"/>then the <hi>murthering</hi> of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſeeing that it is affirmed, that ſuch <hi>Princes</hi> may be
<hi>depoſed</hi> or <hi>murthered,</hi> it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that the Coniunction [<hi>or</hi>] can not ſignifie <hi>at leaſt wiſe,</hi> becauſe if the Doctrine of <hi>depoſing</hi> ſuch Princes may be abiured as <hi>hereticall,</hi> much more and not much leſſe the Doctrine of
<hi>murthering</hi> them may bee abiured as <hi>hereticall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. And by this it is apparant, that to abiure as
<hi>hereticall</hi> this Doctrine, &amp; <hi>conditionall</hi> diſiunctiue poſition, <hi>That Princes which be excommunicated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued by the Pope, may be depoſed or murthered by their ſubiects, or any other whatſoeuer;</hi> it ſufficeth by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of the
<hi>words,</hi> onely to abiure as <hi>hereticall</hi> the Doctrine of
<hi>murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> ſuch Princes, although, <hi>by reaſon</hi> of the
<hi>matter,</hi> it be lawfull (as you ſhal ſee forthwith) to abiure as
<hi>hereticall</hi> not onely the Doctrine of <hi>murthering,</hi> but alſo of <hi>depoſing</hi> ſuch Princes.</p>
            <p n="10">10. That the Doctrine of <hi>murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> ſuch Princes is <hi>hereticall,</hi> or, which is all one, contayneth in it a
<hi>manifest falſhood,</hi> which is repugnant to the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:19923:67"/>
               <hi>Word</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> it is euident by thoſe two places of holy <hi>Scripture</hi> cited by <hi>Widdrington, Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> Exod. 20. which words are generall and common to euerie vniuſt <hi>killing,</hi> and <hi>Kill him not, for who ſhall extend his hand vpon the Lords annoynted, and bee innocent,</hi> 1. Reg. 26. Which wordes are proper and peculiar to the <hi>mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering</hi> of Princes. Neyther doth the <hi>excommunicating,</hi> or <hi>depriuing</hi> of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces by the
<hi>Pope,</hi> which are added in this Doctrine and poſition, giue ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient warrant to <hi>murther</hi> ſuch Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, although wee ſhould admit that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to depriue them; for that
<hi>Excommunication</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priueth onely of ſpirituall graces, and
<hi>depriuation</hi> onely of temporall King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, but neyther of them of cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall life, as <hi>Suarez</hi> alſo confeſſeth.<note place="margin">Suarez <hi>in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. &amp;c. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 4.
<hi>nu.</hi> 10. <hi>&amp; ſeq.</hi>
               </note> Yea we may truely abiure as
<hi>manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> falſe, damnable, and repugnant to thoſe words of holy Scriptures, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill,</hi> and conſequently as
<hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall,</hi> this Doctrine and poſition, <hi>That it is lawfull for euery man to kill a male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factour, who is condemned by the Iudge
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:19923:67"/>to dye,</hi> for that the ſentence of death denounced againſt him by the Iudge doth not giue leaue, licence, warrant, and commiſſion to euerie man to put him to death, but onely to the
<hi>She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rife,</hi> or others, who are appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Executioners</hi> of iuſtice in that caſe.</p>
            <p n="11">11. That the Doctrine alſo of <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing</hi> ſuch Princes is <hi>hereticall,</hi> and contayneth a <hi>manifeſt</hi> falſhood repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the Word of God, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent; for that to take away by force and violence the Crowne and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of a <hi>Prince</hi> who is in poſſeſſion thereof, only vpon a probable or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſed title, is open iniuſtice, as you haue ſeene before in the <hi>fift Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation;</hi> and conſequently <hi>Theft</hi> and <hi>Rapine</hi> in a moſt high degree, and therefore repugnant both to that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Decalogue, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> and to the <hi>third</hi> Commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother,</hi> wherein the honour and reuerence, which is due from ſubiects to their <hi>Prince,</hi> who is the
<hi>Father</hi> of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, is according to the doctrine of all
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:19923:68"/>Diuines included, and it is alſo ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally againſt that commaundement of our Sauiour, <hi>Render to Caeſar the things that are Caeſars,</hi> which precept inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth alſo the <hi>negatiue,</hi> not to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from <hi>Caeſar</hi> that which is his due,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Matth.</hi> 22.</note> as contrariwiſe that precept, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſteale,</hi> includeth alſo the
<hi>affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matiue,</hi> to render and reſtore backe what hath beene wrongfully taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. Wherefore there is no more ſcruple to be made, to abiure the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Doctrine and poſition as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, damnable, and
<hi>heretical,</hi> then to abiure it as <hi>manifestly falſe</hi> and
<hi>iniuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> to Princes, ſeeing that the <hi>mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt falſhood</hi> and <hi>iniustice</hi> contayned therein, is expreſly repugnant to the word and commaundement of God reuealed to vs in the holy Scriptures: and it is alſo grounded vpon theſe two manifeſt principles, and which without manifeſt impudency cannot be denyed by any man; The
<hi>one,</hi> that it is a contouerſie among Catholicks, whether the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to depriue <hi>Princes,</hi> &amp; the
<hi>other,</hi> that it is open iniuſtice to depoſe, or to thruſt
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:19923:68"/>one out of his poſſeſſion vpon a title, which is not moſt certaine but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie.</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Lastly,</hi> I wiſh the <hi>Reader</hi> to conſider the <hi>third</hi> and laſt expoſition of this <hi>Branch,</hi> which <hi>Widdrington</hi> brought in his <hi>Theologicall Disputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and defendeth at large in, his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere</hi> to <hi>Fitz-herberts</hi> Reply againſt the ſame, to wit, that albeit in <hi>regard</hi> of the
<hi>matter,</hi> wee may lawfully ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure <hi>for heretical,</hi> the doctrine not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of <hi>murthering,</hi> but alſo of <hi>deſpoſing</hi> Princes,
<hi>which bee excommunicated or depriued by the Pope,</hi> yet, by
<hi>force</hi> and <hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>wordes,</hi> wee are not bound to abiure either the doctrine of <hi>depoſing,</hi> or alſo of
<hi>murthering</hi> ſuch Princes, <hi>for hereticall,</hi> but only <hi>as hereticall,</hi> that is, for a very falſe and iniurious doctrine in the higheſt degree almoſt of fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood and iniuſtice, and which there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in regard of the abhorring, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, and abiuring thereof, hath ſome reſemblance and ſimilitude with <hi>hereticall</hi> doctrine, although we take the word <hi>hereticall</hi> in the moſt
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:19923:69"/>ſtrict and rigorous ſenſe that may be. And the reaſon is, for that the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerbe [<hi>as</hi>] being an Aduerbe of ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude, doth properly and vſually by <hi>force</hi> and
<hi>vertue</hi> of the <hi>word</hi> denote only a ſimilitude, and if at any time it ſignifie an identitie, equalitie, or realtie, as (ſometimes it doth, but moſt commonly it doth not) it is not by force of the <hi>word,</hi> but only in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the matter, to which it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed. And this
<hi>Explication</hi> will ſerue very well to conuince the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe of him, who out of his ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred to this Oath, will contrarie to all reaſon, and the rules before aſſigned out of <hi>Suarez,</hi> needes haue the word
<hi>hereticall</hi> to bee taken only for that, which the definition of the Church maketh <hi>hereticall,</hi> and which before was not
<hi>hereticall,</hi> although it was moſt euidently falſe, and repugnant to the holy Scriptures, and the word <hi>impious</hi> only for that, which is againſt pietie, which is due to God or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Parents, albeit otherwiſe it bee neuer ſo wicked and iniurious to <hi>Princes</hi> who are the Fathers of the
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:19923:69"/>Countrie. For we may verie well an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere him, that the Aduerbe <hi>as</hi> being an Aduerbe of ſimilitude, and by force of the <hi>word,</hi> and, according to the plaine and common ſenſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of the ſame, ſignifying only a ſimilitude, &amp; not a reality, but in regard of the matter to which it is referred, doth in this
<hi>Branch</hi> denote only a <hi>ſimilitude</hi> of that ſtrict and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous <hi>Hereſie</hi> and <hi>Impietie,</hi> becauſe the matter, to which it is applyed, will not ſuffer it to ſignifie a doctrine
<hi>impious</hi> and <hi>hereticall</hi> in that ſtrict and rigorous manner, but only by way of compariſon and ſimilitude: and then the ſenſe and meaning of this <hi>Branch</hi> is, that I doe abhorre, deteſt, and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iure that doctrine and poſition as <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious</hi> and <hi>hereticall,</hi> that is, in a moſt high degree of horror and deteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not much vnlike to the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of that doctrine, which is <hi>impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> and
<hi>hereticall,</hi> in that ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much ſtrict and rigorous manner. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe this <hi>Explication,</hi> as hath beene ſhewed aboue, is not neceſſary, but only for ſuch wilfull perſons, as do
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:19923:70"/>ſeeke to expound the wordes of the
<hi>Oath</hi> in the moſt odious ſenſe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the plaine and common vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding of them, and the true meaning of the Law-maker.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. V. The <hi>Fift</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an
<hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q>ANd I doe beleeue, and in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence am reſolued, that neither the <hi>Pope</hi> nor any perſon whatſoeuer hath power to abſolue me of this Oath, or any part thereof.</q>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Clauſe</hi> hath in it no more difficultie, then is in the former, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it implieth, ſuppoſeth, and is grounded vpon the iuſtice and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of the <hi>Third</hi> and
<hi>Second</hi> Branch. <hi>Firſt,</hi> therefore by thoſe wordes. [<hi>And I doe beleeue</hi>] is not vnderſtood a <hi>ſupernaturall</hi> beliefe, but only a morall credulitie, as the next wordes [<hi>and in conſcience am reſolued</hi>] which are an explication of the former, doe ſufficiently declare: and the ſenſe of them is, that I doe thinke and am
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19923:70"/>perſwaded in my conſcience, that
<hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Pope, &amp;c.</hi> For it cannot with any reaſon be imagined, that the words which are laſt added, muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh, but rather increaſe, or at leaſt wiſe more fully declare the truth and veritie of the former wordes: As for example, it were vnaptly ſpoken to ſay, that
<hi>ſuch a one is a man,</hi> and alſo <hi>a liuing creature;</hi> Princes
<hi>may be mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and alſo depoſed by the Pope: I doe moſt certainly beleeue ſo, and alſo I doe thinke or am perſwaded ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the meaning of this <hi>Clauſe</hi> is not to deny the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>abſolue,</hi> or diſpence in Oaths in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, but only <hi>in this Oath, or any part thereof,</hi> as the expreſſe wordes doe plainly ſignifie; neither doth it follow, that becauſe the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot diſpence in this Oath, therefore hee cannot in other Oaths, wherein there is not the like reaſon as of this, or that becauſe hee can diſpenſe in other Oaths, wherein there is not the like reaſon, therefore hee can diſpence in this.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> neither is it the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:19923:71"/>of this <hi>Clauſe,</hi> that if perchance any one ſhould offend God by taking this Oath againſt his conſcience, thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it to be vnlawfull, the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not power to abſolue him in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Penance from the guilt of ſinne thereby committed, but only the meaning is, that <hi>the Pope hath not power to abſolue</hi> or diſpence, <hi>with any man in this Oath, or any part thereof,</hi> that is, to free, releaſe, and diſcharge him from performing any of thoſe things, which in this Oath hee hath promiſed to performe, or, which is all one, to giue him leaue or licence to do againſt that, which in this <hi>Oath</hi> hee hath promiſed to doe, or not to doe. For all the parts and parcels of this
<hi>Oath</hi> are either <hi>aſſertorie,</hi> as <hi>that Our Soueraigne Lord King</hi> Iames <hi>is lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, &amp;c. and that the Pope hath not any power or authoritie to depoſe him, &amp;c. or to au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize any forraigne Prince to inuade or annoy Him or His Countries, or to diſcharge any of His ſubiects of their Allegiance, &amp;c. and that from my heart I doe abhorre, deteſt, and abiure
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:19923:71"/>as impious and hereticall, &amp;c.</hi> and no
<hi>aſſertorie Oaths</hi> can bee diſpenced withall, neither hath the
<hi>Pope</hi> any power or authoritie, according to the receiued doctrine of all Diuines, to abſolue any man from the bond of theſe kind of Oaths;<note place="margin">So S. <hi>Thom.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 89. <hi>ar.</hi> 9. and all other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines.</note> And the reaſon is, becauſe the matter of an
<hi>aſſertorie Oath</hi> being of an act preſent or paſt, is now made altogether neceſſarie and irreuocable, for that as ſoone as euer the Oath is made, it is either true or falſe by reaſon of the truth or falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of the act which now is paſt. Wherefore ſeeing that it is impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that the act which is paſt, be not paſt, ſo alſo it is impoſſible, that the <hi>Popes</hi> Diſpenſation or Abſolution can alter it or recall it: for it is impoſſible, that the act of ſwearing, which is now, or hath beene true, be not now, or hath not beene true: Or elſe they are
<hi>promiſſorie,</hi> to wit, wherein ſome thing is promiſed for the future time to bee done, or not to be done. And only theſe kinde of Oathes can bee diſpenced withall. For as well ſaith Saint <hi>Thomas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Thom.</hi> 2. 2. q. 89. <hi>ar.</hi> 7.</note> with whome all other
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:19923:72"/>Diuines doe herein agree, <hi>the bond of an Oath is referred to ſome thing which is to bee performed or omit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, wherefore it doth not appertayne to an aſſertorie Oath which is of a thing preſent or past, but only to a promiſſorie Oath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Now in this <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance only <hi>three things</hi> are promiſed by the ſwearer, all which are contained in the
<hi>third</hi> Branch; to wit, that <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding any declaration or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Excommunication or depriua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made or to bee made against the</hi> Kings Maieſtie, <hi>his Heires or Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,</hi> Firſt,
<hi>he will beare faith, and true allegiance to his</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>his Heires and Succeſſors:</hi> Secondly, <hi>hee will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend them to the vttermost of his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er against all Conſpiracies &amp;c. and</hi> Thirdly,
<hi>he wil make known vnto them all Treaſons &amp; trayterous Conſpiracies, which hee ſhall know or heare of to bee made against any of them.</hi> Wherefore there is no more difficultie in this <hi>Clauſe,</hi> then is in the <hi>third,</hi> whereon this <hi>Clauſe</hi> is chiefely grounded. And therefore it is moſt euident, that the
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:19923:72"/>
               <hi>Pope</hi> hath no more authoritie to
<hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue,</hi> or diſpence in any of theſe <hi>three</hi> things, which the ſwearer promiſeth, then hee hath authoritie to <hi>depoſe the King,</hi> and to make him no King: for that it is moſt certaine, as Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine</hi> him ſelfe confeſſeth,<note place="margin">Bell. <hi>in Tract. contra</hi> Barclai. <hi>cap.</hi> 21.
<hi>pag.</hi> 202.</note> that <hi>Subiects are bound by the Law of God to beare faith and true Allegiance</hi> (which includeth the reſiſting and diſcloſing of all Treaſons and Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Conſpiracies) <hi>to their lawfull Prince, ſo long as he remaineth Prince:</hi> ſeeing that it is euident, as well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth <hi>Suarez,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Suarez <hi>in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſ. &amp;c. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 3 <hi>num.</hi> 3.</note> that
<hi>the obligation of obedience in any degree or ſtate whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth ſo long endure in the ſubiect, as the dignitie, or power and iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth endure in the Superiour, for theſe are corelatiues, and the one de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendeth on the other.</hi> Therefore it is manifeſt, that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath no more authoritie to <hi>abſolue,</hi> or diſpenſe
<hi>in this Oath, or any part thereof,</hi> to wit, in thoſe <hi>three</hi> things before mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, then hee hath to make <hi>Kings</hi> no
<hi>Kings,</hi> and to depriue them of their <hi>Regall</hi> dignitie, power, and iuriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:19923:73"/>5. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> neither is it the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this <hi>Clauſe,</hi> that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not any power to <hi>abſolue</hi> the ſwearer from the promiſe which hee maketh to performe thoſe <hi>three</hi> things mentioned in the <hi>third</hi> Branch, only with this reduplication, as it is ſworne or confirmed by Oath, or, which is all one, only from the ſacred and religious bond of the Oath; but the meaning is, that the <hi>Pope hath not authoritie to abſolue from this Oath or any part thereof</hi> for as much it concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the ciuill and naturall obligation of temporall Allegiance; both for that, when it is ſaid that the
<hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to abſolue one from an Oath, which he hath made to doe ſome certaine thing, the meaning is, (according to the plaine and proper ſignification of the words, the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Doctrine of all Diuines, and the vſuall practices of <hi>Popes,</hi> who when they abſolue from any Oath, they abſolue from all obligation whatſoeuer contained therein<note place="margin">See the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons <hi>Nos San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum, Iuratos, Abſolutos.</hi>
               </note>) that the <hi>Pope,</hi> hath authoritie to releaſe him of that promiſe, and to giue
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:19923:73"/>him leaue to doe otherwiſe then hee hath promiſed by Oath to doe: And alſo for that his <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the State, according to whoſe meaning eſpecially the doubtfull words of this Oath are to bee vnderſtood and determined, doe little regard this ſubtile quircke of refined wits, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the <hi>Pope</hi> hath power to abſolue his
<hi>Maiesties</hi> ſubiects from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred and religious bond of their na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall Allegiance, or, which is all one, only as it is ſworne, or confirmed by Oath, ſo that notwithſtanding the releaſing of this ſacred bond, they may bee aſſured, that the ciuill and naturall obligation of the ſubiects temporall Allegiance, to the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation whereof this
<hi>Oath</hi> is ſuperad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, doth remaine inuiolable, and indiſpenſable, and by the <hi>Popes</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie cannot any way be diſſolued or diminiſhed, but that his <hi>Subiects,</hi> although they might by the
<hi>Popes</hi> authoritie bee abſolued from the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred bond of their Allegiance as it is confirmed by Oath, are neuertheleſſe by the Law of God and Nature obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:19923:74"/>to beare faith and true Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to his
<hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. And although wee ſhould for Diſputation ſake admit, that it were the meaning of this Clauſe, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to abſolue the ſwearer ſo much as from the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> bond of this Oath, or any part thereof, or, which is all one, from any of theſe <hi>three</hi> things promiſed in the <hi>third</hi> Branch, only with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duplication as they are ſworne, or confirmed by Oath (of which nice ſubtiltie his <hi>Maiestie</hi> and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> by all likelihood little dreamed) yet any man may with great reaſon thinke, and in conſcience be reſolued, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no ſuch authoritie: for that, according to the common doctrine of Diuines, the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not power to abſolue from <hi>Oaths,</hi> when the abſoluing from them tendeth to the temporall preiudice of a <hi>third</hi> perſon, vnleſſe either directly or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly hee hath power to diſpoſe of the temporall goods of that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:19923:74"/>For <hi>hee hath not power,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Sotus, Aragona,</hi> and <hi>Sayrus</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <p>Scotus <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>de Inſtit. q.</hi> 1.
<hi>art.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Aragona</hi> 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 89. <hi>art.</hi> 9.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sayrus</hi> lib. 5. <hi>Theſauri</hi> cap. 8. num.
4.</p>
               </note> 
               <hi>to releaſe an Oath which one hath made to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther man to pay him that debt which he oweth him, becauſe he hath not pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to take from another man that which is his owne, and therefore he can not doe him wrong in releaſing the Oath which was made vnto him. Wherefore this difference is betweene Vowes and Oaths, that in changing and diſpencing of Vowes that only must be regarded which is more pleaſing to God, but in releaſing of Oaths great caution muſt be vſed, that no wrong be done to a third perſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And this is farre more euident in the doctaine of Saint
<hi>Thomas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. <hi>Thom.</hi> 2. 2. qu. 89. art.
9.</note> whom the greateſt part of Diuines doe herein follow, who houldeth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot diſpence in Oaths by releaſing directly the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred obligation of the Oath, for that this obligation is <hi>de iure naturae,</hi> wherein the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot diſpence, but only by declaring, that the thing promiſed by Oath, which before was a fit thing to bee ſworne, and
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:19923:75"/>therefore by vertue of the Oath to be performed, ſo long as it remay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth ſo, is now, by reaſon of ſome particular accident or circumſtance, become vnlawfull, hurtful, or an hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of greater good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore now no fit matter to be ſworne, nor by vertue of the Oath to be now any longer performed. From whence it plainely followeth, that the <hi>Pope</hi> cannot abſolue from this
<hi>Oath</hi> of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance, vnleſſe hee hath power to declare, that temporall Allegiance, which Subiects by the Law of <hi>God,</hi> and
<hi>Nature</hi> owe to their lawfull Prince ſo long as he remaineth Prince, be vnlawfull, hurtfull, or an hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of greater good, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not in any wiſe declare, vnleſſe hee hath power to make a King no King. For conſequently hee ſhould alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Nature</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Subiects to beare true faith and Allegiance to their lawfull Prince, ſhould enioyne them an vnlawfull or hurtfull thing, or which is an hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of greater good, which is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible. And ſo in this Clauſe there
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:19923:75"/>is no more difficultie concerning this point of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie not to abſolue from this <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance, or any part thereof, then is in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer clauſes, wherein the
<hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to <hi>depoſe</hi> Kings, and to
<hi>abſolue</hi> Subiects from their naturall allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, is denyed.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Laſtly,</hi> by thoſe words [<hi>nor any perſon whatſoeuer</hi>] is not vnderſtood the <hi>Kings Maieſtie:</hi> Both for that in the Lawes of this Realme the Kings <hi>Maiestie</hi> is not vnderſtood by the name of <hi>perſon,</hi> or perſons, when the matter is odious: &amp; alſo, as in no penal law the <hi>Prince</hi> or
<hi>Law-maker</hi> himſelfe is included vnder any generall word, becauſe he is not ſubiect to ſuch laws, according to that principle of the law,
<hi>Princeps legibus ſolutus eſt, The Prince is free from lawes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Leg</hi> Princeps. <hi>ff.</hi> de Legibus.</note> ſo alſo when it is ſaid in the Law, that no <hi>perſon what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer</hi> hath power to diſpence in that law, or to change or alter that Law, the
<hi>Law-maker</hi> himſelfe, who is aboue the Law, is not comprehended vnder thoſe generall words; yea and, as well obſerueth <hi>Salas</hi> and
<hi>Sa,</hi> both Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:19923:76"/>
               <hi>In a generall ſpeech the perſon who ſpeaketh is vnderstood to bee excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Salas
<hi>diſp.</hi> 21. <hi>de Legibus ſec.</hi> 3. <hi>regula</hi> 22.
<hi>&amp;</hi> Emanuel Sa <hi>verbo Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio. nu.</hi> 14.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. And although we ſhould admit, that the <hi>Kings Maieſtie</hi> were inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in thoſe wordes [<hi>nor any perſon whatſoeuer</hi>] yet this <hi>clauſe</hi> would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe be very true: And the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, for that albeit his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath power to diſpence with his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, that they ſhall not take this
<hi>Oath,</hi> which is not the meaning of this <hi>Clauſe,</hi> yet he hath not power to abſolue them from this <hi>Oath,</hi> or any part thereof after they haue once ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it, which is the true ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of this Branch. <hi>Firſt,</hi> for that to <hi>dispence</hi> or <hi>abſolue</hi> from Oaths (taking thoſe words [to <hi>dispence</hi> or <hi>abſolue</hi>] according to their proper ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and as they are taken commonly by Diuines) doth belong onely to ſpirituall and not to temporall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. Wherefore the Diuines make a great difference betweene <hi>abſoluing</hi> or
<hi>dispencing</hi> in Oathes or Vowes, and <hi>releaſing</hi> or
<hi>annulling</hi> the ſame; and they affirme, that to <hi>releaſe</hi> or
<hi>annull</hi>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:19923:76"/>an Oath or Vow, a temporall power, yea and ſometimes priuate authoritie may ſuffice, as Parents may releaſe and annull the oathes and vowes of their children; but to <hi>abſolue</hi> or
<hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpence</hi> in an Oath or Vow, a ſpirituall authoritie and iuriſdiction is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily required. But <hi>ſecondly,</hi> and
<hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally,</hi> for that his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> hath not power to releaſe his ſubiects from their temporall and naturall allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, vnleſſe he will ceaſe to be their Prince, becauſe temporall allegiance is by the law of God and Nature due to him from his <hi>Subiects,</hi> ſo long as he remayneth their Prince; and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he cannot abſolue, diſcharge, or releaſe them from the Obligation of this Oath or any part thereof; or, which is all one, he cannot giue them <hi>leaue,</hi> not <hi>to beare faith and true allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to his</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>and conſequently not to defend him to the vttermoſt of their power againſt all Treaſons and trayterous conſpiracies, which ſhall be made againſt his Royall perſon, Crowne and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,</hi> and <hi>not to doe their best endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uor to diſcloſe, and make them knowne
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:19923:77"/>vnto his Maieſtie,</hi> ſeeing that to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all theſe things Subiects are bound by the law of <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Nature,</hi> wherein no temporall or ſpirituall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie can diſpence. And therefore the <hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtants Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for the Roman Church,</hi> trac. 3. Sec. 5. doth very well affirme, that <hi>all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes are by all Lawes, Diuine and Humane,</hi> indiſſolubly <hi>obliged in the highest degree of all earthly Allegiance to his Maiestie that now is, as to their true, vndoubted, lawfull Soueraigne liege Lord and King.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VI. The <hi>Sixt</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an
<hi>Explication</hi> of the ſame.</head>
            <q>WHich <hi>Oath</hi> I acknowledge by good and full authoritie to bee lawfully miniſtred vnto mee: and doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all pardons and diſpenſations to the contrarie.</q>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Branch</hi> contayneth in it no difficultie at all, if wee conſider what
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:19923:77"/>hath beene ſaid before; to wit, that in this
<hi>Oath</hi> is onely demanded a ſincere profeſſion of true temporall allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and that no authoritie or obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, which is due to the
<hi>Pope,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied therein: And that to treat of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, not <hi>affirmatiuely</hi> what power he hath, but
<hi>affirmatiuely</hi> what authoritie in temporalls the <hi>Kings Maieſtie</hi> hath ouer his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and Subiects; and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly what authoritie in temporalls the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not ouer the ſaid kingdome and ſubiects: and alſo, that to exact of Subiects an <hi>Oath</hi> not onely of their temporall allegiance in <hi>generall,</hi> but alſo of ſuch allegiance in <hi>particular,</hi> which his <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and the
<hi>State</hi> ſhall for prudent reaſons &amp; motiues thinke to be neceſſarie for the preſeruation of the Kingdome from future Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Inuaſions, or Perturbations, ſo that it bee contayned within the bounds of true temporall allegiance, doth no way exceede the limits of temporall authoritie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore by thoſe words [<hi>good and full authoritie</hi>] is not vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:19923:78"/>any authoritie of the <hi>Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> cauſes, but onely in
<hi>temporall</hi> matters, as is the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring of an Oath of true temporall allegiance. For although his <hi>Maieſty</hi> be perſwaded, that hee hath full and ſupreme authoritie not onely in <hi>tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall,</hi> but alſo in <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> affaires, for externall gouernement; and that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath not ouer him or his Subiects within this Realme, any au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie or iuriſdiction, nor power to <hi>excommunicate</hi> his
<hi>Maieſtie,</hi> yet his meaning is not to meddle at all in this Oath eyther with his owne, or with the Popes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall Supremacie,</hi> but onely with his owne <hi>temporall So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigntie,</hi> and conſequently with the <hi>Popes authoritie</hi> not to <hi>depoſe</hi> him, or to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of his Kingdome, or to <hi>au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorize</hi> any forraigne Prince to inuade or annoy him, or to <hi>abſolue</hi> his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects from their obedience, &amp;c. And therefore, as I obſerued before in the
<hi>third</hi> obſeruation, wee muſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh betwixt his
<hi>Maieſties</hi> vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding or perſwaſion, and his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning or intention: for his meaning
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:19923:78"/>was not to exact <hi>in this Oath</hi> of His Subiects all which hee is perſwaded he might lawfully exact of them, but only to demand of them <hi>in this Oath</hi> a profeſſion of that temporall Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, which all Subiects are bound by the Law of God to giue to their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soueraigne, as it is manifeſt by the declaration both of His
<hi>Maieſtie</hi> and alſo of the <hi>Parliament:</hi> and therefore Hee was carefull not to meddle with the <hi>Popes</hi> authority to
<hi>excommunicate</hi> Him,</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Secondly,</hi> it is certaine, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit Chriſtian <hi>Princes</hi> haue not au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to define and determine what poſition is <hi>hereticall,</hi> or to puniſh He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes with ſpirituall puniſhments (for theſe are meere ſpirituall things) yet they haue authoritie to command their ſubiects to abiure ſuch poſitions as are alreadie defined, or knowne to bee manifeſtly falſe and repugnant to the holy Scriptures, for ſuch: and to puniſh with temporall puniſhments the obſtinate maintayners of the ſame, eſpecially as the mayntayning of ſuch poſitions is hurtfull to the
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:19923:79"/>publike temporall peace, whereof the
<hi>King</hi> hath charge: and who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may alſo by the materiall Sword repell the wrongs and iniuries offered to the temporall Kingdome or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth by Clergie-men, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the abuſes of the ſpirituall Sword, when they tend to the hurt of the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill Common-wealth, as
<hi>Franciſcus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictoria, Ioannes Pariſienſis,</hi> and
<hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerruuias</hi> doe well obſerue.<note place="margin">
                  <p>Victoria <hi>Relect.</hi> 1. <hi>de poteſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. ſec.</hi> 7. §. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaua propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio.</p>
                  <p>Pariſienſis <hi>de poteſt. Reg. &amp; Pap. cap.</hi> 11.
<hi>ad</hi> 37.</p>
                  <p>Couerruu. <hi>cap.</hi> 35. Practic. queſtion.</p>
               </note> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>a King,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dominicus Bannes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bannes 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 11. <hi>ar. q.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>doth puniſh Heretikes as moſt ſeditious Enemies to the peace of His Kingdome, which cannot be preſerued without vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Religion. And Marriage,</hi> ſaith <hi>Dominicus Sotus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Sotus <hi>in</hi> 4.
<hi>diſt.</hi> 29. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>ar.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>being a Sacrament in ſuch ſort, that it is alſo a ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, it nothing letteth, but that as in the former reſpect it belongeth to the Eccleſiasticall Court, ſo in regard of the later it is ſubiect alſo in ſome ſort to the Ciuill. Not that Princes can alter thoſe things which are of the ſubstance of Matrimonie, but that they may pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them, who contract they ſhall offend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the publike peace: for against
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:19923:79"/>thoſe crimes, whoſe iudgement doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the Eccleſiasticall Court, they may alſo ordayne puniſhments, as they diſturbe the peace of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth.</hi> Which doctrine of
<hi>Sotus</hi> may in the very like manner bee ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to <hi>Hereſie,</hi> which <hi>being a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall offence in ſuch ſort, that alſo it disturbeth the temporall peace of the Common-wealth, it nothing letteth, but that as in the former respect it belongeth to the Eccleſiasticall Court, ſo in regard of the later it is ſubiect alſo in ſome ſort to the Ciuill; not that Princes can determine and define what is Hereſie, but that they may puniſh Heretikes, when by defending hereticall poſitions, they ſhall offend against the publike good. For against thoſe crimes, whoſe iudgement doth belong to the Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Court, they may alſo ordayne pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as they disturbe the peace of the Common-wealth.</hi> And therefore Chriſtian Princes haue good and full power to compell their Subiects to abiure impious, damnable, and <hi>here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall</hi> poſitions for ſuch, when it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie to the preſeruation of the
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:19923:80"/>publike temporall peace, and to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couer how their Subiects ſtand affect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in point of their Loyaltie and due Obedience.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> it is euident, that
<hi>Clergie-men</hi> being truely ſubiect to <hi>temporall Princes,</hi> in regard of their naturall birth, and of their liuing in Ciuill Societie with others, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently bound, according to the common doctrine of
<hi>Diuines,</hi> to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their iuſt Lawes not only
<hi>vira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis,</hi> but alſo <hi>vi legis,</hi> by <hi>force of the Law,</hi> doe owe true Allegiance to their naturall Prince, no leſſe then
<hi>Lay men,</hi> and that therefore hee may lawfully demand of them, as they are Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, an Oath of their Allegiance, whenſoeuer hee ſhall iuſtly ſuſpect their fidelitie. And although ſome <hi>Clergie-men</hi> ſhould bee ſo capricious, as to imagine, contrarie to the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Primitiue Church, the doctrine of the Ancient Fathers, and manifeſt reaſon, that they are not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect at all to the authoritie of tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Princes, and thereupon ſhould make a ſcruple to take this <hi>Oath</hi> as
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19923:80"/>
               <hi>lawfully ministred to them by good and full authoritie,</hi> yet this could not bee a ſufficient proofe, that the
<hi>Oath</hi> is vnlawfull in it ſelfe, or that <hi>Lay-men</hi> cannot lawfully take it, and alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that it is lawfully mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred vnto them by good and full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Lastly,</hi> in thoſe words [<hi>And I doe renounce all Pardons and Dispen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations to the contrarie</hi>] is not implyed a renouncing in generall of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to giue Pardons and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, but, as the wordes doe plainly ſignifie, in them is only con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned a denyall of the <hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to diſpence with the Swearer, or to giue him leaue and licenſe to doe contrarie to that which hee hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed in this Oath. Wherefore the veritie of theſe laſt wordes is chiefly grounded vpon the lawfulneſſe of the <hi>Fift</hi> Branch. For if the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no power and authoritie to abſolue the Swearer from any part of this Oath, becauſe thoſe <hi>three</hi> things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, which he promiſeth to performe, he is bound by the Law
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:19923:81"/>of God and Nature to performe, and that therein no authoritie of <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Prince</hi> can diſpence, it is manifeſt, that hee may lawfully renounce all Pardons and Diſpenſations to the contrarie.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VII. The <hi>Seuenth</hi> Branch of the Oath, and an
<hi>Explication</hi> thereof.</head>
            <q>"ANd all theſe things I do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely acknowledge and ſweare according to theſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe words by me ſpoken, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the plaine and common ſenſe, &amp; vnderſtanding of the ſame words without any equiuocation, or mentall euaſion, or ſecret reſeruaſion whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</q>
            <p n="1">1. This <hi>Branch</hi> is greatly to bee regarded, for that it expreſly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, in what ſenſe the Swearer is bound to take all the parts and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels of this Oath. And <hi>firſt,</hi> by thoſe firſt words <hi>And all theſe things I doe plainly and ſincerely acknowledge and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:19923:81"/>ſweare, &amp;c.</hi>] it is manifeſt, that the immediate obiect of all this Oath and euery part therof, or, which is all one, that which in all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Branches</hi> I doe directly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediatly ſweare, is my <hi>plaine and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere acknowledgement,</hi> to wit, that our <hi>Soueraigne Lord King</hi> Iames <hi>is the lawfull and rightfull King of this Realme, &amp;c.</hi> and <hi>that the Pope hath not any power or authoritie to depoſe him, &amp;c.</hi> and that <hi>I will beare Faith &amp; true Allegiance to His</hi> Maieſtie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and
<hi>that from my heart I doe abhorre, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test and abiure as impious and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, &amp;c.</hi> and that I doe beleeue and in conſcience am reſolued, &amp;c. and that <hi>it is lawfully ministred vnto me by good and full authoritie,</hi> and that I <hi>doe renounce all Pardons and Diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to the contrarie.</hi> Whereupon the Oath concludeth thus:
<hi>And I doe make this recognition and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment heartily, willingly and truly vpon the true faith of a Christian.</hi> So that the plaine and proper meaning of this <hi>Branch</hi> is, that whatſoeuer I doe
<hi>ſweare</hi> in this Oath, I doe ſweare
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:19923:82"/>plainly and ſincerely according to theſe expreſſe words, &amp;c.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Secondly,</hi> the meaning of thoſe words
[<hi>without any equiuocation, &amp;c.</hi>] is not, that there is not to be found in this Oath any equiuocall wordes, and which may not haue two proper and vſuall ſignifications, eſpecially if they be taken barely and by themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone (for if wee conſider them as they be ioined with other words and make a full and perfect ſentence, and doe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo duly regard the intention of the Law-maker with the other obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions before ſet downe, we ſhall hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find any one ſentence in this Oath ſo equiuocall or ambiguous, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the common vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of men it hath two ſenſes, equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly common, which is properly to bee equiuocal.) But the plaine and proper meaning of thoſe words is, that the Swearer muſt not in this <hi>Oath</hi> equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocate, or vſe any equiuocation, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal euaſion, or ſecret reſeruation what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, but that he muſt deale plainly and ſincerely according to the minde and intention of the Law-maker. For
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:19923:82"/>it is one thing to <hi>vſe equiuocall words,</hi> and an other thing to equiuocate, or <hi>to vſe equiuocation,</hi> becauſe one may vſe equiuocal words, and not deceiue or delude the hearer, for that hee v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the words in that ſenſe, wherein the hearer vnderſtandeth them. But to <hi>equiuocate</hi> implyeth a fraudulent, deceitfull, and vnſincere dealing by v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the words in an other ſenſe, then the hearer vnderſtandeth them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Wherefore the plaine meaning of this <hi>Branch</hi> is, that albeit in this Oath there might bee found diuerſe common ſenſes of the ſame wordes, yet the Swearer muſt not <hi>equiuocate,</hi> but hee muſt take the wordes in that ſenſe, wherin the Law-maker vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth them, with whome hee is bound, by vertue of this <hi>Branch,</hi> to deale plainly, ſincerely, without any guile, fraude, deceit, euaſion, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret reſeruation whatſoeuer. But if perchance there ſhould any difficulty ariſe concerning any ambiguous word, or ſentence contayned in this Oath, and the will, meaning, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention of the Law-maker could not
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:19923:83"/>bee knowne, then wee muſt vſe thoſe rules, which, according to the appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued doctrine of all Diuines and Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers, wee haue aboue ſet downe for the interpreting of doubtfull and am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguous ſpeeches in any Law. And namely among the reſt, that in penall Lawes and odious matters the mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and more fauourable ſenſe, and which contayneth in it no abſurditie, is to be choſen.</p>
            <p n="4">4 Seeing therefore that, according to the doctrine of all Diuines, it is not lawfull to <hi>equiuocate,</hi> or to <hi>vſe equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocation,</hi> but we muſt anſwere plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and intention of the Iudge, when hee proceedeth iuridically, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth no vniuſt and vnlawfull thing, but which hee hath authoritie to demand, it is manifeſt, that the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of this <hi>Branch</hi> dependeth whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpon the lawfulneſſe of the Oath, and vpon the authoritie of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker thereof, and that conſequently there is no difficultie in this Clauſe, ſuppoſing the lawfulneſſe of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Clauſes, and that this Oath is
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:19923:83"/>
               <hi>lawfully ministred by good and full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. VIII. The <hi>Eight</hi> and laſt Branch of the Oath.</head>
            <q>"ANd I doe make this recognition and acknowledgement heartily, willingly, and truely, vpon the true faith of a Chriſtian. So helpe mee God.</q>
            <p n="1">1. The lawfulneſſe of this <hi>Branch</hi> dependeth wholly vpon the veritie and iuſtice of the former Clauſes, and will cleerely appeare, if wee ſuppoſe, as hath beene ſhewed before, that this
<hi>Oath</hi> of Allegiance contayneth in it no falſhood or iniuſtice, and that it is miniſtred vnder great penalties by lawfull authoritie, to make a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all how his <hi>Maieſties</hi> ſubiects ſtand affected in point of their loyaltie and due obedience. For as <hi>Vaſquez</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth very well out of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vaſquez 1. 2.
<hi>Diſp.</hi> 51. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; disp.</hi> 73. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.
<hi>&amp; disp.</hi> 86. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</note> with whom all Diuines and Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers do herein agree, to make an act of vertue to bee morally good and
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:19923:84"/>vertuous, it is not only required, that it haue a good and vertuous obiect, but alſo it muſt bee done directly for the goodneſſe and honeſtie of the vertue it ſelfe, and not for any other end or motiue. For otherwiſe if one doe acts of vertue, as of iuſtice, or temperance, not for iuſtice or tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſake, but for ſome other end, as for lucre, vaine glorie, feare of puniſhment, or any other motiue whatſoeuer, <hi>he ſholl doe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ariſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ariſtot. 2. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thic. cap.</hi> 4.</note> 
               <hi>iuſt or temperate actions, but hee ſhall not doe them iuſtly or temperately, neither ſhall hee for doing thoſe actions be accounted a iuſt or temperate man.</hi> Seeing therefore that euery iuſt and vertuous man ought to obſerue iuſt Lawes, not for feare of puniſhment as the wicked do, but heartily, willingly, and <hi>truely,</hi> that is, <hi>ſincerely,</hi> and
<hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainedly,</hi> for the loue of vertue, it is euident, that euery good and well af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected ſubiect may and ought to take this Oath of Allegiance, ſuppoſing it to be lawfull and miniſtred by good and full authoritie, not for feare of puniſhment, as likewiſe we ought to
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:19923:84"/>obſerue God his commandements, not for feare of eternall damnation, but heartily, willingly, and vnfained<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for the loue of vertue and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. Wherefore it is manifeſt, that euery good and vertuous Subiect ought to haue a farre greater wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe in obſeruing iuſt Lawes, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they be impoſed vnder paine of death, then hath a Merchant be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in danger of drowning, to caſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer board his goods for ſauing his life: for that a Merchant in that caſe is only willing to loſe his goods, for that otherwiſe hee cannot eſcape the danger of his life, but euery vertuous man ought to obſerue iuſt Lawes heartily, willingly, and vnfainedly, for vertue and obedience ſake, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though hee were in no danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing puniſhed for not obſeruing the ſame.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And thus thou ſeeſt <hi>good Reader,</hi> that this
<hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance</hi> doth not want either <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritie, Iustice</hi> or <hi>Iudgement,</hi> as well in regard of the takers, as of the makers &amp; propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the ſame: That the State,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:19923:85"/>ſuppoſing that horrible <hi>Powder Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> which was grounded vpon co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour and pretence of the
<hi>Popes</hi> autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to take away the Crownes and liues of
<hi>Princes</hi> in order to ſpirituall good, had iuſt cauſe to deuiſe a <hi>new Oath</hi> of Allegiance, wherein menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſhould bee made of the aforeſaid authoritie, to make a true difference, betwixt ciuilly obedient Subiects, and the peruerſe diſciples of thoſe <hi>Powder Traitors,</hi> it is euident by that which hath beene ſaid before in the fourth obſeruation: and that therfore the <hi>State</hi> in deuiſing and propounding ſuch an Oath did not want <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> Alſo that the Subiect hath iuſt cauſe to take the Oath, ſuppoſing it to bee lawfull and miniſtred by good and full authoritie, and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in taking it, after he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amined and ſeene the lawfulneſſe thereof, doth not want <hi>Iudgement,</hi> it is as euident, as that there is no want of
<hi>Iudgement</hi> to obſerue the iuſt commandement of his Lawfull Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour, when after due examination he findeth the commandement to bee
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:19923:85"/>iuſt. And finally, that no
<hi>aſſertorie</hi> Clauſe of the Oath wanteth <hi>Veritie,</hi> nor any
<hi>Promiſſorie</hi> Clauſe wanteth <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> or, which is all one, that no falſhood or iniuſtice is to bee found in any part or parcell of the Oath, it is manifeſt by the former Explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of euery
<hi>Branch</hi> in particular.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="9" type="chapter">
            <head>CHAP. IX. <hi>An Anſwere to the Popes Breues.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. THere remaineth only one dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie to be explained con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>Popes Breues,</hi> which for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid Engliſh Catholikes to take this new Oath <hi>for that it containeth many things which are plainely againſt faith and ſaluation.</hi> And although <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> both in his <hi>Theologicall Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation,</hi> and alſo more fully in his
<hi>Anſwere</hi> to <hi>Fitz-herberts</hi> Reply hath cleared this difficultie,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Wriddrington</hi> in his <hi>Disput. Theolog. cap.</hi> 10. <hi>ſec.</hi> 2. and in his <hi>Anſwere</hi> to
<hi>Fitzherb. part.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 7.</note> yet I thinke it not amiſſe briefly to ſet downe ſome generall heads of his anſwere to the ſaid <hi>Breues,</hi> whereby any iudicious man may haue ſufficient grounds to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:19923:86"/>iudge not only how farre the <hi>Popes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid <hi>Breues,</hi> but alſo all other of the like kind may without any irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerence or diſobedience to <hi>the Sea Apoſtolike</hi> be contradicted, or not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by good and vertuous Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Firſt</hi> therefore, <hi>Widdrington</hi> ſheweth out of the approued Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Suarez</hi> and other Diuines, that there bee two ſorts of Lawes or Precepts, the <hi>one</hi> are called
<hi>Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue,</hi> for that they doe not ſuppoſe, but make the thing, which they for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid, to be vnlawfull, which, if that Precept were not, would be lawfull, as the Precept of the Church to faſt from Fleſh in Lent, to abſtaine from ſeruile works vpon commanded Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-daies, to receiue the Bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at Eaſter, or the like: And that no
<hi>Constitutiue</hi> Precept of the Church doth binde, when by obſeruing it there is danger to incurre ſome nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corporall or temporall hurt. The
<hi>other</hi> are called <hi>Declaratiue,</hi> for that they doe not make, but ſuppoſe and declare the thing to bee vnlawfull
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:19923:86"/>which they forbid, as being forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by ſome former Law; as the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding of Theft, Murder, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, Vſurie, and ſuch like, for that they are before forbidden by the Law of God and Nature: And that the obligation of <hi>Declaratiue</hi> Precepts doth only depend vpon the reaſon and former Law, which in the <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue</hi> Precept is ſuppoſed and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared: So that if there bee no ſuch former Law or prohibition, as in the <hi>Declaratiue</hi> Precept is ſuppoſed and declared, the <hi>Declaratiue</hi> Precept hath no force to bind.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Secondly,</hi> he ſheweth, that the <hi>Popes Breues</hi> forbidding Engliſh Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes to take the Oath, doe not containe a <hi>Conſtitutiue,</hi> but only a <hi>Declaratiue</hi> Precept, neither do they make, but ſuppoſe and declare the Oath to be vnlawfull, <hi>for that,</hi> ſay the <hi>Breues, it contayneth in it many things, which are manifeſtly againſt faith and ſaluation;</hi> and that conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, if in the Oath there bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing againſt faith or ſaluation, as the
<hi>Breues</hi> ſuppoſe and declare, it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt,
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:19923:87"/>that the <hi>Breues</hi> haue no force at all to bind Engliſh Catholickes not to take the Oath, for that they are grounded vpon a falſe reaſon, ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and declaration.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Thirdly,</hi> he ſheweth that all <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claratiue Breues</hi> are eyther <hi>definitiue,</hi> or grounded vpon ſome former defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, of <hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Councell,</hi> or elſe they are onely
<hi>opinatiue,</hi> or grounded vpon the <hi>Popes</hi> opinatiue iudgement, perſwaſion, or probable opinion: And that if they bee grounded vpon the
<hi>Popes</hi> opinion, no man is bound to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey them, as neyther to follow his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion, whereon they are grounded: but hee may as lawfully contradict them, as he may contradict his opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, although the <hi>Pope</hi> thinke it to bee neuer ſo <hi>probable:</hi> And that vpon this ground, cauſe, and reaſon, it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for Catholickes to contradict the <hi>declaratiue Breue</hi> of Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> the Firſt,
<note n="a" place="margin">De conſecr. <hi>diſt.</hi> 4.
<hi>can.</hi> A quodam Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeo.</note> wherein he declared, that <hi>Baptiſme miniſtred in the name of Chriſt without expreſſing the three perſons of the B. Trinitie was valid and true Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme:</hi> And the <hi>declaratiue Breue</hi> of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:19923:87"/>Pope <hi>Celeſtine</hi> the Third,
<note n="b" place="margin">Which was once extant in the Canon Law, in cap. <hi>Laudabilem de controuerſ. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugot.</hi>
               </note> wherein he declared, and, as <hi>Alphonſus de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stro</hi> ſaith,<note n="b" place="margin">Caſtro <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de haereſ. cap.</hi> 4.</note> he defined, that <hi>Marriage is ſo diſſolued by hereſie, that the partie whoſe Conſort falleth into hereſie, may lawfully marry an other,</hi> which Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine is now condemned in the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of <hi>Trent:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sec.</hi> 24. <hi>de Reform. can.</hi>
5.</note> And the <hi>declaratiue Breues</hi> or <hi>Letters</hi> of Pope
<hi>Iohn</hi> the 22. who publiquely taught and declared, <hi>that the ſoules of the Bleſſed ſhould not ſee God, before the reſurrection,</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Caſtro <hi>lib.</hi> 3.
<hi>contra haereſ. verbo Beatitudo hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſ.</hi> 6. Bellar. <hi>lib.</hi>
4. <hi>de Rom.</hi> Pont. <hi>c.</hi> 14. Hadrianus <hi>Papa in quaeſt. de</hi> Confirm. <hi>circa finem,</hi> and other Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in hee was contradicted by the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> and cauſed to recall his Doctrine: And the <hi>declaratiue Breue</hi> of Pope
<hi>Boniface</hi> the eight, wherein he <hi>declared,</hi> that <hi>Philip the French King was ſubiect to him in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualls and temporalls, wherein he was contradicted by the French Nation, and taxed of wonderfull impudency.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laus Vignerius <hi>ad annum</hi> 1300.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Fourthly,</hi> he ſheweth, that the <hi>Popes declaratiue Breues</hi> forbidding Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks to take the oath, <hi>for that it contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth many things which are manifeſtly againſt faith and ſaluation,</hi> are neyther <hi>definitiue,</hi> for that they are not dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to the whole Church, nor doe
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:19923:88"/>contayne any of thoſe rules, which, according to Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine</hi> and other Diuines, is required to a true and infallible definition of faith (for onely of this kind of definition now wee ſpeake) and that although they were <hi>definitiue,</hi> yet conſidering that it is a probable Doctrine, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie infallibly to define without a generall Councell, no Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke is bound to giue more credit to his definition, then to follow his probable Doctrine and opinion: ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are they grounded vpon any for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer definition of
<hi>Pope</hi> or <hi>Councell,</hi> and which all Catholickes are bound to admit for a true definition, as <hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> hath proued at large by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering all the Decrees and Canons of <hi>Popes</hi> or
<hi>Councells;</hi> which <hi>Leſſius</hi> (masked vnder the name of <hi>D. Single<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi>) hath ſcraped together. But they are grounded onely vpon the
<hi>opina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> iudgement of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and ſome other
<hi>Diuines</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> who then were of opinion, that many things are contayned in the Oath manifeſtly
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:19923:88"/>repugnant to faith and ſaluation, for one of theſe <hi>two</hi> grounds and reaſons, or rather for both: The
<hi>firſt,</hi> that the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>excommunicate,</hi> and conſequently his ſpirituall authoritie is denyed in the Oath: and that the
<hi>Breues</hi> were chiefly grounded vpon this reaſon, <hi>Widdrington</hi> conuinceth by the <hi>Popes</hi> anſwer to Fa: <hi>Parſons;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Widdrington</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Fitzh.</hi> part 3. chap. 17.</note> by the conſult and reſolution of the <hi>Diuines of Rome;</hi> by Cardinall
<hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his
<hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Apologie,</hi> pag. 9.</note> (who doubtleſſe would not in this poynt diſſent from the opinion and reſolution of the
<hi>Pope,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Diuines of <hi>Rome,</hi> nor they from him) affirming that in the Oath <hi>is plainely</hi> or <hi>manifeſtly denyed to the</hi> Pope, <hi>power to excommunicate euen hereticall Kings,</hi> for which he is deſeruedly tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by his <hi>Maiestie</hi> of manifeſt fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhood: and <hi>laſtly,</hi> by thoſe wordes of the <hi>Breues, that in the Oath are contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many things,</hi> quae apertè aduerſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur fidei,
<hi>which are plainely or expreſly repugnant to faith:</hi> But none of our learned Aduerſaries dare affirme, that the denyall of the <hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe</hi> Princes, is plainely and expreſly
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:19923:89"/>repugnant to faith, but at the moſt,
<hi>tacite,</hi> and <hi>tecte, conertly,</hi> and <hi>cloſely,</hi> and that by many farre fetcht (and ill deduced) inferences and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Suarez <hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. <hi>de</hi> Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramento fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatis.</note> and that therefore they ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with Cardinall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that the Popes power to <hi>excommunicate,</hi> is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed in the Oath: The <hi>ſecond</hi> ground or reaſon is, that the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to <hi>depoſe</hi> Princes, to dipoſe of their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls, and to abſolue ſubiects from their temporall allegiance, which doubtleſſe is denyed in the Oath, is a cleare poynt of faith, and not in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among Catholiques, both which grounds and reaſons are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly falſe, as hath beene ſufficiently conuinced by the former Diſcourſe: and conſequently, that it is no more vnlawful not to obey the
<hi>Popes decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratiue Breues</hi> forbidding Catholickes to take the Oath, they being groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the aforeſaid reaſons &amp; ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, which are manifeſtly falſe, then it is vnlawfull not to approue the ſaid falſe reaſons and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for that a <hi>declaratiue precept</hi> hath no more force to bind, according to
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:19923:89"/>the Doctrine of <hi>Suarez,</hi> (which is alſo conforme to manifeſt reaſon) then hath the reaſon &amp; ſuppoſition where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it is grounded.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Lastly,</hi> he ſheweth out of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of
<hi>Dominicus Sotus,</hi> &amp; other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines,<note place="margin">Sotus <hi>de de de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legendo ſecreto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to memb.</hi> 2. <hi>nu.</hi> 2. See
<hi>Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drington</hi> in the Diſcouery of the 15. colum of D.
<hi>Schulked.</hi>
               </note> that if a Prelate, or any other Superiour command a thing, which the Subiect doubteth to be vniuſt, and the thing which is commanded be in preiudice of a third perſon, who is in poſſeſſion of his goods and good name, it is no irreurence, or diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in the Subiect not to obey, propounding to his Superiour with all humilitie and reuerence the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of his doubt. Seeing therefore that <hi>Widdrington</hi> hath in the name of Engliſh Catholickes propounded to his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> the reaſons which mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued them to doubt, that his <hi>declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Breues</hi> were not iuſt, as beeing greatly preiudiciall to his <hi>Mtieſties</hi> temporall Soueraigntie, and namely for that they were grounded vpon the
<hi>two</hi> aforeſaid falſe reaſons and ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, and that they haue not had as yet any ſatisfaction concerning thoſe
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:19923:90"/>their doubts, it is not onely manifeſt, that they cannot be iuſtly taxed of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſobedience or irreuerence to his
<hi>Holineſſe,</hi> for not obeying the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid <hi>Breues,</hi> but alſo it is an euident ſigne, that his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> could not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their doubts, and that now hee plainly ſeeth, that he and his Diuines were miſtaken, and that his <hi>declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Breues</hi> were grounded vpon thoſe falſe reaſons and ſuppoſitions which he could not iuſtifie or make good: Otherwiſe he would without all doubt, in regard of his Fatherly care, and Paſtorall charge, haue ſought to haue giuen them all poſſible ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in this poynt, which ſo neerely concerneth not onely their ſoules health, and their temporall ſtates and libertie, but which alſo is ſo iniurious to his <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and ſo ſcandalous to Catholicke Religion, giuing occaſion to all <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Princes and ſubiects to perſwade themſelues, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the Catholicke <hi>Roman Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> cannot ſtand with true and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant loyaltie, but that it is a Nurcery of vniuſt Inuaſions, Rebellions, and Powder-Treaſons.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="179" facs="tcp:19923:90"/>7. Wherefore, (for the laſt fare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well) I beſeech you again and againe <hi>(deare Countrimen)</hi> not to forget thoſe two moſt certaine Principles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is chiefly grounded the Doctrine for the iuſtifying of the Oath, and for the ſecuring of Princes from all tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terous Conſpiracies, practiſes, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts, vnder the colour and pretence of the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie to depoſe them; to wit, that it is a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie among learned Catholickes, and therefore not certayne, but true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly probable, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to depriue Soueraigne Princes, and that no power or title, which is not moſt certayn but in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, can bee a lawfull ground, whereby immediately any man may be puniſhed, or depriued of that right, dominion, or any other thing which hee really and <hi>bona fide</hi> poſſeſſeth; both which Principles, are, as you haue ſeene, ſo cleare and manifeſt, that no learned man can from his hart de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny them, howſoeuer ſome one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſome temporall reſpect, end, or motiue, may ſpeake or write con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:19923:91"/>to his mind and knowledge.</p>
            <p n="8">8. But, as <hi>Widdrington</hi> towards the end of his Anſwer to <hi>Fitzherberts</hi> Preface well obſerueth out of
<hi>Moli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> and <hi>Leſſius,</hi> both famous Ieſuites, there is a great difference betwixt the <hi>poſſeſſing</hi> of temporall and corporall goods, as Lands, Houſes, Crownes, Kingdomes, and the like, and the
<hi>poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing</hi> of authoritie, Iuriſdiction, rights, and claymes, which one may pretend to haue to ſuch temporall goods. For that
<hi>poſſeſſion</hi> properly is onely of temporall goods; and ſuch goods may properly be <hi>poſſeſſed,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the party, who hath true right to thoſe goods, contradicteth neuer ſo much; but rights, and claymes are not <hi>properly poſſeſſed,</hi> but they are one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſaid to be, <hi>as it were, in ſome ſort,</hi> or <hi>improperly poſſeſſed:</hi> and beſides, to the <hi>poſſeſſing</hi> of power, authoritie, iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, right; or claime to any tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall thing, in ſuch manner as right, iuriſdiction, and claime may be ſayd to be poſſeſſed, it is neceſſarie, that the right or claime, which is preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, be without contradiction and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:19923:91"/>of the aduerſe part. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe if one ſhould challenge any right or authoritie be it good or bad, true or falſe, and ſhould exerciſe that pretended right or authoritie, the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe part contradicting, he might ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe be ſaid to bee in poſſeſſion of that right or authoritie, which is manifeſtly falſe and abſurd. For ſo if a Lay-man ſhould pretend to haue true ſpirituall iuriſdiction ouer Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie men, as power to excommunicate, and ſhould exerciſe that pretended iuriſdiction, hee might be ſaid to be in poſſeſſion of true ſpirituall iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, although the Clergie ſhould neuer ſo much contradict and except againſt the ſame. And for this rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, albeit ſome <hi>Popes</hi> haue for as many hundreds of yeares, as haue beene ſince the time of Pope <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Seuenth, challenged a right and authoritie to depriue <hi>Kings</hi> of their regall Soueraigntie, yet they cannot be ſaid to haue beene for one day or one houre in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of that their pretended right and authoritie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſtian Kings and Subiects,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:19923:92"/>from the time of <hi>Henrie</hi> the Fourth Emperour, who was the firſt Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour that was depriued by Pope
<hi>Gregorie</hi> the Seuenth, vntill the time of <hi>Henrie</hi> the Fourth moſt Chriſtian King, who was the laſt King who was depriued by Pope
<hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fift, haue euer reſiſted and contradicted this pretended authoritie and clayme of <hi>Popes</hi> to depriue them of their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralls. And although perchance there ſhould haue beene, or hereafter ſhall be ſome or other Chriſtian King, who for ſome priuate or pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique reſpect and intereſt, hath not, or ſhall not reſiſt the
<hi>Popes</hi> ſentence of depriuation denounced or to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him, but rather yeeld thereunto, yet this cannot preiudice his ſucceſſors, or be a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ground, that the <hi>Pope</hi> may be truely ſaid to be in <hi>poſſeſſion</hi> of his pretended right, au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and claime to depriue <hi>Kings</hi> in general, but at the moſt to depriue that <hi>King</hi> in particular, who did not reſiſt or gainſay, but rather acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged the right and authority, which the
<hi>Pope</hi> claimed to depriue him.</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:19923:92"/>9. <hi>Finally,</hi> although it may bee obiected, that diuerſe <hi>Popes</hi> haue <hi>practized</hi> the
<hi>depoſing</hi> of <hi>Princes,</hi> and many learned Diuines haue approued the ſaid <hi>practice,</hi> therefore the <hi>practice</hi> being approued by many learned and skilfull men in the Arte which they profeſſe is truly probable, euen accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Widdringtons</hi> grounds, which he taketh from <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſquez:</hi> Yet this is eaſily anſwerd. For thoſe
<hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>learned men</hi> in approuing that <hi>practice</hi> for lawfull, did either thinke aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that the doctrine for the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to depriue <hi>Princes</hi> was moſt certaine, vnqueſtionable, and out of all controuerſie, and that the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie doctrine was not at that time, nor could lawfully bee approued by any learned Catholike, which howſoeuer thoſe Doctours might at that time thinke or be perſwaded (wherein ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe they were greatly decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, becauſe euen from the firſt broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of this doctrine and practice by <hi>Pope Gregorie</hi> the VII. <hi>A thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of before that Age,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Onu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Onuphr. <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>de varia creat.</hi> Rom. Pont.</note> 
               <hi>it hath euer beene a great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie,</hi>
               <pb n="184" facs="tcp:19923:93"/>ſaith <hi>Azor</hi> the Ieſuite,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Azor.</hi> cited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue in the <hi>Sixt</hi> Obſeruat.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Popes and Emperours</hi>) yet now it is ſo cleere and manifeſt, that there is at this time a great controuerſie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong learned Catholikes concerning this authoritie of the <hi>Pope.</hi> as that all the World both by the publike wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings and proceedings in this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſie can giue ſufficient teſtimonie of the ſame: Or elſe thoſe
<hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours,</hi> did not conſider and examine the difference betwixt <hi>ſpeculation</hi> and <hi>practice,</hi> but without any further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, thought euery doctrine that was probable and approoued by learned men in <hi>ſpeculation,</hi> and might
<hi>ſpeculatiuely</hi> and abſtracting from <hi>practice</hi> bee diſputed in Schooles <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>contra,</hi> might alſo bee
<hi>practiſed,</hi> and put in execution, not conſidering whether it tendeth to the preiudice of a third perſon, and to the diſpoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him of that which hee actually and <hi>bona fide</hi> poſſeſſeth, or no, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as it is moſt certaine and out of all controuerſie, (as hath beene ſhewed aboue) that it is open iniuſtice to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue vpon a probable or controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:19923:93"/>power or title any man of that which hee hath really in his poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p n="10">10. Now it is euident, according to <hi>Vaſquez</hi> doctrine which <hi>Widdring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> followeth, and which ſtands with manifeſt reaſon; that the approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and authoritie of ancient or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derne Doctours is not ſufficient to make their doctrine probable to other learned men, if either their doctrine bee grounded vpon ſome principle, which to thoſe learned men is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly falſe, or it may bee confuted by ſome reaſon, which to thoſe learned men ſeemeth inuincible and not to be anſwered, and which reaſon thoſe Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours haue not ſeene, conſidered, and examined; <hi>Obſeruandum tamen maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me eſt, &amp;c. But it is greatly to bee ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued,</hi> ſaith <hi>Vaſquez,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Vaſquez 1. 2. <hi>disp.</hi> 62. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>nu.</hi>
18. cited by Widder. <hi>in diſp. Theolog c.</hi> 10. <hi>ſec.</hi> 2.
<hi>nu.</hi> 16.</note> 
               <hi>that it may ſometimes fall out, that the ancient Writers, whoſe opinions are now in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, did not conſider ſome Reaſon, Law, or Decree, which hath great force against their opinion: but contrariwiſe that the later Doctors being conuinced with that Reaſon, Law, or Decree, doe
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:19923:94"/>now defend the contrarie opinion. If therfore a learned man ſeeing that Law or Decree, or conſidering that new rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth defend the opinion of the later Writers against the ancient, hee cannot follow in practice the opinion of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Writers, against his owne opinion,</hi> or which is all one by reaſon of their authoritie and approbation, <hi>becauſe the opinion of the ancient, who haue not ſeene, or conſidered that Decree, or Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, ought not now to be accounted pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable.</hi> And therefore <hi>Widdrington</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fining <hi>probable</hi> to bee that, which is <hi>approued by learned and skilfull men,</hi> for the better vnderſtanding and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the laſt words, he added, <hi>who haue ſeene and examined the diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie,</hi> for if they haue not ſeene and conſidered that particular difficultie and controuerſie, they cannot bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted learned and skilfull therein.</p>
            <p n="11">11. Now the particular difficulty, and controuerſie concerning this point, and which thoſe <hi>Popes</hi> and <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours</hi> mentioned in the obiection did not conſider and examine, is, whether, ſuppoſing it to bee now a
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:19923:94"/>controuerſie, and to be apptooued by learned Catholikes, that the <hi>Pope</hi> hath no authoritie to depriue
<hi>Princes,</hi> it be not open iniuſtice in the <hi>Pope</hi> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priue
<hi>Princes</hi> of their Kingdomes and Dominions, which they really and
<hi>bona fide</hi> doe poſſeſſe. And therefore vnleſſe it can bee conuinced, that it is not at this day a controuerſie among learned Catholikes, whether the <hi>Pope</hi> hath authoritie to depriue, which is as hard a matter, as to proue, that the Sunne doth not giue light at noone daies, or elſe that it is lawfull vpon a doubtfull, vncertaine, controuerſed &amp; probable power or title to thruſt by violence any man out of that, which heeactually and <hi>bona fide</hi> poſſeſſeth, the <hi>practice</hi> of depoſing <hi>Princes,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pretence of the probability of the
<hi>Popes</hi> power to depriue <hi>Princes,</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee accounted probable to any learned man, ſo much as to excuſe him in conſcience, and in the ſight of God from formall ſinne and iniuſtice.</p>
            <p n="12">12. But to conclude with this <hi>Obſeruation,</hi> which I wiſh you <hi>(Deare Countremen)</hi> diligently to conſider;
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:19923:95"/>That howſoeuer any Subiect concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in
<hi>practice</hi> with the <hi>Pope</hi> to the depoſing of his lawfull Soueraigue <hi>Prince,</hi> may vnder pretence of ſome probabilitie of the doctrine to depoſe <hi>Princes</hi> by the <hi>Popes</hi> authoritie, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade himſelfe, that hee is excuſed from ſinne and formall Treaſon in his conſcience, and before the ſight of God, (wherewith
<hi>Princes</hi> not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſecrets of mens hearts, but lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing them to the iudgement of God, doe not intermeddle in their Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals) yet conſidering theſe <hi>two</hi> things: The <hi>firſt,</hi> that it is moſt certayne and out of all controuerſie, that hee is excuſed in conſcience, and before the ſight of God from all ſinne and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence in defending his lawfull <hi>Prince,</hi> who is in poſſeſſion, and in reſiſting ſuch inuaſions and depoſitions which are grounded only vpon a probable power and title, whereas hee cannot with any reaſon aſſuredly perſwade himſelfe, that hee is ſecure in conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence by taking part with the <hi>Pope</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his <hi>Prince,</hi> who is in poſſeſſion of his Crowne: The <hi>Second,</hi> that it is
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:19923:95"/>alſo moſt certaine, and out of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie, that hee may iuſtly in taking the <hi>Popes</hi> part againſt his <hi>Prince</hi> being inuaded and depriued vnder pretence of a probable power and title (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in very deed the power and title were neuer ſo probable) bee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed and condemned both in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular and alſo Eccleſiaſticall Court of the <hi>Prince</hi> inuaded of open and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt Treaſon, and as a manifeſt Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour be deſeruedly put to death: for that it <hi>is open iniuſtice in the Pope</hi> (ſaith the
<hi>Authour</hi> of the <hi>Prelate</hi> and the <hi>Prince</hi>) <hi>to depriue a Prince of his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to which hee hath probable right, and withall poſſeſſion,</hi> and conſequently it is open Treaſon in the Subiect to take part with the <hi>Pope</hi> in that caſe againſt his rightfull
<hi>Prince.</hi> Theſe two things, I ſay, being duly conſidered, I thinke thoſe Subiects to bee ſtarke mad and ſenſleſſe, and to haue neither the feare of God nor Man before their eyes, that can be drawne to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue ſuch damnable practices, and conſequently neither the doctrine, grounds, and principles thereof: or
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:19923:96"/>to concurre with the <hi>Pope,</hi> to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, and diſpoſſeſſing of their So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne <hi>Prince,</hi> vnder pretence of a power, title, and clayme, which euen in ſpeculation, and abſtracting from practice, can bee at the moſt but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable. And ſo recommending to your prudent conſiderations this my ſerious and ſincere aduertiſement I make an end, and requeſt you euer to haue in minde, that which I ſaid in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning and cannot too often repeate: <hi>Feare God, Honour the King: Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to God and</hi> Caeſar (and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently to Popes and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces) <hi>that which is their due.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1.
<hi>Pet.</hi> 2. <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.</note>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="documents">
            <pb n="191" facs="tcp:19923:96"/>
            <div type="oath">
               <head>A Copie of the <hi>Oath</hi> of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, or the <hi>First Article,</hi> which the Lower Houſe of Parliament (wherein of 200.
<hi>Deputies</hi> for the <hi>Third Estates</hi> were but ſixe
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants</hi>) propounded to the <hi>French King,</hi> to haue eſtabliſhed for a <hi>fundamentall Law,</hi> in the generall
<hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the <hi>three Estates,</hi> hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at <hi>Paris</hi> in the yeere 1614.</head>
               <div type="text">
                  <head>The First Article of the Third Eſtates, <hi>taken out of a Booke intituled,</hi> Apologie de l'Article primier du Tiers Estat.
<hi>pag.</hi> 4.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>THat, to</hi> ſtay the courſe of that pernitious dostrine which ſome years ſince hath been broached, against Kings and Souereigne powers eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by God, by ſeditious ſpirits, who attend only to disturbe and ſubuert the ſame, Supplication may bee made to the King, that hee will cauſe to bee decreed in the Aſſemblie of theſe Eſtates for a fundamentall Law of the Realme, <hi>That,</hi> for as much as hee is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged Soueraigne in his Estate, nor
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:19923:97"/>houlding his Crowne but from God al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,
<hi>There</hi> is not any power on Earth whatſoeuer it be. Spirituall or Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, which hath any right ouer his Kingdome to depriue the ſacred perſons of our Kings, nor to diſpence or abſolue for any cauſe or pretence whatſoeuer, their Subiects from the Allegiance and obedience which they owe to them: <hi>That</hi> all the Subiects of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer they be, ſhall hould this Law for holy and true, as agreeable to the Word of God, without distinction, equiuocation, or limitation whatſoeuer:
<hi>Which</hi> ſhall be ſworne and ſigned by all the Deputies of the Estates, and from henceforth by all that haue Benefices or offices in the Kingdome, before they enter into poſſeſſion of their Benefices, and bee admitted into their Offices: <hi>That</hi> all Masters, Regents, Doctors, and Preachers ſhall bee bound to teach and publiſh, that the contrarie opinion,
<hi>to wit,</hi> that it is lawfull to kill and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our Kings, to riſe vp and rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst them, to ſhake of the yoake of their obedience, for any occaſion what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer, is impious, detestable, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:19923:97"/>to truth, and against the esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of the State of France, which dependeth immediatly on none but God:
<hi>That</hi> all Bookes which doe teach that falſe and peruerſe opinion, ſhall <hi>be</hi> held for ſeditious and to bee cenſured: <hi>All</hi> Strangers that ſhall write and publiſh it, for ſworne Enemies of the Crowne: <hi>All</hi> his Maieſties Subiects, <hi>that</hi> ſhall adhere vnto it, <hi>of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer they be,</hi> for Rebels, infringers of the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, and guiltie of Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in the higsteſt degree. <hi>And</hi> if there be found any booke, or Diſcourſe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by any Stranger Eccleſiastike, or of any other qualitie, that containeth any propoſition contrarie to the ſaid Law directly or indirectly, the Eccleſiastikes of the ſame Order eſtabliſhed in France ſhall be bound to anſwere them, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugne and contradict them inceſſantly, without reſpect, ambiguitie, or equiuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, vnder paine of being puniſhed with the ſame puniſhments as aboue ſaid, as abetters of the enemies of this State.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <pb n="194" facs="tcp:19923:98"/>
                  <p>This <hi>Article</hi> is in effect and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance all one with our <hi>new Oath</hi> of <hi>Allegiance,</hi> and the lawfulneſſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is manifeſt by the former Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; and how greatly <hi>Card. Peron</hi> was miſtaken in impugning the ſaid <hi>Article, Widdrington</hi> ſheweth both in his <hi>Anſwere</hi> to <hi>Fitz-herbert</hi> part. 3. chap. 11. num. 15. &amp; ſeq. and in his <hi>Diſcuſſion</hi> of the decree of the <hi>Late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran Councell</hi> againſt <hi>Leſſius</hi> part.
2. ſec. 9. and part. 3. ſec. 9.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="decree">
               <head>A Copie of the <hi>Arreſt,</hi> or Decree of the Parliament of <hi>Paris,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Card. Bellarmine</hi> his booke a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<hi>William Barclay</hi> is condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</head>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>Taken out of the <hi>Records</hi> of the Court of Parliament,
<date>the 26. of Nouember 1610.</date>
                  </head>
                  <p>THis preſent day the Kings Solici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, (<hi>Lewis Seruin</hi> the Kings Attorney making the Declaration, and <hi>Lewis Duret</hi> the Kings Aduocate ſubſcribing) aduertiſed the Court, that it was related to them, that ſome
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:19923:98"/>few daies ſince there hath beene divul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in this <hi>city</hi> of <hi>Paris</hi> a new booke en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled
<hi>Tractatus de poteſtate Summi Pontificis in temporalibus aduerſus Gulielmum Barclaium, Auctore Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berto S. R. E. Cardinale Bellarmino. Romae per Bartholomaeum Zannetti,</hi> printed this preſent yeere; out of which booke diuers perſons, ſome with a good intent, and others with an euill, haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vulged many things, which they haue collected from thence. And becauſe this Booke doth containe propoſitions, which are preiudiciall to the
<hi>Kings</hi> power and authoritie, and to the <hi>State of France,</hi> of whom the <hi>Author</hi> ſpeaketh in the ſame manner as of other Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Common-wealths, they haue through their care gotten a Copie there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which they hauing exactly read and examined, thought it their duties to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſe the <hi>Parliament</hi> of thoſe things, which are against the Powers eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed by God, and eſpecially against this Kingdome. Wherefore they haue obſerued, that <hi>Cardinall Bellarmine</hi> doth in this new Treatiſe not only teach thoſe propoſitions, which hee affirmed
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:19923:99"/>in his former books, as in that booke which is intituled, <hi>De Romani Ponti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficis Hierarchia</hi> written in the time of Pope <hi>Sixtus the V.</hi> and dedicated to the ſaid <hi>Pope,</hi> which he hath deuided into fiue books, in the laſt whereof hee maintaineth, that <hi>the</hi> Pope <hi>hath tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall power indirectly;</hi> But they alſo haue obſerued, that to this erroneous aſſertion others no leſſe falſe, and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding further are added in the places by them cited, which the <hi>Parliament,</hi> if it be ſo pleaſed, may behould. And
<hi>firſt</hi> the very Title is to be obſerued, wherein he giueth to the
<hi>Pope</hi> a power in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals. <hi>Then</hi> hee bringeth diuerſe au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities from the writings of Italians, French-men, Spaniards, Germans, Engliſh &amp; Scots, beginning with <hi>Pope Gregorie</hi> the <hi>VII.</hi> who liued in the yeere of our Lord 1073. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore to the end that fraud and deceit may for the ſafegard of true French men be preuented, the aforeſaid <hi>Attorney generall</hi> conſidering, that in regard of Conſcience, and the office which hee beareth in being the Kings <hi>Attorney,</hi> he is bound ſincerely to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge his duty, <hi>produceth Cardinall</hi>
                     <pb n="197" facs="tcp:19923:99"/>Bellarmines booke, which was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, when our King <hi>Henry</hi> the Great was liuing (in whoſe raigne none durſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenture to diuulge the ſame) but publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed forthwith as ſoone as he was dead, wherein hee hath noted diuers places, which the
<hi>Parliament</hi> may peruſe, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>pag.</hi> 37, 38. 57. 58. and 76. 77. to which may be added 160. 115. 116. And moreouer, he exhibiteth in written hand the requeſts, which the <hi>Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneys</hi> doe in the
<hi>Kings</hi> name demand; to wit, that by <hi>Decree</hi> of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> it be enacted, <hi>That none of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or condition ſoeuer, ſhall receiue, haue, keepe, print or vtter this booke of</hi> Bellarmine, <hi>vnder paine of Treaſon ordained againſt thoſe that ſhal tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe the ſame, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <opener>The matter being examined, The great Chamber, Criminall, and of the Edict being aſſembled.</opener>
                  <p>THe Court hath decreed and doth decree, that no perſon of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie or condition ſoeuer, vnder payne of Treaſon ordayned againſt thoſe that
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:19923:100"/>tranſgreſſe the ſame, doe receiue, keepe, communicate, print, vtter, or ſell the ſaid Booke, which contayneth that falſe and detestable propoſition, tending to the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion of ſupreme Powers eſtabliſhed and ordayned by God inciting Subiects to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, and derogating from the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Princes, animating to attempt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their liues and Crownes, and final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to diſturbe the publike peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Thoſe</hi> that haue Copies of the ſaide Booke, or know any that haue, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded forthwith to make it knowne to their Iudges, that, vpon the demand of the <hi>Kings Attorneys,</hi> Inquiſition bee made againſt the Crime, and thoſe that be guiltie be puniſhed accordingly.
<hi>It for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth</hi> vnder the ſame puniſhment Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, Profeſſours, and others, to treat, dispute, write, teach directly or indirectly in Schooles, Colledges, or other places, the ſaid propoſition.
<hi>The</hi> ſaid Court doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, that this <hi>Decree</hi> bee ſent, read, publiſhed, recorded, and obſerued accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the afore ſaid manner and forme in all the Benches ſubiect to the Iuriſdiction of this Court. <hi>The Subſtitutes</hi> to the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:19923:100"/>
                     <hi>Kings Attorney</hi> are commanded to cauſe forthwith this <hi>Decree</hi> to be put in execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and to aduertiſe the Court within a moneth of their diligence.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Made in <hi>Parliament</hi> vpon
<date>Friday 26. Nouemb. 1610.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed VOISIN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="observations">
                  <p>The <hi>decree</hi> being made, the <hi>Kings At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torneys</hi> were ſent for, to whom the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the <hi>Court</hi> was ſignified,
<hi>and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the</hi> Decree the ſaid Booke of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> was deliuered to their hands.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="decree">
               <div type="part">
                  <head>A Decree of the Court of Parliament made the 26. and executed the 27. of Iune 1614.</head>
                  <p>Against a Booke printed at Collen this preſent yeare, which is entituled, <hi>Franciſci Suarez Granatenſis Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:19923:101"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="129" facs="tcp:19923:101"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="200" facs="tcp:19923:102"/>Ieſu doctoris Theologi Defenſio fidei Catholicae &amp; Apoſtolicae aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Anglicanae ſectae errores,</hi> contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning many maximes and propoſitions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to the Soueraigne powers of Kings ordayned and establiſhed by God, the ſafetie of their perſons, the peace and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etneſſe of their States.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>The Place <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> where the Kings armes of France and Nauarre are ſet<lb/>At Paris,</dateline>
                     <signed>By F. Morel and P. Mettayer the Kings ordinarie Printers and Stationers
<date>1614.</date>
                     </signed> With his Maieſties Priuiledge.</closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <opener>Taken out of the Records of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</opener>
                  <p>The Court of the great Chamber, Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall, and of the
<hi>Edict</hi> aſſembled, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſeene the Booke printed at
<hi>Collen</hi> this preſent yeare, entituled, <hi>Franciſci Suarez Granatenſis Societatis Ieſu Doctoris Theologi Defenſio fidei Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicae &amp; Apoſtolicae aduerſus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicanae ſectae errores,</hi> contayning in the third Booke <hi>Chap.</hi> 23. <hi>p.</hi> 376. 79, 80, 82. <hi>Chap.</hi>
29. <hi>p.</hi> 410. 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Chap.</hi> 6.
<hi>pag.</hi>
                     <pb n="201" facs="tcp:19923:102"/>834. <hi>Chap.</hi> 8. <hi>pag.</hi> 844. and in other places many propoſitions contrarie to the Soueraigne powers of Kings ordained and eſtabliſhed by God, the peace and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their States, and that it is lawfull for their ſubiects and ſtrangers to attempt againſt their perſons: <hi>Concluſions of the Kings Attorney generall.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <opener>All which beeing conſidered;</opener>
                  <p>The ſaid <hi>Court</hi> hath declared and doth declare the propoſitions and max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes contayned in the ſaide Booke to bee ſcandalous and ſeditious, tending to the ſubuerſion of States, and to induce the ſubiects of Kings and ſoueraign Princes, and others, to attempt againſt their ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred perſons: and the diſcourſes, making mention of <hi>King Glodoueus</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip the Faire,</hi> to be falſe and ſlanderous:
<hi>Hath</hi> ordayned and doth ordayne the ſaid Booke of <hi>Suarez</hi> to bee burned in the Court of the Palace by the Executioner of high Iuſtice.
<hi>Hath</hi> made and doth make iniunctions and inhibitions to Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners and Printers, not to print, ſell, or vtter it, and to all perſons of what qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:19923:103"/>or condition ſoeuer, not to haue, co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie out, keepe, teach in Schooles nor in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, nor to dispute the ſaid max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>imes and propoſitions. <hi>It doth ordayne,</hi> that, according to the <hi>Arreſt</hi> made the 8. of Iune 1610. that the <hi>Decree</hi> of the Theologicall Facultie made the 4. of Iune the ſame yeare of renewing the doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Cenſure of the ſaid Facultie made in the yeare 1408. confirmed by the <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell</hi> of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> together with this preſent Arreſt <hi>or Decree,</hi> as alſo thoſe of the yeare 1578, and 95. bee read e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very yeare the 4. day of Iune as well in the ſaid Facultie, as in the Colledge of the Prieſt and Schollers of the Colledge of
<hi>Claremont,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">This Colledge of <hi>Claremont,</hi> is the <hi>Ieſuites</hi> Colledge.</note> and of the foure Mendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cants.
<hi>And</hi> that at the inſtance of the Kings <hi>Attorney generall</hi> informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be taken of the tranſgreſſions againſt the ſaid Arrests: and Inhibitions bee made againſt the copying out, hauing, and keeping the like bookes.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Made in <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                        <date>the 26. day of Iune 1614.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Signed VOISIN.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>
                     <hi>Moreouer,</hi> it is decreed, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:19923:103"/>
                     <hi>Ignace Armand</hi> Rectour in this Citie, <hi>Cotton, Fronton,</hi> and <hi>Sirmund,</hi> ſhall be ſent for the firſt day of the Court, and it ſhall be ſhewed them, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their declaration, and the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree</hi> of their <hi>Generall,</hi> made in the yeare 1610. the Booke of <hi>Suarez</hi> hath beene printed, and brought into this Citie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the authoritie of the <hi>King,</hi> the ſafetie of his Crowne and State: And it ſhall be enioyned them to cauſe their
<hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall</hi> to renew the ſaid <hi>Decree,</hi> and that it be publiſhed; and that they bring in the <hi>Act</hi> within ſixe moneths;
<hi>And</hi> that they prouide, that no bookes, contay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſuch damnable and pernicious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, bee hereafter made or publiſhed by any of their Societie: <hi>And</hi> that it bee inioyned them, to perſwade the people by their Preachers, the Doctrine contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to the ſaid propoſitions: Otherwiſe the <hi>Court</hi> wil proceed againſt the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, as againſt Traytors, and perturbers of the publique peace.</p>
                  <p>The aforeſaide Arreſt, <hi>or Decree,</hi> and what hath beene decreed, was pronounced in the preſence of the Fathers, <hi>Ignace Armand, Charles
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:19923:104"/>de la Tour,</hi> who came in place of Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Cotton</hi> abſent, <hi>Fronton du Duc,</hi> and <hi>Iames Sirmund:</hi> And the <hi>Arreſt</hi> was executed before the great Staires of the Pallace,
<date>the 27. of <hi>Iune,</hi> 1614.</date>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="decree">
               <head>A Copie of another <hi>Arreſt</hi> or Decree of the
<hi>Parliament</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> wherein the former doctrine of practizing the depoſition of Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Princes is condemned, and the former. Decrees, made againſt the Bookes of <hi>Card. Bellarmine,</hi> and
<hi>Suarez,</hi> are againe confirmed.</head>
               <head>An Arreſt <hi>or Decree</hi> of the Court of Parliament touching the Kings Soueraigntie in Temporals, and against the pernicious doctrine to attempt vpon the ſacred perſons of Kings.</head>
               <opener>The place <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> of the Kings Armes of <hi>France</hi> and
<hi>Nauarre.</hi> 
                  <dateline>At <hi>Paris.</hi>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>By <hi>F. Morel, P. Mettayer</hi> the Kings Ordinarie Printers and Stationers.
<date>1615.</date>
                  </signed>
               </opener>
               <opener>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:19923:104"/>Taken out of the <hi>Records of the</hi> Parliament.</opener>
               <p>WHereas the Kings <hi>Attourney Generall</hi> hath complayned to the <hi>Court,</hi> all the <hi>Chambers</hi> thereof being aſſembled, that albeit by many <hi>Arreſts</hi> or <hi>Decrees,</hi> heretofore made with great and mature deliberation, the <hi>Court</hi> hath confirmed the Maximes, which haue at all times beene held in <hi>France,</hi> and are naturally engrafted to the Crowne, <hi>That the King doth not acknowledge any Superiour in Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porals of his Kingdome but God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> And that, <hi>no power or autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie can rightfully releaſe his Subiect; from the Oath of Allegiance and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience which they owe to Him, nor ſuſpend, depriue, or depoſe him from his ſaid Kingdome:</hi> and much leſſe, <hi>to attempt, or to cauſe to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt either by publike or priuate authoritie againſt the ſacred perſons of Kings:</hi> Neuertheleſſe it hath beene aduertized, that by Diſcourſes, as well in priuate as in publike, many perſons, doe preſume to call in question the ſaid
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:19923:105"/>Maximes, to diſpute of them, and to hold them for problematike, from whence may ariſe very many inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences, which of neceſſitie must be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided against, and that ſpeedily: <hi>Hee</hi> (the ſaid <hi>Attourney</hi>) requesteth, that ſeeing the Court is aſſembled, all buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſet aſide, it will bee pleaſed to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, that the ſaid <hi>Decrees</hi> ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed, and againe publiſhed in all the Benches ſubiect to the Iuriſdiction of this Court; to the end that the mindes of all the Kings Subiects, of what quality or condition ſo euer, may be kept firme and aſſured concerning the ſaid Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, and Rules, and for the ſafetie of the <hi>Kings</hi> life, the publike peace and quietneſſe: With Inhibitions not to tranſgreſſe the ſame vnder the penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties ſet downe by the ſaid <hi>Arreſts.</hi> And that it be enioyned to all their Subſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes to cauſe the publication thereof to be made, and to certifie the Court with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a moneth, vnder paine to be depriued of their Offices.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Court,</hi> all the <hi>Chambers</hi> being aſſembled, hath ordayned and doth or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne, that the <hi>Arreſts</hi> of the 2. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemb.</hi>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:19923:105"/>1561. the 29. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 1594, the 7. of <hi>Ianuarie,</hi> and the 19. of <hi>Iuly</hi> 1595. the 27. of
<hi>May,</hi> the 8. of <hi>Iune,</hi> and the 26. of <hi>Nouemb.</hi> 1610. and the 26. of <hi>Iune</hi> 1614. ſhall bee kept, and obſerued according to their forme and tenour. Forbidding all perſons, of what qualitie or condition ſoeuer, to tranſgreſſe the ſame. And to this end they ſhall bee publiſhed in the <hi>Bayli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wikes, Stewardſhips,</hi> and other
<hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches</hi> ſubiect to this Court by the care of the
<hi>Subſtitutes</hi> to the <hi>Attourney Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall,</hi> who ſhall certifie the Court with in a moneth vnder paine to anſwere it at their perill.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Made in <hi>Parliament</hi>
                     <date>the ſecond of <hi>Ianuarie</hi> 1615.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Signed VOISIN.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusions">
               <p>The lawfulneſſe of all theſe <hi>Arreſts</hi> or
<hi>Decrees</hi> is manifeſt, partly by that which hath beene ſaid in this
<hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe,</hi> in the <hi>Fourth</hi> and <hi>Fift</hi> Obſeruati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in the <hi>Second, Third,</hi> and <hi>Fift</hi> Chapters, and more particularly by <hi>Widdrington</hi> in his <hi>Diſcuſſion</hi> of the
<hi>Decree</hi> of the <hi>Lateran</hi> Councell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:19923:106"/>
                  <hi>Leſſius, part.</hi> 2.
<hi>ſect.</hi> 9. for that Chriſtian Princes by vertue of their temporall power haue good &amp; full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie (according to the doctrine of
<hi>Ioannes Pariſienſis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ioh. Paris. <hi>de poteſt. Reg. &amp; Pap. c.</hi> 21. <hi>ad</hi> 37.</note>
                  <hi>Victoria,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Victoria <hi>Relect.</hi> 1. <hi>de poteſt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. ſec.</hi> 7. §. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaua propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitio.</note>
                  <hi> Sotus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Sotus <hi>in</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 29.
<hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>ar.</hi> 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Ba<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Bannes 2. 2. <hi>q</hi> 11. <hi>ar.</hi> 4. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>in fine.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Couerrunias,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Couerr. <hi>cap.</hi>
35. <hi>pract. queſt.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; which is grounded in manifeſt reaſon) to forbid the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning, teaching, and publiſhing, not only of hereticall erroneous, and falſe propoſitions, but alſo of all vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie doctrines and poſitions, be they neuer ſo probable, as the teaching and publiſhing of the ſame is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to the Crownes and liues of temporall Princes, and tendeth to the ſubuerſion of the State, and to the diſturbance of the publike peace in the Ciuill Common-wealth, whereof the <hi>Prince</hi> hath charge, and to puniſh with temporall puniſhments the tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, maintayners, and publiſhers, of ſuch dangerous and ſeditious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines.</p>
               <trailer>Haec omnia Eccleſiae Catholicae indicio ſubiecta ſunto.</trailer>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:19923:106"/>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label">Page</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Line</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Faults</cell>
                     <cell role="label">corrected.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>8.</cell>
                     <cell>13.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>would</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>would not.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>35.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>at firſt</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>at the firſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>71.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Authors</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Authour.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>87.</cell>
                     <cell>27.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>or vnlawfull</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>or lawfully.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>133.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bound</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>144.</cell>
                     <cell>16.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bound</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>bound.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>146.</cell>
                     <cell>10.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>dipoſe</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>diſpoſe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>187.</cell>
                     <cell>1.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>and to be</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>and be.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>191.</cell>
                     <cell>4.</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deputies</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Deputies.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
